<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>JohnMathews.eu - Technical/Data Science</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/feeds/technical/data-science.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://johnmathews.eu/</id><updated>2021-01-26T14:34:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Portfolio: Image Recognition</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/portfolio-image-recognition.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-26T14:34:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-26T14:34:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-26:/portfolio-image-recognition.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve created a &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/traffic.html"&gt;computer vision
model&lt;/a&gt; that recognizes
traffic lights. I’ve also created a page where the model can be queried and the
results shown. This needed to be a custom page and not a typical blog article,
so its hosted in the portfolio section
&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/traffic.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This page will redirect automatically if you view it in a browser, but for
those of you reading this using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt;, head on over and see the results!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Technical/Data Science"/></entry><entry><title>Coursera’s “Data Science Specialisation”</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/courseras-data-science-specialisation.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2016-08-01T13:30:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-08-01T13:30:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2016-08-01:/courseras-data-science-specialisation.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last year I decided to learn the tools required to work as a data
scientist. I was confident I already had the mathematical and analysis
skills I needed, but I wasn’t familiar with the tools of the trade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some googling brought me to Coursera, and the &lt;a href="https://www.coursera.org/specializations/jhu-data-science"&gt;Data Science
Specialisation&lt;/a&gt;
run by Johns Hopkins University.  It consists of 9 courses, and so far
I’ve completed five. If you do the courses in order then prior knowledge
isn’t required, and I think the courses strike a good balance of brevity
and depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main downside to me is that the courses exclusively use R (which is
popular in academia) and I would rather be using Python (which is more
popular in Industry).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each course lasts about 3 weeks and deals with a specific aspect of data
science, such as statistical inference or machine learning. Key concepts
and tools in each subject are explained and developed, and whilst it’s
not as thorough as a longer course would be, there is more than enough
material packed into the lectures, quizzes, assignments and projects to
apply to real applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve read that the second half of the specialisation is a lot more
technical than the first, so I’m looking forward to setting aside some
time, working through the assignments and acquiring some useful skills!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Technical/Data Science"/><category term="Coursera"/><category term="Data Science"/><category term="R"/></entry></feed>