<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>JohnMathews.eu - Non-technical</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/feed/non-technical.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://johnmathews.eu/</id><updated>2021-01-22T11:42:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Photographs</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/photographs.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-22T11:42:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-22T11:42:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-22:/photographs.html</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/polder.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Polder and windmill" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/polder.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/dog_walker.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="dog walker" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/dog_walker.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/stompetoren.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="stompetoren" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/stompetoren.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/geese_on_polder.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="geese_on_polder" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/geese_on_polder.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/bridges_and_gates.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="bridges and gates" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/bridges_and_gates.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/clouds_and_lake.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="clounds above a lake" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/clouds_and_lake.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/boat_in_mist.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="boat in the mist" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/boat_in_mist.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/path_to_knowwhere.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="path going nowhere" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/path_to_knowwhere.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/path_to_the_stars.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="path to the stars" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/path_to_the_stars.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/floating_huts.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="floating huts" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/floating_huts.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Photography"></category></entry><entry><title>Mental Models I Used To Use</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/mental-models-i-used-to-use.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-20T16:48:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T16:48:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-20:/mental-models-i-used-to-use.html</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The rules&lt;sup id="sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-1-back"&gt;&lt;a href="#sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-1" class="simple-footnote" title="or policies"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and mental models that helped me
succeed in one season or phase of life may not be the best for the next phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a list of a few mental models I remember being concious of in previous
years. Probably I’ve already forgotten some.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Always ask “why…”&lt;/em&gt;. Be obsessive about this. It’s going to make things
    harder for a while before things get easier. You’ll find difficult answers
    that you otherwise wouldn’t. If you’re only concerned with the present then
    its true that ignorance is bliss, but otherwise it’s a liability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;What if…”&lt;/em&gt; is another good question to ask a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adapt&lt;/em&gt; to the situation, don’t make it adapt to you if you have any
    choice. Be kind of like water, going around things and through the gaps.
    Look for the edges and the gaps, the parts that aren’t well known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Let people talk&lt;/em&gt; as much as they want to. Shut up and listen. If they
    mean you harm or don’t respect you then it’ll become more obvious the more
    they keep talking. If they mean you well or they’re saying something
    useful, you will benefit more from letting them talk more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inversion&lt;/em&gt; - it can be hard to know if you should do something, but how
    would you feel if you didn’t do it, or if it didn’t happen?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Regrets are inevitable&lt;/em&gt;, everyone has them. Same as making mistakes. Let
    your regrets be for things that you did do, and not what you didn’t do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are willing to try something, fail at it, and still be glad that you
    tried, then you should almost definitely do it. Commit to it and enjoy the
    experience! Don’t be scared, or at least, be scared &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; optimistic and
    happy&lt;sup id="sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-2-back"&gt;&lt;a href="#sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-2" class="simple-footnote" title="Courage isn’t the absence of fear. It’s being scared and doing     the right thing anyway."&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is beauty and luxury in being in such a bad spot that you are backed
    into a corner with seemingly no way out. Things become black and white,
    instead of shades of gray, and that will make priorities and options much
    clearer. You are likely to work very efficiently and effectively in this
    scenario, and you will learn important things about yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I’m older and I have responsibilities, I can’t ever let things
become so bad that a situation becomes black and white. I have to
navigate a world of grays. If they do become black and white, I’ll
already have a long list of failings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was younger, things were more fragile. My resources were smaller and
things could quickly flip from good to bad. Enjoy the few benefits that a
situation like that gives, because (hopefully) once its gone its gone for good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to solve a problem is to prevent it from occurring in the first
    place. Succeeding at this will bring its own challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take responsibility for things you are not responsible for, kind of. Do it
    deliberately and for your own benefit, but don’t forget that you are only
    pretending that it’s your responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do this, you will force yourself to understand a situation more
deeply and from other peoples perspectives. This will let you learn faster
and help you in future. Keep this at arms length though - it’s make-believe
and you need to be able to switch it on and off. It’s a toy for you to play
with. This seems to be what “extreme responsibility” is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think its important to have mental models that you’re comfortable with,
because it lets you make decisions quickly and consistently. But understand
that &lt;a href="https://fs.blog/2015/11/map-and-territory/"&gt;the map is not the
territory&lt;/a&gt;, and these are just
tools in a toolbox.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-1"&gt;or policies &lt;a href="#sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-1-back" class="simple-footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-2"&gt;Courage isn’t the absence of fear. It’s being scared and doing
    the right thing anyway. &lt;a href="#sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-2-back" class="simple-footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"></category></entry><entry><title>What’s So Different About Now</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/whats-so-different-about-now.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-20T14:44:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T14:44:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-20:/whats-so-different-about-now.html</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I think we are less aware of our ignorance than previous generations. It is
easy to implicitly assume that all useful information is available to us, and
that we are therefore more informed than we really&amp;nbsp;are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is because the internet has made information more accessible
and global air travel have made the world feel&amp;nbsp;smaller.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whilst an individual would hopefully never pretend to know everything, I think
its easy to assume that the right information exists and is being used by the
people to whom it is&amp;nbsp;relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the accessibility of all information has put us in a situation similar to
information scarcity. We still need to actively search for the information we
want, because the information that comes to us easily or for free is not equal
to what we find when we apply&amp;nbsp;effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can easily have so many short pieces of news or information that I am
always slightly overwhelmed. The pace of modern communications encourages me to
never slow down enough to form my own questions or frame my own arguments. I
can always find &lt;em&gt;an&lt;/em&gt; answer to my questions, but when was the last time I checked
that whoever gave it to me wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to profit from&amp;nbsp;it?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Career"></category></entry><entry><title>What Happens Next?</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/what-happens-next.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-20T14:05:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T14:05:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-20:/what-happens-next.html</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Predicting the future sounds like a tough problem, but we try to do it all the
time without realising&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We predict the future when we think about how risky or scary something is, or
when we think about what&amp;rsquo;s really going to change because of an announcement or
press release. We try to predict the future when we&amp;rsquo;re at the supermarket
checkouts and we try to pick the queue that will move the fastest. I always
seem to pick the wrong&amp;nbsp;one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There must be a million ways of trying to predicting the future but all the good
ones are models which reduce complexity and emphasise key considerations. One
of them could be comparing the influence of human nature and technology on the
outcome, and then comparing the event to what&amp;rsquo;s happened&amp;nbsp;before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human nature doesn&amp;rsquo;t change, so if something is driven by fear or greed then it
probably doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter what century it occurs in. Technology &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; change, and
if something is enabled or prevented due to technological progress then the
date is&amp;nbsp;important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is driving the scenario? Is it human nature or technology? Supermarket
checkouts are mostly manual and require a couple of adults to work together, so
human nature has a much bigger role on efficiency than tech. Young men will
stack and pack quickly, old women will be the opposite. What types of shopping
bags they have, or how they pay, or even how many items they&amp;rsquo;re buying, are
probably not going to lead you to the right&amp;nbsp;decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same probably works for getting through airport&amp;nbsp;security.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Career"></category></entry><entry><title>Financial Doom And Gloom</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/financial-doom-and-gloom.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-19T14:57:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-19T14:57:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-19:/financial-doom-and-gloom.html</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Financial crises seem to happen fairly regularly, so they shouldn’t be unexpected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But on the other hand, no-one seems particularly concerned about
any particular aspect of our current financial system. At the moment our
attention is controlled by other threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am concerned that a lot of money has been injected into the money supply but
we haven’t seen any inflation, and I am concerned that the price of stocks
is no longer driven by the business fundamentals of the company, but by macro
economics. It is a terrible time to be a value investor, and that is alarming.
Value investing should &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; be a decent way to make money, unless the
markets are broken. If the price of something doesn’t represent its value, then a correction is inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interest rates are really low at the moment, so if you have spare money and you
want to make it work for you then where do you put it? Not into a bank account,
because interest rates are low&lt;sup id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-1-back"&gt;&lt;a href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-1" class="simple-footnote" title="Why are interest rates low? Because confidence in the economy is low, so central bankers have to lower interest rates to make it 1. Cheaper for a business to borrow money to invest in their business and therefore easier for a business investments to be profitable, and 2. So that its more attractive for investors to use their capital to invest in a business  (which grows the economy) relative to depositing spare cash in a bank account (which is safer but a less efficient way to deploy capital). Interest rates affect the relative risk-reward ratios of different investment strategies"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and not into government debt, because
the yield is so low. It has to be stocks if you want the value of your
investments to increase meaningfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But everyone is doing this which drives the price up, and because their price
is increasing they excel even further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that the main reason for concern is super low interest rates and
massive increases in the money supply, but there are a couple of other factors
that are also contributing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easier than ever for retail investors to participate in the stock market,
and this seems like a good idea. Democratization. However if retail investors
have influence to effect prices, and they themselves can be manipulated or
influenced regarding what or when they buy or sell, then that is likely a new
kind of threat to financial stability. We’ve never seen social media combined
with quick, cheap investment services for amateurs before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Index funds are also more popular than ever&lt;sup id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-2-back"&gt;&lt;a href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-2" class="simple-footnote" title="Index Funds Are the New Kings of Wall Street"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; - the efficacy of index investing
relative to traditional funds that use stock pickers is very high over medium
or long time horizons because index funds are much cheaper. But if index
funds become too large then they end up influencing the market in predictable
and rigid ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Index funds cannot choose what they buy or how much they buy - they just track
the index. If a company’s stock crosses certain thresholds, their stock has
to be bought or sold. It seems like its possible to create feedback loops where
funds have to buy more of a rising stock, which increases its scarcity and
price, which then requires index funds to purchase more of the same stock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The amount of euros in existence in 2019 was 90% more than in
2010.&lt;sup id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-3-back"&gt;&lt;a href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-3" class="simple-footnote" title="statista"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
But inflation between 2010 and 2020 is
13%.&lt;sup id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-4-back"&gt;&lt;a href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-4" class="simple-footnote" title="in2013dollars.com"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Why is that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the price of something doesn’t represent its value, then a correction is inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-1"&gt;Why are interest rates low? Because
confidence in the economy is low, so central bankers have to lower interest
rates to make it 1. Cheaper for a business to borrow money to invest in their business and
therefore easier for a business investments to be profitable, and 2. So that
its more attractive for investors to use their capital to invest in a business 
(which grows the economy) relative to depositing spare cash in a bank account (which is safer but a less efficient way to deploy capital). Interest rates affect the relative risk-reward ratios of
different investment strategies &lt;a href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-1-back" class="simple-footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-2"&gt;&lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20210119144242/https://www.wsj.com/articles/index-funds-are-the-new-kings-of-wall-street-11568799004"&gt;Index Funds Are the New Kings of Wall Street&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-2-back" class="simple-footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-3"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/254220/value-of-euro-coins-in-circulation-since-2002/"&gt;statista&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-3-back" class="simple-footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-4"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.in2013dollars.com/europe/inflation/2010"&gt;in2013dollars.com&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-4-back" class="simple-footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Career"></category></entry><entry><title>Why I Want To Write Regularly</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/why-i-want-to-write-regularly.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-18T11:51:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-18T11:51:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-18:/why-i-want-to-write-regularly.html</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As you can see, I’ve recently started writing more frequently. I want to do
this because I often have thoughts which I’d like to explore and develop
further, but rarely do. I find writing hard because it forces me to organise my
thoughts and look at how substantial they really are, or aren’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is truth in the saying that “to know a thing you need to be able to teach
it &lt;sup id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1-back"&gt;&lt;a href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1" class="simple-footnote" title="wikipedia article, and some extenal validation"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
“, and writing well has several similarities to teaching. Can I really copy a
collection of thoughts from my head to yours?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember watching Inception and hearing that the most resilient parasite is
an idea. I think that’s mostly true, and the older I get the more I believe
that ideas matter&lt;sup id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2-back"&gt;&lt;a href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2" class="simple-footnote" title="and also, that asking the right question is more important than finding the right answer. I guess asking the right question is always necessary, but finding the right answer is only sometimes sufficient. Sometimes you can get the answer a bit wrong if you asked the right question, and still get enough benefits to avoid the problem."&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. They have so many
subtle consequences. They are the first
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domino_effect"&gt;dominos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t expect writing regularly to become a permanent habit - it doesn’t need
to be. But I do want to focus on it for a while so that I become significantly
better. It’s a skill that has too many benefits to be ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realised that the blogs I remembered most were focussed and unapologetic
about their priorities. Most of them have a lot of text and do not focus on
design. They make it easy to read text, and don’t spend time or attention on
header images or styling. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I redesigned this blog I had default settings that asked me to supply an
image for each post, and for a summary, and a suggested tweet. None of it was
necessary, and whilst they all tried to make the blog better they ended up
making it worse because they added complexity and distracted from the main thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These features are still there if I want to use them, but they are not set up
to be used by default anymore. They’ve been moved to the background, and if I
forget they exist then that is &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt; - it just shows they weren’t as important in
practice as I thought they’d be when I was &lt;a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/yak_shaving"&gt;Yak
Shaving&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/You_aren%27t_gonna_need_it"&gt;You Ain’t Gonna Need
It&lt;/a&gt;, mate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1"&gt;wikipedia
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Learning_by_teaching"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;, and some
&lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20210118112910/https://digest.bps.org.uk/2018/05/04/learning-by-teaching-others-is-extremely-effective-a-new-study-tested-a-key-reason-why/"&gt;extenal
validation&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1-back" class="simple-footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2"&gt;and also, that asking the right question is more
important than finding the right answer. I guess asking the right question is
always necessary, but finding the right answer is only sometimes &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Necessity_and_sufficiency"&gt;sufficient&lt;/a&gt;.
Sometimes you can get the answer a bit wrong if you asked the right question,
and still get enough benefits to avoid the problem. &lt;a href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2-back" class="simple-footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"></category></entry><entry><title>Using RSS</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/using-rss.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-14T16:52:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-14T16:52:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-14:/using-rss.html</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="google-reader"&gt;Google&amp;nbsp;Reader&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; is a very effective way of having good quality information
come to you. Back in 2008, I used to use Google Reader to subscribe to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt;
feeds. I was an aspiring photographer back then and I remember being subscribed
to around 80 blogs. Each day I&amp;rsquo;d read articles from whoever had posted
something new, without needing to visit their websites or remember who they are
or that I&amp;rsquo;d subscribed to their&amp;nbsp;blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="social-media"&gt;Social&amp;nbsp;Media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years later Google Reader was closed down, presumably because using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt;
didn&amp;rsquo;t fit with Googles advertising model. I was unaware of it at the time but
I imaging it sent shockwaves  through blogging communities and probably upended
many businesses. I mostly stopped reading&amp;nbsp;blogs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook was growing fast, Instagram felt new and exciting, and content was
moving onto &amp;lsquo;platforms&amp;rsquo;, or into walled gardens. And as they kept on growing
the average quality of the content&amp;nbsp;decreased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter is like this now I think. There are some real diamonds to be found from
time to time, but there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of mud too. Mostly its just mud, but the
occasional diamond can have outsized&amp;nbsp;benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; isn&amp;rsquo;t like this. I choose the contents of my &amp;lsquo;news feed&amp;rsquo;, and
each article can be much longer than a Tweet, or a caption to a photo, or a
status update. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to write well and to create an interesting or useful blog
post, and that makes it harder to dilute quality with entertaining
distractions. I have complete control about what content I see, and I can
change it whenever I want. The process is designed around&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="reeder5"&gt;Reeder5&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used &lt;code&gt;netNewsWire&lt;/code&gt; for a few weeks, but it couldn&amp;rsquo;t sync between my laptop
and phone, so I bought &lt;code&gt;Reeder 5&lt;/code&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s got a few unusual design patterns, but
 it works well and has all the features I want. I&amp;rsquo;ve been unsubscribing from
 email newsletters and subscribing to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; feed&amp;nbsp;instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It keeps my inbox quieter, and it feels good to have a &amp;lsquo;separation of
 concerns&amp;rsquo;. It makes it easier to read interesting content without being&amp;nbsp;distracted.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"></category></entry><entry><title>Why Start Talking About Faith In Jesus?</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/faith-in-jesus.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-05T18:24:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-05T18:24:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-05:/faith-in-jesus.html</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="start-with-happiness"&gt;Start with happiness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems to me that I am much happier as a Christian than I would be if I
weren’t. By “being a Christian” I mean following Jesus - trying my best to act,
think and speak like he want’s me to because I’m grateful that he did what I
believe he did. I believe he died for my sins and is now alive, having been
miraculously resurrected by his father&lt;sup id="sf-faith-in-jesus-1-back"&gt;&lt;a href="#sf-faith-in-jesus-1" class="simple-footnote" title="And many other things also."&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
(who is now my father too).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not just an intellectual exercise. I believe that Jesus is alive because I
seem to have experienced his companionship and intervention in my day-to-day
life. This is unusual, mind boggling, and makes things significantly more
complicated than if I thought he were dead. Nonetheless it seems to be true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not like I see supernatural intervention every day or anything, but there
have been various times - too many to discard - when my prayers have been
answered in practical ways (I’ll leave out the intangible for now) that have
surprised me and given me a lot of respect for the risen Jesus doing what its
said he’d do in the bible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="obvious-answers"&gt;Obvious answers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was this time I was in Yemen trying to get back to my room across town,
at night and during a storm. I was lost and couldn’t read Arabic to understand
which bus to get. So I prayed, and two buses later I got off at the right stop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another example, I was getting a haircut in Liverpool Street Station in London,
and as I was sitting in the chair someone took my work bag. When I came to pay,
I realised my laptop and wallet had gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trying to find a stolen bag in central London feels ridiculous. Even so, I spent
a few hours wondering around the alleys and parks looking for it, and I
resigned myself to some awkward conversations and using most of my next salary
to replace the stolen computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To my surprise, my parents-in-law prayed about it and were really confident it
would come back to me, which seemed super unlikely. A few days later I received
a call from an office worker in the Gherkin building - my bag was under his
desk and he wanted to know if I’d like to collect it. I guess I’ll try not to
make the same mistake twice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other example I tend to remember happened not long after I’d first moved to
Vienna. I was feeling lonely and isolated and I was wondering how on earth I
was going to find some sort of normal that was healthy and sustainable. Try as
I might, I wasn’t enjoying things at all and was feeling stressed and
overwhelmed. I remember walking up this steep hill in the 18th district towards
my office, and repeatedly praying this really simple prayer ‘God, please help,
please help, please help..’. It was that simple because I couldn’t think of
anything more useful to say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing dramatic happened that day, or even that week as far as I can remember.
But when I look back, it was a turning point when things started getting better
instead of worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suppose you can call this last example an intangible answer to prayer. Maybe
it is, but I think anyone whose grappled with overwhelming loneliness or panic
would say that the emotions become all too tangible at times. Being in a
different emotional state seemed to make a tangible difference to just about
every area of life. Eating, productivity at work, relationships with friends
and colleagues, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is only the beginning of why I think Jesus is alive and why I think
Christianity is a real and living faith. It’s not primarily a tradition, a worldview or a set of rules and ideals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christianity is a relationship with Jesus. He did lots of amazing things that
have let me have a very practical relationship with him. It’s an almost
unbelievable premise from which to live a life. It has so many implications.
And it holds up to scrutiny and my experiences bear it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-write-this"&gt;Why write this?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite Jesus’ incredible works and their implications, modern Christianity
seems to be in a really confused and ineffective state. Ideas and thoughts
about Christianity-the-faith have become mixed up with cultural christianity,
or christian politics and traditions. These are each different things, and unless we distinguish between them with the words we use, we are going to find it hard to think and communicate clearly. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suspect that we are in a negative cycle of imprecise thinking leading to imprecise articulation, which leads to further imprecise thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless we can talk and think about one thing at a time, atomically&lt;sup id="sf-faith-in-jesus-2-back"&gt;&lt;a href="#sf-faith-in-jesus-2" class="simple-footnote" title="from first principals"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; if necessary, we take on the additional risks of
reaching the wrong conclusions personally, or arguing with others due to
misunderstandings rather than actual disagreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should try to create a more precise vocabulary to navigate our Christian
lives, so that we can think clearly about the experiences and questions we have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imprecise thinking is frustrating, and conversations are less effective when
there’s an increased risk of disagreement or misunderstanding what someone
else means. This makes it harder to talk about our faith, which makes talking
less common, and this creates room for misunderstanding or apathy, or missed
opportunities, or sadness.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-faith-in-jesus-1"&gt;And many other things also. &lt;a href="#sf-faith-in-jesus-1-back" class="simple-footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-faith-in-jesus-2"&gt;from
first principals &lt;a href="#sf-faith-in-jesus-2-back" class="simple-footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/christianity"></category></entry><entry><title>Product-Led Growth</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/product-led-growth.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-08T12:59:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-08T12:59:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-12-08:/product-led-growth.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My notes on &amp;ldquo;Product-Led Growth&amp;rdquo; by Wes&amp;nbsp;Bush&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="part-1-design-your-strategy"&gt;Part 1: Design your&amp;nbsp;strategy&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-1-why-is-product-led-growth-of-rising-importance"&gt;Chapter 1: Why is product-led growth of rising&amp;nbsp;importance?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product-Led Growth is a go-to-market (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt;) strategy that relies on using your product as the main vehicle to acquire, activate and retain&amp;nbsp;customers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product-Led Growth (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLG&lt;/span&gt;) means that every team influences the product:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marketing - how can our products generate a demand&amp;nbsp;fly-wheel?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sales - how can we use the product to qualify our prospects for&amp;nbsp;us?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customer Success - how can we create a product that helps customers become
  successful beyond our&amp;nbsp;dreams?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By having every team focussed on the product, you create a culture that is built around enduring customer&amp;nbsp;value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By leading with the product throughout the org, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PL&lt;/span&gt; companies get&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shorter sales&amp;nbsp;cycles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lower Customer Acquisition Costs&amp;nbsp;(CACs)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;higher Revenue Per Employee (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPE&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; strategy is an action plan that specifies how a company will reach target customers and achieve a competitive&amp;nbsp;advantage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In order to select a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt;, you first need to understand:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;market&amp;nbsp;conditions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;competitive&amp;nbsp;positioning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ideal&amp;nbsp;customer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;product&amp;nbsp;offering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowing these elements will help you choose the correct &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; that will
   acquire, retain and grow you customer base in the most capital-efficient&amp;nbsp;way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sales-led-go-to-market-strategies"&gt;Sales-Led Go-To-Market&amp;nbsp;Strategies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Profit Centers: Sales, Marketing, Customer&amp;nbsp;Success&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cost Centers: Engineering,&amp;nbsp;Product&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advantages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Annual Contract Value (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACV&lt;/span&gt;) can be very&amp;nbsp;high&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enterprise first solutions that are very complex and therefore need a high-touch sales&amp;nbsp;model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the Total Addressable Market (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;TAM&lt;/span&gt;) is very small, because your market is super niche, you can quite easily talk to almost all market participants. (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLG&lt;/span&gt; is built for large&amp;nbsp;TAMs)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s great for new categories of product where education is required, because you need to change how people approach a problem. This takes time and requires&amp;nbsp;education.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is turn requires that you understand your customers pain points, objections, core problems. If you jump to quickly a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLG&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; strategy then you risk a high church rate because you haven&amp;rsquo;t understood or educated
your customers well&amp;nbsp;enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disadvantages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sales cycles are very&amp;nbsp;long&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Life Time Value (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;LTV&lt;/span&gt;) must be high enough to recoup the investment in
  &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAC&lt;/span&gt;. This often requires charging the customer a premium. This premium
  price isn&amp;rsquo;t because the product is amazing, or more valuable to the
  customer, but because the customer acquisition model is more&amp;nbsp;expensive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you use a Sales-Led &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt;, you need to watch out for competitors who can
  sell more efficiently, or have a more efficient Customer Acquisition
  Model. They can steal your market share by offering the same product with
  at a lower&amp;nbsp;price.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customer Acquisition methods are super leaky. Most marketing-qualified leads (MQLs) never result in a closed deal, this is partly because:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it encourages markets to gate content in order to hit their &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MQL&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;goals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it focusses on content consumption as a leading indicator of intent.
  (but reading a white-paper or brochure doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean I&amp;rsquo;m going to buy
  the&amp;nbsp;thing).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the entire process rewards creating friction in the buying&amp;nbsp;process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consequently, there is often a disconnect between marketing and&amp;nbsp;sales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="product-led-go-to-market-strategies"&gt;Product-Led Go-To-Market&amp;nbsp;Strategies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Switching from Sales-Led &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; to Product-Led &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; creates a defensive&amp;nbsp;moat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A product led marketing team asks &amp;ldquo;How can we use the product to qualify our prospects for&amp;nbsp;us?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A product led customer success team asks &amp;ldquo;How can we create a product that helps customers be successful without our&amp;nbsp;help?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A product-led engineering team asks &amp;ldquo;How can we create a product with a quick&amp;nbsp;time-to-value?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Growth is much faster, because:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you need fewer resources to&amp;nbsp;scale,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the top of the customer funnel is much&amp;nbsp;wider.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAC&lt;/span&gt; is much&amp;nbsp;lower&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Higher &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPE&lt;/span&gt; (revenue per&amp;nbsp;employee)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User experience is&amp;nbsp;better&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-2-free-freemium-or-demo"&gt;Chapter 2 - Free, Freemium or&amp;nbsp;Demo&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MOAT&lt;/span&gt; framework to pick the right &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;strategy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt;arket Strategy - Dominant? Disruptive?&amp;nbsp;Differentiated?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;O&lt;/strong&gt;cean Conditions - Blue or&amp;nbsp;Red?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;udience - Do you have a top-down or bottom-up marketing&amp;nbsp;strategy?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;ime to Value - How much time do you need for a customer to
  experience the&amp;nbsp;value?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dominant - Do it better than the competition &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; charge a lower&amp;nbsp;price&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is your &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TAM&lt;/span&gt; big&amp;nbsp;enough?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does your product solve a specific job significantly better and at lower cost than anyone else on the&amp;nbsp;market?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can the user realize significant ongoing value quickly with little or no&amp;nbsp;help?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you want to be the undisputed market&amp;nbsp;leader?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Differentiated - Pick and win a fight against an industry giant&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Main line of defense against the giant is&amp;nbsp;specialization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on an underserved&amp;nbsp;niche&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do a specific job better than the competition but charge significantly&amp;nbsp;more&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is not a one-size-fits-all&amp;nbsp;model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free trials and demos work well&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because its specialized, combining freemium with quick time-to-value is&amp;nbsp;difficult&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Main competitive advantage is how you solve your customers&amp;nbsp;problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does your market have underserved&amp;nbsp;customers?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TAM&lt;/span&gt; big&amp;nbsp;enough?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;is the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACV&lt;/span&gt; high&amp;nbsp;enough?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Could prospects experience a Magic Moment during a free&amp;nbsp;trial?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disruptive - Charge less for an inferior product (e.g. Canva, Google docs)&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build a simpler product that solves a specific pain point, and because its simpler, its faster, you can charge less, and its more appropriate to some over-served or priced-out&amp;nbsp;customers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a scaled-down&amp;nbsp;product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Costs must be&amp;nbsp;low&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product must be easy to&amp;nbsp;use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TAM&lt;/span&gt; large&amp;nbsp;enough?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can on-boarding be completely&amp;nbsp;self-service?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freemium model&amp;nbsp;thrives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-3-red-ocean-or-blue-ocean-markets"&gt;Chapter 3 - Red-Ocean or Blue-Ocean&amp;nbsp;markets?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Red-ocean companies try to outperform their rivals in order to grab a larger share of the existing market. As the market gets crowded, opportunity for profit and growth reduces. Products become commodities. Cut-throat competition turns the waters&amp;nbsp;red.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue-ocean companies access untapped market space and create demand. They have opportunity for highly profitable growth. Competition is irrelevant. Create and capture new&amp;nbsp;demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some markets will be red-ocean, but a particular niche within it will be blue&amp;nbsp;ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue Oceans require educating the customer to create the demand. This is high-touch, and often a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; strategy isn&amp;rsquo;t going to work. It needs to be sales-led in order to educate the customer enough. But if Time-To-Value (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;TTV&lt;/span&gt;) is short then &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLG&lt;/span&gt; could be&amp;nbsp;great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Red Oceans need big wide funnels in order to compete, and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; strategies work great. They&amp;rsquo;re defensible, keep costs low and make sales cycles&amp;nbsp;short.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-4-top-down-or-bottom-up-selling-strategy"&gt;Chapter 4 - Top-Down or Bottom-Up selling&amp;nbsp;strategy?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLG&lt;/span&gt; works for&amp;nbsp;bottom-up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High touch sales-led strategies work for Top-Down enterprise sales strategies, where the product is super complex and the sales cyccle is very&amp;nbsp;long.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top-Down (Sales team is the growth&amp;nbsp;engine):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Additional&amp;nbsp;Services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lower customer&amp;nbsp;churn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Poor revenue&amp;nbsp;distribution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Long sales&amp;nbsp;cycles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free Trial sometimes&amp;nbsp;works&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bottom-Up (Product is the growth&amp;nbsp;engine):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wider&amp;nbsp;top-of-funnel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Predictable sales&amp;nbsp;figures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revenue&amp;nbsp;diversity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scalable&amp;nbsp;fast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small contracts&amp;nbsp;only&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;non-paying&amp;nbsp;customers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;expertise&amp;nbsp;shortage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;upfront investment as non-paying customers drain&amp;nbsp;resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freemium&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free-Trial&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-5-time-to-value"&gt;Chapter 5 -&amp;nbsp;Time-to-Value&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much time until you deliver on your promise to&amp;nbsp;prospects?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much time until the product sells&amp;nbsp;itself?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; strategies require fast&amp;nbsp;time-to-value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rank your uses across 2 dimensions and group into 4 quadrants. The dimensions are Ability (low - high) and Motivation (low - high)&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low Motivation - Low Ability = Mission&amp;nbsp;Impossible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High Motivation - Low Ability =&amp;nbsp;Rookie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low Motivation - High Ability =&amp;nbsp;Veteran&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High Motivation - High Ability =&amp;nbsp;Spoiled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Figure out your top two quadrants. Unless all your users are Spoiled, you need to decrease&amp;nbsp;Time-To-Value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How motivated are your&amp;nbsp;users?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is your product easy for your target audience to&amp;nbsp;use?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can users experience the core value (magic moment?) without&amp;nbsp;hand-holding?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="part-2-build-your-foundation"&gt;Part 2 - Build Your&amp;nbsp;Foundation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-7-build-a-product-led-foundation"&gt;Chapter 7 - Build a product-led&amp;nbsp;foundation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A positive feedback&amp;nbsp;loop:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understand&lt;/strong&gt; your&amp;nbsp;value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Communicate&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deliver&lt;/strong&gt; on your&amp;nbsp;promise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-8-understand-your-value"&gt;Chapter 8 - Understand your&amp;nbsp;value&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re selling live-chat software, you&amp;rsquo;re not really selling live-chat software, you are selling a new and better way to acquire&amp;nbsp;customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are selling the outcome, the result, the&amp;nbsp;why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pain makes us want to change so that we can avoid or prevent the pain&amp;nbsp;altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pain is product&amp;nbsp;agnostic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three reasons why people buy a&amp;nbsp;product:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Functional Outcome - the core task that needs to get&amp;nbsp;done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emotional Outcome - how a customer wants to feel or avoid feeling as a result of the functional&amp;nbsp;outcome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social Outcome - how a customer wants to be perceived by others by using
   your&amp;nbsp;product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In every software, there are usage patterns that point towards to core outcomes that are most important to&amp;nbsp;customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest differences between sales-led and product-led companies is that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SL&lt;/span&gt; companies monitor usage patters to see if users are accomplishing meaningful outcomes. These outcomes are referred to as &lt;strong&gt;value-metrics&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A value-metric is the way you measure value exchange in your product&lt;/strong&gt;. They are the linchpin to successful execution of a product-led &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; strategy because you are aligning your revenue model directly with your customer acquisition model. Because your value metrics play a vital role in how you price your product, set up your monitoring, and build your&amp;nbsp;team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Value metrics could&amp;nbsp;be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for Vimeo, number of videos uploaded by the&amp;nbsp;user.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for Slack, number of messages sent by the&amp;nbsp;user&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for PayPal, amount of revenue generated by the user&amp;nbsp;(processed?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;strong&gt;functional&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;outcome based&lt;/strong&gt; value metrics. Functional value metrics are &amp;ldquo;per user&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;per 100 videos&amp;rdquo;. Pricing scales around functions of usage. Outcome based value metrics charge based on the outcome, e.g. how many views a video received, or how much money a customer made when using your payment process&amp;nbsp;method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many SaaS companies rely on feature differentiation as a way to justify higher prices, but this produces higher&amp;nbsp;churn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Value metrics outperform feature differentiation with upto 75% less&amp;nbsp;churn&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome based value metrics reduce church by an additional 40%.&amp;nbsp;Apparently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A good value metric is easy for a customer to understand. They need to immediately understand what they&amp;rsquo;re paying for and where they fit in your packing/pricing structure. If you&amp;rsquo;re in an established market, it makes senses to look at what the competition&amp;nbsp;charges.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A good value metric is aligned with the value that the customer receives through the product. Consider the low-level components of your high-level outcome. E.g. what low level actions are necessary to get the end result?  Sending lots of messages? Meeting lots of people? Finding lots of&amp;nbsp;things?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A good value metric grows with your customers usage of the valuable outcome. If customers get incredible value from the product, charge them more because the product is worth it. Also, if they aren&amp;rsquo;t getting much value from the product, charge them&amp;nbsp;less.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t do user based pricing if you want to get lots of users - its a conflict of&amp;nbsp;interests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re small, you can try different pricing strategies and iterate to&amp;nbsp;success.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask&amp;nbsp;yourself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do my best customers&amp;nbsp;do?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do my best customers not&amp;nbsp;do?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What features did my best customers try first when they were&amp;nbsp;on-boarding?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the similarities along my best customers that led to&amp;nbsp;success?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For churned customers, what were the main differences between them and the
   best customers? Were they in the ideal audience? Why did they church? What
   did they do or not do that good customers&amp;nbsp;didn&amp;rsquo;t?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"></category><category term="marketing"></category><category term="startups"></category></entry><entry><title>The Mom Test</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/mom-test.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-04T16:07:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-04T16:07:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-12-04:/mom-test.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My notes on &amp;ldquo;The Mom Test&amp;rdquo; by Rob&amp;nbsp;Fitzpatrick&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s called the Mom Test because it leads to questions that even your mom couldn&amp;rsquo;t lie to you&amp;nbsp;about&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="overview"&gt;Overview:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask good&amp;nbsp;questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid bad&amp;nbsp;data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep it&amp;nbsp;casual&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push for commitment and&amp;nbsp;advancement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frame the meeting&amp;nbsp;well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on the right, tight, customer&amp;nbsp;segment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prep well, take good notes, review your&amp;nbsp;notes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-1-opinions-are-worthless-you-want-objective-facts-about-what-happened-in-the-past"&gt;Chapter 1 - Opinions are worthless, you want objective facts about what happened in the&amp;nbsp;past&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find out if people care about your idea by never mentioning&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Forcing yourself not to mention your idea will force you to ask better&amp;nbsp;questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure your questions pass the mom test:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Talk about their lives, not your idea Ask about specifics in the&amp;nbsp;past,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;not hypotheticals Spend most of your time listening, not&amp;nbsp;talking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule of thumb: Anything involving the future is an overly optimistic&amp;nbsp;lie&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-2-avoid-bad-data-compliments-fluff-hypotheticals-ideas"&gt;Chapter 2 - Avoid bad data - Compliments, Fluff, Hypotheticals,&amp;nbsp;Ideas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You aren&amp;rsquo;t allowed to tell them what their problem is, and they aren&amp;rsquo;t allowed
to tell you what to&amp;nbsp;build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-3-ask-the-important-questions"&gt;Chapter 3 - Ask the Important&amp;nbsp;Questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should be terrified of at least one of the questions you ask in each&amp;nbsp;conversation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search out the scary questions you&amp;rsquo;ve been unintentionally avoiding. What&amp;rsquo;s the worst thing a prospect could say? What&amp;rsquo;s the scariest question you could&amp;nbsp;ask?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A good way to find scary questions is to imagine that your company has failed and then to ask&amp;nbsp;why.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you get an unexpected answer to one of your questions and it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have any effect on what you&amp;rsquo;re going to do, then was it really worth asking&amp;nbsp;it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;General advice for hard things including asking hard questions - imagine you were delegating the task, what would you tel the person to do? That&amp;rsquo;s&amp;nbsp;you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can ask about&amp;nbsp;money.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Love bad news - if you find out that your idea is fundamentally flawed you&amp;rsquo;ve just saved a tonne of time and energy and money. Move on. It&amp;rsquo;s getting you closer to the&amp;nbsp;truth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bad news isn&amp;rsquo;t the result of an opinion. No one knows if your idea will work, only the market knows. Opinions don&amp;rsquo;t&amp;nbsp;count.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lukewarm response to your idea can be a great conversation, because you realise that your idea isn&amp;rsquo;t a great idea. Lukewarm means they don&amp;rsquo;t care enough to buy the first (worst) version before it&amp;rsquo;s&amp;nbsp;ready.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look before you zoom. Don&amp;rsquo;t focus on details too soon, you need to understand the big picture&amp;nbsp;first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have &lt;strong&gt;product risk&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;customer risk&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product risk&lt;/strong&gt; - can I build it and grow&amp;nbsp;it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Customer risk&lt;/strong&gt; - is there a big enough group of people who are going to buy&amp;nbsp;it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pre-plan a list of the 3 most important questions (including a scary one) before every meeting or conversation. Be ready with these. They should change from week to week. As you get good quality answers to existing questions you can bring in new&amp;nbsp;questions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-4-keep-it-casual-structure-problem-solution-sales"&gt;Chapter 4 - Keep it casual, Structure: Problem -&amp;gt; Solution -&amp;gt;&amp;nbsp;Sales&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Normally you would have 3 meetings with a client in order to make a big sale. This lets you do each stage really well without blurring the data:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify your prospect&amp;rsquo;s&amp;nbsp;problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explain your&amp;nbsp;solution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sell the&amp;nbsp;solution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identifying a problem doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be a meeting, keep it casual and you will get more honest feedback much faster. It works better as a&amp;nbsp;chat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It take 5 minutes (max) to identify if a problem exists and is&amp;nbsp;important&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Give as little info as possible about your idea whilst still nudging the conversation&amp;nbsp;along&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-5-the-currencies-of-conversation-time-reputation-money"&gt;Chapter 5 - The currencies of conversation - Time, Reputation,&amp;nbsp;Money&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In early stage sales, the main goal is learning. Money is a&amp;nbsp;side-effect.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If someone is willing to risk reputation, or spend time or money on your idea, then you can believe that they&amp;rsquo;re&amp;nbsp;interested.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hearing a compliment is still useful - it means they&amp;rsquo;re trying to get rid of&amp;nbsp;you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If its a bad meeting, push for a commitment of some kind. Ask them to spend time, reputation or money and you&amp;rsquo;ll see what they really&amp;nbsp;think.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If they aren&amp;rsquo;t excited (not just interested, but in pain and excited for your solution) then you need to find that out &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ASAP&lt;/span&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s still a good meeting if you can discover&amp;nbsp;this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lead isn&amp;rsquo;t a real lead until you&amp;rsquo;ve given them a concrete chance to reject&amp;nbsp;you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask learning questions by using the Mom Test, then confirm by selling&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need &lt;strong&gt;crazy customers&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They have a painful and expensive&amp;nbsp;problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They know they have a painful and expensive&amp;nbsp;problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They have the money to pay you to solve&amp;nbsp;it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They already have their own bad solution to this terrible problem, and
  yours is clearly&amp;nbsp;better&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A crazy customer doesn&amp;rsquo;t say &amp;ldquo;yeah that&amp;rsquo;s great, I&amp;rsquo;m really interested, let me know when its ready&amp;rdquo;. They say &amp;ldquo;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AHHH&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;THIS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;THE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WORST&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PART&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OF&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MY&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LIFE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AND&lt;/span&gt; I &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WILL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PAY&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;YOU&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RIGHT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NOW&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TO&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FIX&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IT&lt;/span&gt;!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A crazy customer will front you the money when all you have is a prototype made of&amp;nbsp;duct-tape&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A crazy customer is the person reading you blog, searching for workarounds, when you haven&amp;rsquo;t spent loads of marketing and lead&amp;nbsp;generation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep a crazy customer close - they&amp;rsquo;ll stick with you when times are&amp;nbsp;tough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-6-finding-good-conversations"&gt;Chapter 6 - Finding good&amp;nbsp;conversations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;eep having conversations until you stop hearing new&amp;nbsp;stuff&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If it&amp;rsquo;s a topic you both care about, find an excuse. You&amp;rsquo;ll both enjoy the chat. You don&amp;rsquo;t need to mention your idea if it breaks the&amp;nbsp;premise.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Warm introductions are the ideal way to start a new conversation. 6 degrees of freedom in the world, so find someone who knows someone who knows&amp;nbsp;someone..&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cold calls - LinkedIn,&amp;nbsp;maybe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Serendipity - be prepared, be&amp;nbsp;bold&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a good excuse -&amp;nbsp;hustle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Landing pages so that googling the problems brings them to&amp;nbsp;you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organise an event - bring the businesses together for an event. You&amp;rsquo;ll be considered an expert cos you&amp;rsquo;re facilitating&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Become a subject matter&amp;nbsp;expert&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaking and teaching engagements - you get to have strong opinions, and you&amp;rsquo;ll be&amp;nbsp;respected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vision -&amp;gt; Framing -&amp;gt; Weakness -&amp;gt; Pedestal -&amp;gt;&amp;nbsp;Ask&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-7-choosing-you-customers"&gt;Chapter 7 - Choosing you&amp;nbsp;customers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Startups don&amp;rsquo;t starve, they drown. In options, choices, ideas. You get&amp;nbsp;overwhelmed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose a good customer segment, focus on it, and don&amp;rsquo;t get&amp;nbsp;distracted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the beginning:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google - PhD&amp;nbsp;students&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PayPal -&amp;nbsp;eBay&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evernote - Moms with recipes,&amp;nbsp;etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It will look obvious with hindsight, probably not so obvious before you&amp;rsquo;ve figured it out&amp;nbsp;though.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you can&amp;rsquo;t get a consistent answer to a question, maybe you&amp;rsquo;re speaking to different&amp;nbsp;segments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you aren&amp;rsquo;t finding &lt;strong&gt;consistent problems and goals&lt;/strong&gt; then you don&amp;rsquo;t have a specific enough customer segment&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Within the group, which type of person would want it the&amp;nbsp;most?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would everyone within the group want to buy/use it? Or only&amp;nbsp;some?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why does the subset want&amp;nbsp;it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does everyone in the group have the same&amp;nbsp;motivation?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What other motivations are&amp;nbsp;there?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who else (outside the group) have these&amp;nbsp;motivations?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go for &lt;strong&gt;Who-Where&lt;/strong&gt; pairs of segments. &amp;ldquo;Finance professionals who run&amp;nbsp;marathons&amp;rdquo;..&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You want customers who are reachable, profitable, and personally&amp;nbsp;rewarding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good segments are usually &amp;ldquo;who-where&amp;rdquo; pairs. If you don&amp;rsquo;t know where to find your customers, keep slicing until you do. Make sure the segment is reachable, profitable, and personally&amp;nbsp;rewarding&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-8-getting-the-most-from-the-conversations-by-prepping-and-reviewing"&gt;Chapter 8 - Getting the most from the conversations by prepping and&amp;nbsp;reviewing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prepare well&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you 3 big questions ready, including the scary&amp;nbsp;ones&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Know who you are speaking&amp;nbsp;to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Know what commitment and next-steps you want to push&amp;nbsp;for&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spend up to an hour &lt;strong&gt;writing down your best guesses about what you think they will say, what they care about and what they want.&lt;/strong&gt; If you have a focussed segment, you&amp;rsquo;ll only need to do this&amp;nbsp;occasionally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whilst prepping, if you come across a question which can be answered using the internet, use the&amp;nbsp;internet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take good notes&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask if you can record the&amp;nbsp;audio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Record emotions as well as words. Verbatim alone isn&amp;rsquo;t always accurate 6 months&amp;nbsp;later&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use shorthand for follow up, happy, angry, meh,&amp;nbsp;etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pains and obstacles are a lot more important if someone is embarrassed or angry when they&amp;rsquo;re talking about&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dig into the big emotions, find out what&amp;rsquo;s causing them, or why its a big&amp;nbsp;deal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review your notes&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meta - which questions went well or&amp;nbsp;not?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What were the answers to the scary&amp;nbsp;questions?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can you do better next&amp;nbsp;time?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What were the clear signals? What signals did you&amp;nbsp;miss?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"></category></entry><entry><title>Obviously Awesome</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/obviously-awesome.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-03T15:46:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-03T15:46:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-12-03:/obviously-awesome.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My notes on &amp;ldquo;Obviously Awesome&amp;rdquo; by April&amp;nbsp;Dunford&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3 id="intro"&gt;Intro&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In order to do better marketing, understand your value and differentiators&amp;nbsp;better&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand what makes a best-fit&amp;nbsp;customer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positioning is a fundamental input to every business tactic you&amp;nbsp;use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you fail at positioning, you fail at marketing and&amp;nbsp;sales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positioning is &amp;ldquo;conext setting&amp;rdquo; for&amp;nbsp;products&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customers need to be able to easily understand&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What your product&amp;nbsp;does&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why it is&amp;nbsp;special&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why it matters to&amp;nbsp;them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your prospects can&amp;rsquo;t figure out what your product does quickly, they will
   invent a position for you. It might hide your key strengths or misunderstand
   your&amp;nbsp;value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find people to demo your product to, then ask them to describe it back to
   you. Do the same with existing customers. If they&amp;rsquo;re not saying the same
   thing then you have a positioning&amp;nbsp;problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Products with strong positioning:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find the best kind of&amp;nbsp;customer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the value&amp;nbsp;obvious&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sell&amp;nbsp;quickly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="part-1"&gt;Part&amp;nbsp;1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="positioning-as-context"&gt;Positioning as&amp;nbsp;context&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Without positioning to guide us, we don&amp;rsquo;t know how to understnad a&amp;nbsp;product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positioning lets us make assumptions about&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who a product is&amp;nbsp;for&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what its main features&amp;nbsp;are&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how much it&amp;nbsp;costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Without it we would be paralyzed by choice, and we wouldnt be able to make
   sense of all the products around&amp;nbsp;us. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The context and purpose of a product from the founders/engineers perspective
   are often different to those of the&amp;nbsp;prospect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Products can be positioned in multiple ways, and often the best positioning
   is not the default&amp;nbsp;positioning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bad positioning makes it harder for prospects to figure out if your product
   is worth thinking&amp;nbsp;about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positioning requires considering:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customers point of view - what problem/pain does it&amp;nbsp;solve&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ways your product is uniquely&amp;nbsp;different&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The characteristics of a potential&amp;nbsp;customer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The best market context to make your value uniquely&amp;nbsp;obvious&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id="five-plus-one-components-of-effective-positioning"&gt;Five (plus one) components of effective&amp;nbsp;positioning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Competitive Alternatives - if you didn&amp;rsquo;t exist, what would your customers
   use instead?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Its what your prospects would use to do the task if your product didn&amp;rsquo;t
   exist. It could be excel, or pen and paper. It could be nothing, (in
   which case maybe you product doesn&amp;rsquo;t solve a real pain&amp;nbsp;point.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You probably know a lot more about your market, and problem, and
   alternative solutions, than your prospects do. (&amp;ldquo;Doing nothing&amp;rdquo; could be
   an opportunity, not a red&amp;nbsp;flag.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Its important to understand what customers will compare your product
   with, because this is how they will define &amp;ldquo;better&amp;rdquo;. Is it &amp;ldquo;easier&amp;rdquo; than
   a pen and&amp;nbsp;paper?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customers might never have purchased a solution like yours&amp;nbsp;before.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unique Attributes - What do you have that alternative do not?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Could be:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivery Model (online vs offline, installed on-site vs&amp;nbsp;not)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Business model (rental vs&amp;nbsp;purchase)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specific expertise (data scientist with financial and back-end web
   dev&amp;nbsp;expertise)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Value (and quantifiable objective proof) - What value do the attributes
   enable for customers?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If unique attributes are your secret sauce, the value is why someone
   might care about your secret&amp;nbsp;sauce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fact based, provable, demonstrable, quantifiable, objective. Third party
   opinions are&amp;nbsp;relevant. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Target market characteristics - Who cares a lot about that value?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on customers who are most likely to purchase quickly, wont ask for
   discounts, will tell their friends about&amp;nbsp;you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should clearly identify who these are&amp;nbsp;and &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identity what sets them apart from other groups of customers. Why are
   they uniquely likely to buy from you when others wouldnt or would take
   longer to consider and make a&amp;nbsp;purchase&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Market Category - What context makes your value obvious to the ideal
   customer?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Declaring that your product exists in a certain market triggers a
   powerful set of&amp;nbsp;assumptions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make these assumptions help you, not hinder&amp;nbsp;you. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When presented with your product, customers will try to use what they
   already know to figure out what your product is all about and why its
   special. You want them to be able to do this really quickly and&amp;nbsp;easily. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make these assumptions work for you, not against you. You won&amp;rsquo;t have to
   list every feature, because most of them will be assumed by the context
   of the market&amp;nbsp;category. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get it right, and sales efforts (copy) wont be wasted battling those
   assumptions, but can instead build off of them to show secret sauce and
   value more&amp;nbsp;obviously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Bonus) Relevant Trends - what trends make your product relevant right
   now?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Used carefully, trends can show prospoects why they should pay attention
   to your product right now. Increases&amp;nbsp;urgency.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can increase urgency, excitement, coolness,&amp;nbsp;credibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;but the trend must be directly relevant, practically and objectively&amp;nbsp;applicable. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blockchains, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AI&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ML&lt;/span&gt; are trends - they are relevant to multiple&amp;nbsp;markets. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of these components is relevant to the&amp;nbsp;others&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"></category><category term="marketing"></category><category term="positioning"></category><category term="startups"></category><category term="book"></category></entry><entry><title>How I learnt to code</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/How-I-learnt-to-code.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-01T13:51:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-01T13:51:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-12-01:/How-I-learnt-to-code.html</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;4 years ago I started learning how to code, and it was &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; difficult! It&amp;rsquo;s
still difficult, but I now have a collection of tools and perspectives that
make it less daunting (more on that below). Leveling up requires one more
abstraction to wrap my head around, or one more &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; to understand. I can do&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I don&amp;rsquo;t think it needed to be so difficult, so now I&amp;rsquo;m building &lt;a href="https://codeschoolmeta.com"&gt;Code
School Meta&lt;/a&gt; to make it easier to learn how to&amp;nbsp;code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning to code has been fun, ultimately successful, and life changing (hello
job security!) but at the beginning it was sooo slow, and super&amp;nbsp;tricky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember feeling like an imposter, and thinking that I was definitely not a
real developer - I hadn&amp;rsquo;t taken any classes in computer science. I felt like I
knew almost nothing about&amp;nbsp;anything. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process began with Pandas, a (&lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt;) Python analytics library. Spreadsheets
were slowing me down at work, and I was bored. I found this &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/5JnMutdy6Fw"&gt;great
tutorial&lt;/a&gt; by Brandon Rhodes. From there I found
out about Jupyter Notebooks, and then I found about Github pages and how to
make a blog using &lt;a href="https://blog.getpelican.com/"&gt;pelican&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That led to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; (and also JavaScript, which I tried very hard to avoid
for as long as possible). I felt like a monkey bashing a keyboard as I tried to
make &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; elements do what I&amp;nbsp;wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Git was next, but I found this &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/rys-git-tutorial.html"&gt;amazing tutorial&lt;/a&gt;
to help me learn. It made Git seem &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt;, and also helped &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; make more
sense too.&amp;nbsp;Bonus!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suddenly realized that great learning materials are crucial if I was going to
keep momentum and keep on enjoying the thrill of seeing the computer do
something I hadn&amp;rsquo;t made it do&amp;nbsp;before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now I&amp;rsquo;m now working on &lt;a href="https://codeschoolmeta.com"&gt;Code School: Meta&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s
an online community to make it easier to teach yourself how to code - less
confusion about how to get started or what to learn next, more encouragement,
and lots of high quality&amp;nbsp;resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;d like to know more, please &lt;a href="https://codeschoolmeta.com"&gt;check it out&lt;/a&gt;
and sign up for&amp;nbsp;updates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"></category></entry><entry><title>The 1-Page Marketing Plan</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/1-page-marketing-plan.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-11-19T15:50:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-19T15:50:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-11-19:/1-page-marketing-plan.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My notes on &amp;ldquo;The 1-Page Marketing Plan&amp;rdquo; by Allan&amp;nbsp;Dib&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="marketing-has-three-phases"&gt;Marketing has three&amp;nbsp;phases&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Before (prospect) - get people to know you and indicate&amp;nbsp;interest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;During (lead) - get the to like you and buy from you for the first&amp;nbsp;time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After (customer) - get them to trust you, buy from you regularly, and&amp;nbsp;refer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new&amp;nbsp;customers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marketing is &lt;em&gt;strategy&lt;/em&gt;, all the other things are &lt;em&gt;tactics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="jargon-free-definition-of-marketing"&gt;Jargon free definition of&amp;nbsp;marketing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advertising&lt;/strong&gt; - The circus is coming to town, you paint a sign saying &amp;ldquo;Circus coming to town on&amp;nbsp;Saturday&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Promotion&lt;/strong&gt; - Put the sign on the back of an elephant and walk it into&amp;nbsp;town&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Publicity&lt;/strong&gt; - Walk the elephant through the mayors flower beds and let a newspaper write about&amp;nbsp;it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Public relations&lt;/strong&gt; - Get the mayor to laugh about&amp;nbsp;it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sales&lt;/strong&gt; - the town people go to the circus, you explain how much fun the entertainment is, they buy some tickets, you answer their questions, they spend lots of money on food, games,&amp;nbsp;shows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marketing&lt;/strong&gt; is the plan that made the whole thing&amp;nbsp;happen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"></category><category term="Marketing"></category></entry><entry><title>Learning to market</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/marketing-101.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-11-19T12:40:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-19T12:40:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-11-19:/marketing-101.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve learnt many things this year by being a solo technical founder, but so far marketing isn&amp;rsquo;t one of them. I&amp;rsquo;m trying to change&amp;nbsp;that.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Since April I&amp;rsquo;ve been able to work full time as a solo founder. I&amp;rsquo;ve challenged
myself to build something useful enough that customers would want to pay for it
and in the process of seeking that goal I&amp;rsquo;ve become a much better and more
rounded&amp;nbsp;developer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been working solo for about 7 months now, and in that time I&amp;rsquo;ve begun
using test driven development, I&amp;rsquo;ve built non-trivial data driven web apps
using Django, and I&amp;rsquo;ve learnt how to deploy and monitor those apps in
production and make them&amp;nbsp;performant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve made two main apps; &lt;a href="https://moneybar.nl"&gt;moneybar.nl&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://pippip.email"&gt;pippip.email&lt;/a&gt;, and I&amp;rsquo;ve learnt so&amp;nbsp;much. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m realising though, that I still have much to learn in other spheres. Being a
great developer is deeply meaningful to me. It&amp;rsquo;s literally a bucket list item
for me and I intend to be writing code as long as I live. But there is no point
creating products if no one knows they&amp;nbsp;exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where marketing and positioning comes in. Right now it feels like I
know nothing about how to get users, or validate an idea, or position a
product. These are all super necessary and super&amp;nbsp;unknown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a more meta level, I&amp;rsquo;m confronted with the lost benefits of working with
co-founders, or of having friends doing similar things. I want to work faster
and make progress more efficiently. I need to be part of a&amp;nbsp;community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working in isolation does have its advantages, though. I&amp;rsquo;m self-taught and
self-directed, figuring out the contours of uncharted territory and creating my
own personal map. In my mind, I have a deep and almost personal relationship
with the coding abstractions and tools I&amp;rsquo;ve learnt to work with. Classes and
functions, strings and floats, literally have (to me) their own textures,
colors and weights when I think or dream about&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It feels like I can pick up these abstractions as if they were physical objects
and turn them around to examine them. Place them next to each other and compare
the differences. Run thought experiements. In my experience, this kind of
relationship and affection simply doesn&amp;rsquo;t happen when taking a class or
following someone elses schedule. It&amp;rsquo;s satisying to feel ownership of a skill
like this, and it&amp;rsquo;s one of the primary reasons I consider coding to be similar
to a&amp;nbsp;craft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having said all that, now that I realise I need to validate my product,
position it, and figure out marketing, I&amp;rsquo;ve stopped writing code, put down my
tools, and I&amp;rsquo;m going to learn marketing. I&amp;rsquo;ve bought some books. Maybe I&amp;rsquo;ll
post some reviews here&amp;nbsp;later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In no particular order here is what I plan to&amp;nbsp;read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 1-Page marketing plan, by Allan Dib Obviously Awesome, by April&amp;nbsp;Dunford&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lean Analytics, Hooked, How to build habit-forming products, by Nir Eyal&amp;nbsp;The&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mom Test, by Rob&amp;nbsp;Fitzpatrick&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is marketing, by Seth&amp;nbsp;Godin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product-led growth, by Wes&amp;nbsp;Bush&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know if I&amp;rsquo;ve covered 90% of the distance required or 50%. It&amp;rsquo;s
exhausting but I&amp;rsquo;m here for the journey not the&amp;nbsp;destination.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"></category><category term="marketing"></category><category term="growth"></category></entry><entry><title>Pippip.Email</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/pippip.email.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-28T13:37:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-10-28T13:37:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-10-28:/pippip.email.html</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="pippip"&gt;&lt;a href="https://pippip.email"&gt;PipPip&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6 weeks ago I had an idea for a product whilst reading a news&amp;nbsp;article. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be great if the writing and sending of important messages could be
separated, so that I could write something long before I needed to send it, and
know that then sending would happen at the right time without having to think
about it. This could be useful for sending my daughter a message on her 15th
birthday, or to my wife on our 10th anniversary. I also designed a check-in
mechanism, so that messages could be sent if I disappeared or pass&amp;nbsp;away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://PipPip.email"&gt;PipPip&lt;/a&gt; is the result - event-driven and scheduled email delivery, from days to&amp;nbsp;decades&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re working on validating the idea and finding the right niche&amp;nbsp;audience. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Entrepreneurship"></category><category term="PipPip"></category></entry><entry><title>Between Clients</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/between-clients.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-10-08T16:05:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-10-08T16:05:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2019-10-08:/between-clients.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As a freelance data scientist, I use time between client engagements to up-skill and pursue professional interests that I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t otherwise be able&amp;nbsp;to.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At the end of the summer I had time between engagements to work on some side projects and grapple with some new (to me) libraries and&amp;nbsp;technologies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="during-august-and-september-2019-i"&gt;During August and September 2019,&amp;nbsp;I:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practiced creating websites using the &lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com"&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;web-framework&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigated and demo&amp;rsquo;ed &lt;a href="https://pypi.org/project/django-plotly-dash/"&gt;django-plotly-dash&lt;/a&gt; - a library that allows exposing &lt;a href="https://dash.plot.ly"&gt;Plotly Dash&lt;/a&gt; apps to django&amp;nbsp;projects&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Built a personal finance dashboard using &lt;a href="https://dash.plot.ly"&gt;Plotly Dash&lt;/a&gt; and began turning it into a web app using &lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com"&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://pypi.org/project/django-plotly-dash/"&gt;django-plotly-dash&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interviewed for a role at &lt;a href="https://coinmetrics.io"&gt;CoinMetrics.io&lt;/a&gt; and created &lt;a href="https://blog.johnmathews.eu/btc-fork-analysis.html"&gt;this investigation&lt;/a&gt; as a technical&amp;nbsp;exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Created a company &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://atlasdata.nl"&gt;Atlas Consulting Internatonal&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; to facilitate life as a freelance data scientist and&amp;nbsp;consultant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spent a lot of time working at the cafe in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IKEA&lt;/span&gt; because my co-working space wouldn&amp;rsquo;t let me stay late or work on public&amp;nbsp;holidays&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduced myself to this &lt;a href="http://haarlemoffice.nl"&gt;new coworking space&lt;/a&gt; and suggested we could work together to create the best tech-focussed startup hub and coworking space in the&amp;nbsp;Netherlands. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bought our first car. It required a lot more time and research than I&amp;nbsp;expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Created &lt;a href="http://www.texnidata.com"&gt;Texni Data Consultancy&lt;/a&gt; with Dan Caputo to provide data strategy consultancy&amp;nbsp;services. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Built the website for &lt;a href="http://www.texnidata.com"&gt;Texni Data&lt;/a&gt; using django and deployed it to Heroku with a custom domain&amp;nbsp;name. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deployed a django app to &lt;a href="https://cloud.google.com"&gt;Google Cloud Platform&lt;/a&gt; using &lt;a href="https://cloud.google.com/appengine/"&gt;App Engine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Created a &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu"&gt;business website&lt;/a&gt; to represent my work as a freelance data scientist and made my &lt;a href="https://blog.johnmathews.eu"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; a subdomain of this&amp;nbsp;site. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moved my blog off of github pages and onto &lt;a href="https://firebase.google.com"&gt;firebase&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks Github for several years of simple trouble free&amp;nbsp;hosting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experimented with using storage buckets on Google Cloud Platform to host static sites and serve them over &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSL&lt;/span&gt;. My conclusion is that serving static sites using storage buckets is great - it&amp;rsquo;s simple, quick and cheap (free). But adding &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSL&lt;/span&gt; proved too difficult. I spent too many hours trying to create a loadbalancer that would work for both the root domain &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu"&gt;johnmathews.eu&lt;/a&gt; and also a subdomain &lt;a href="https://blog.johnmathews.eu"&gt;blog.johnmathews.eu&lt;/a&gt;. In the end I found out about firebase. Firebase is also quick and cheap (free) and simple enough to pick-up&amp;nbsp;quickly. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Created a photo book using &lt;a href="https://www.photobox.co.uk"&gt;PhotoBox&lt;/a&gt; that turned out great. It covers the last 3.5 years and is mostly full of snapshots of our kids and selfies with&amp;nbsp;Ritsya.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chose a primary school for my daughter to go to next&amp;nbsp;year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Career"></category><category term="Freelance"></category></entry><entry><title>Bakke-Rij</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/bakkerij.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-06-11T13:09:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-06-11T13:09:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2018-06-11:/bakkerij.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a great example of a creative and innovative coworking&amp;nbsp;space.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently began working in a new coworking space, sharing an office unit with another entrepreneur. What makes this coworking space unique is it&amp;rsquo;s conversion from an industrial bakery to a coworking space. Where the machinery once stood, converted shipping containers with glass walls have become offices for startups and&amp;nbsp;freelancers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The skylights, glass walls and bright colors create a light and airy atmosphere, and the space seems popular with designers and founders working in creative industries. It&amp;rsquo;s an energetic space with a creative feel to&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bakke-Rij" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/bakkerij1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bakke-Rij" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/bakkerij2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Entrepreneurship"></category><category term="coworking"></category><category term="Netherlands"></category><category term="Haarlem"></category></entry><entry><title>What I’m reading</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/reading.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-06-04T15:52:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-06-04T15:52:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2018-06-04:/reading.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A list of interesting things. June&amp;nbsp;2018&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="articles"&gt;Articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fs.blog/mental-models/"&gt;Mental models&lt;/a&gt; A comprehensive list organised around different disciplines. It a long read but probably one of the most easy to apply and tangibly useful articles I&amp;rsquo;ve read&amp;nbsp;recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/vb.html"&gt;Life is short&lt;/a&gt; - Is life actually short, or would we always want more time, no matter how much we could&amp;nbsp;have?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.eugenewei.com/blog/2018/5/21/invisible-asymptotes"&gt;Invisible asymptotes&lt;/a&gt; - A well written and long look at various facets of business&amp;nbsp;strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://osam.com/Commentary/factors-from-scratch"&gt;Factors from scratch&lt;/a&gt; - Investing: A unified framework to explain how factors&amp;nbsp;work. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://kottke.org/18/06/a-sad-update-about-a-scissors-maker-that-went-viral"&gt;This is tragic&lt;/a&gt; - &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;But I do think this highlights the potential disconnects between mental health &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; business, publicity &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; success, and success &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; happiness. The internet can seem so intimate but ultimately it’s a thin view of an individual’s or company’s&amp;nbsp;reality.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://statico.github.io/vim3.html"&gt;Vim&lt;/a&gt; after 15&amp;nbsp;years&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2018/03/27/a-complete-guide-to-cyprocurrency-regulations-around-the-world.html?__source=sharebar%7Clinkedin&amp;amp;par=sharebar"&gt;Cryptocurrency regulations around the&amp;nbsp;world&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.lrb.co.uk/v40/n13/john-lanchester/after-the-fall"&gt;On the 2008 financial crisis&lt;/a&gt; - &amp;ldquo;I’m not sure if it’s philosophically possible for an action to be both necessary and a disaster, but that in essence is what the bailouts&amp;nbsp;were.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="podcasts"&gt;Podcasts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/whatbitcoindid"&gt;Jill Carlson&lt;/a&gt; on the &amp;ldquo;What Bitcoin Did&amp;rdquo; podcast. “For the first time there is no longer a monopoly on the creation of value or monetary systems, that is really What Bitcoin&amp;nbsp;Did.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/deVoaRTfVqs"&gt;Georges St-Pierre&lt;/a&gt; on the Joe Rogan podcast. A long and candid conversation from one of the world&amp;rsquo;s best&amp;nbsp;athletes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/KqhRZfKRriU"&gt;Ricardo Spagni&lt;/a&gt; a.k.a Fluffypony on Monero vs Bitcoin, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EOS&lt;/span&gt;, the current bear market, Tari, and&amp;nbsp;ASICs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="resources"&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lots of &lt;a href="https://vincentarelbundock.github.io/Rdatasets/datasets.html"&gt;data&amp;nbsp;sets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"></category><category term="Reading"></category></entry><entry><title>Neighbours</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/neighbours.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-31T22:30:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-05-31T22:30:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2018-05-31:/neighbours.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Humans deserve respect, simply because they are human. This truth is in the process of going from self evident, to assumed, to&amp;nbsp;denied.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A useful model I&amp;rsquo;ve come across states that it takes three generations for a society to deny something previously considered true. The first generation studies or experiences something which leads to a particular value or belief. The second generation inherits the belief and assumes it to be true, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t arrive at the belief through their own critical thought. The third generation then questions the assumption, realises that most holders of the belief do not have a good basis for their belief, and disregards&amp;nbsp;it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The belief that people have a responsibility to look after each other and treat each other with a minimum level of respect seems to be following this&amp;nbsp;route.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That humans inherently deserve a degree of respect and dignity simply because they are human is self-evident. In times of comfort and excess it could be ignored, but in times of calamity and in the aftermath of disasters it becomes undeniable and obvious. This is partly because disasters reveal our instinct for justice and our frailty in the face of&amp;nbsp;misfortune.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life is experienced through the lens of the mind, and its perception is mostly governed by fundamental circumstances or desires. The trappings of a prosperous society allows this reality to be covered by a veneer of soft arguments, or rejected in favor of a viewpoint that says we have superseded these supposedly basic&amp;nbsp;origins. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good leaders should know better. They should study history and be self-aware. In the past they have forgotten this reality and have been forced to relearn it at great cost. Are we about to forget, again, and let our children live with those&amp;nbsp;consequences?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My grandfathers generation saw the damage that sectarian systems bring, and were forced to answer questions around how much respect people deserve only because they are people. As the consequences of different views and systems became evident, my fathers generation assumed the answers to be self-evident, because the consequences of the previous &amp;ldquo;forgetting&amp;rdquo; were still&amp;nbsp;clear. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who is clearly articulating this now? This&amp;nbsp;year? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we discuss taxation, social mobility, migration, military intervention, why do we not start with the assumed self-evident truth that people are inherently valuable and important? Humans are more than metrics, and cannot be entirely evaluated using only quantitative&amp;nbsp;methods. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Horton, the title character in &amp;ldquo;Horton Hears a Who&amp;rdquo; by Dr. Zeus, understood this. He went to great lengths to protect the tiny and weak people in who-ville. We teach this truth to our children, but do not demonstrate it as adults. Jesus also understood it. He said that we should love our neighbours, and explained that our neighbours are people we come across who need our&amp;nbsp;help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wonder if forgetting that humans are inherently worthy of respect is a prerequisite for&amp;nbsp;declining;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;standards of&amp;nbsp;governance&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;social&amp;nbsp;mobility&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;peace&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;economic&amp;nbsp;growth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which makes me think it is a self defeating deception. When we choose to disregard a group of humans because it is inconvenient to help them, we are elevating our needs above theirs. This seems to create chains of events where everybody&amp;nbsp;suffers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"></category><category term="Politics"></category><category term="Equality"></category></entry><entry><title>Live near the ocean</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/ocean.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-11-23T18:48:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-11-23T18:48:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-11-23:/ocean.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Being near water is&amp;nbsp;better.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3 id="california"&gt;California&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="California" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/california3.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="California" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/california7.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="California" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/california9.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="dorset"&gt;Dorset&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Dorset" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/dorset.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Dorset" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/beach.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="acapulco"&gt;Acapulco&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Acapulco" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/mex1.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Acapulco" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/mex2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="dublin"&gt;Dublin&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Dublin" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/dublin.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Dublin" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/dublin1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-netherlands"&gt;The&amp;nbsp;Netherlands&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Hague" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/hague.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Hague" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/amsterdam3.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Hague" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/amsterdam1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"></category><category term="water"></category></entry><entry><title>I’m a chartered accountant</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/chartered.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-10-19T21:56:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-10-19T21:56:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-10-19:/chartered.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve qualified as a chartered accountant and will soon become a member of the Institute of Chartered Accountants in England and&amp;nbsp;Wales&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year I qualified as a chartered accountant. Qualification requires passing 15 exams and gaining 3150 hours of work&amp;nbsp;experience. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To celebrate passing your exams and verify your success, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ICAEW&lt;/span&gt; print the names of everyone who passed in an advert in the Financial Times. This happened for me on the 26&amp;nbsp;January.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="exam pass list in the financial times" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/exam_pass_list.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Career"></category><category term="ICAEW"></category><category term="ACA"></category><category term="Accounting"></category></entry><entry><title>Coworking in Dublin</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/coworking.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-15T11:55:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-09-15T11:55:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-09-15:/coworking.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A review of eight coworking spaces in&amp;nbsp;Dublin&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week I arrived in Dublin and had two days to find a coworking space. I ran around Dublin visiting as many as&amp;nbsp;possible. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m looking to rent a hotdesk, which means I don&amp;rsquo;t have any storage space at the office and I don&amp;rsquo;t have a particular&amp;nbsp;desk. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are my impressions of eight businesses offering either hot desks or dedicated desks, ranked in order of preference. It&amp;rsquo;s subjective. The going rate in Dublin seems to be €200 — €300 per month for a hot desk. Hours range from 9am - 7pm Monday - Friday, to&amp;nbsp;24/7. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="first-place-dogpatch-labs"&gt;First place: &lt;a href="http://dogpatchlabs.com/"&gt;Dogpatch&amp;nbsp;Labs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dogpatch offer a coworking space and access to a community of tech startups. They run regular networking and mentoring events and occupy 3 floors of a warehouse next to an old dock. The offices have a range of interiors styles. The middle level is fairly standard but pleasant open plan offices, the top floor is a flexible working space with event areas. The lower level is a series of vaults that each contain meeting rooms of various sizes. There&amp;rsquo;s a lot going on and there&amp;rsquo;s a good buzz in the&amp;nbsp;air. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The range of interior spaces is a big plus for me and I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to being able to switch up my working environment through the day. There&amp;rsquo;s a couple of kitchen areas, and a table football and table-tennis table on the top level. Access is 6am - midnight, and a hot desk is €200 per month. A dedicated desk is&amp;nbsp;€400. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dogpatch occupy less than a quarter of the warehouse building, the remainder of the space is used as a shopping mall and a museum. In my opinion Dogpatch is by far the best value and if you&amp;rsquo;re working in tech it&amp;rsquo;ll probably be your go-to&amp;nbsp;solution. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="second-place-studio9"&gt;Second place: &lt;a href="http://studio9.ie/?page_id=223"&gt;Studio9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These guys are great. The space is a lot smaller that Dogpatch, comprising only ~12 desks. It&amp;rsquo;s a basement, but don&amp;rsquo;t let that put you off — its open plan and has large windows at either end. The space is well designed and uses a lot of light colours and textures, including wood on the walls and floors. There are also plenty of pot plants. These combine to give a bright and airy atmosphere that feels very natural and&amp;nbsp;bright.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are alcoves down one side of the main room which serve as meeting rooms, and a garden and basic kitchen at the back. The owners want the space to foster a community, and I expect that this is achieved. There are no dedicated offices and no teams using multiple desks, everyone is an independent&amp;nbsp;worker. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The desks are large, and each has its own little wall to provide some privacy. €200 per month ongoing, or €250 for just one month. They offer a trial day for&amp;nbsp;free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="third-place-officesuites"&gt;Third place: &lt;a href="http://www.officesuites.ie/locations/20-harcourt-street/"&gt;OfficeSuites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The building looks well run and appears clean and fresh with adequate resources. The building is an old Georgian tenement with high ceilings, cornicing and lots of natural light. The furnishings and decor lean towards corporate rather than something more interesting, but this works well to add a professional feel to the homely architecture. Access is&amp;nbsp;24/7. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s only two rooms for hotdesking, and most of the building is given to private offices. There&amp;rsquo;s a garden with bike storage, meeting rooms and a quiet room for calls. Lockers are extra. They also offer a free day as a&amp;nbsp;trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;€249 p/m for desk access 9am-7pm Monday -&amp;nbsp;Friday&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="fourth-place-element78"&gt;Fourth place: &lt;a href="https://www.element78.co/"&gt;Element78&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friendly and well resourced, but very corporate. The architecture is corporate glass and steel. They&amp;rsquo;re situated on the ground floor in a posh business district with large financials for neighbours. It&amp;rsquo;s too corporate for me, but if you wanted an impressive place to meet clients and a nice address, this could be it. There were about 15 hot-desks for rent, plus plenty of dedicated desks. Clients seemed to include mostly young tech companies and tech&amp;nbsp;freelancers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m hoping to find somewhere with more of a community, more inspiring architecture, and more character. I was offered a free day as a&amp;nbsp;trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;€200 for the first month then €350&amp;nbsp;p/m&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="fifth-place-glandore"&gt;Fifth place: &lt;a href="https://glandore.co/flexible-workspace.aspx#Hot-Desk"&gt;Glandore&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Glandore offer a relatively luxurious package with a corporate feel. They have a few buildings in Dublin and only the flagship has hotdesking space. There&amp;rsquo;s a super looking restaurant and a large club room to relax in, but these are features that I don&amp;rsquo;t need, and the rates aren&amp;rsquo;t competitive if all you need is a desk and somewhere to take calls. It&amp;rsquo;s set up for teams and for impressing clients, and independent tech workers are probably better off&amp;nbsp;elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;€295&amp;nbsp;p/m &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sixth-place-regus"&gt;Sixth place: &lt;a href="https://www.regus.ie/office-space/ireland/dublin/dublin-4-ballsbridge"&gt;Regus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regus offer a polished on boarding experience and the friendly staff were quick to respond and generally helpful, but the office space was bland, grey and generic. The rooms I visited didn&amp;rsquo;t have external windows and it reminded me of the rooms banks often put auditors in. If grey walls and tube lights are your thing then this is for you.  24/7 access, and meeting rooms equipped with&amp;nbsp;A/V.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;€299.70&amp;nbsp;p/m.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="seventh-place-cocreate"&gt;Seventh place: &lt;a href="http://www.cocreate.ie/"&gt;CoCreate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I visited the southern branch and thought the building was a bit shabby and needed a new layer of paint. I recognised the desks as some of the cheapest available from &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IKEA&lt;/span&gt;. The rooms were small and needed cleaning, and there was weird art on the&amp;nbsp;wall. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thought of paying €200 a month to sit at a small wobbly desk put me off. The place was also almost deserted. Maybe their other branch is better, but this is not for&amp;nbsp;me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;€220&amp;nbsp;p/m. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="last-place-tcube"&gt;Last place: &lt;a href="http://tcubedublin.com/tcube/index.html"&gt;tCube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last and least, tCube seems to be putting in zero effort. When I visited I saw two rooms that needed painting, disorganised furniture and abandoned bits of computers lying around. The kitchen isn&amp;rsquo;t high spec and the meeting room isn&amp;rsquo;t big enough. I was also given a speech about how great the wifi was - a prerequisite that was taken for granted everywhere else. At €300 p/m for a dedicated desk its easy to find better value&amp;nbsp;elsewhere. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Career"></category><category term="Freelance"></category><category term="Coworking"></category><category term="Dublin"></category><category term="Element78"></category><category term="Regus"></category><category term="OfficeSuites"></category><category term="CoCreate"></category><category term="Studio9"></category><category term="Glandore"></category><category term="tCube"></category></entry><entry><title>Corporate London</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/corporate.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-07-10T21:37:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-07-10T21:37:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-07-10:/corporate.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Reflections on 3 years living and working in&amp;nbsp;London&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="2014-2017"&gt;2014 -&amp;nbsp;2017&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having made arrangements to leave London, it seems like a reasonable time to reflect on my time&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;London is a tough city to live in — it&amp;rsquo;s big enough that a sub 1-hour commute is considered good, and it&amp;rsquo;s super expensive. My stay in London has been defined by my quest to complete my graduate scheme and qualify as an&amp;nbsp;accountant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first arrived I had no idea what London or working in a corporate would be like. I was coming from academia, and my motivation for moving to finance could be summed up in two&amp;nbsp;points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand more about the 2008 financial&amp;nbsp;crisis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get paid more for using mostly the same skills (math) as in&amp;nbsp;engineering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t think there’s anything wrong with these motivations, but I should have been making a long term career plan&amp;nbsp;instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started my job I was surprised at the 6 weeks of induction and hot-desking. Life as an auditor felt nomadic, as everyone would spend large amounts of time at client&amp;rsquo;s offices, and no-one has their own desk in our office. The only thing you really own is your knowledge and your network of&amp;nbsp;relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2014, I arrived with a high opinion of my employer and the view that I would be staying for several years. Having escaped the financial insecurity of short-term research grants, I’d moved back to my home country to contribute to the system that educated me. I was happy to have a regular job with a decent, predictable&amp;nbsp;salary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A phrase that kept coming to mind back then was “accountant factory”. Our training materials were scripted and everything was a standardised process. We were being processed. Graduates in, corporate accountants&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company is huge and so are the efficiencies and barriers to competition that come with this. When I arrived I was impressed there were free biscuits, and it felt presumptuous to put a meeting in someones diary. Now I ignore any communications addressed to a mailing&amp;nbsp;list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="accountant"&gt;Accountant&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The toughest experiences were related to the accountancy qualification. Naïvely I had believed that the qualification wouldn’t be a big deal and I didn’t give any thought to it when I applied — I just wanted to find out how banks worked. If there were some exams to be done then it would be fine, I’d already achieved a PhD and I would handle&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That turned out to be a mistake. A huge mistake. The alarm bells should have rung louder when I realised most of my graduate colleagues had only applied so that they could get the qualification (and were already intending to leave asap afterwards). Doing the pre-course work before college wasn&amp;rsquo;t trivial. College - I was being sent to a classroom again. We were being taken out of the office, away from clients, and put in a classroom to prepare for these&amp;nbsp;exams…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting a job that required becoming a chartered accountant, without considering the effort and time involved to qualify was dumb. It’s an oversight I find hard to&amp;nbsp;believe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disappointment and sadness at having to study again was profound. The teaching and assessment style was several steps behind what I’d become used to. Compared to the depth, autonomy and research-focus of a doctorate, writing cookie-cutter essays in time-pressured exams felt stupid. The exams were hard and I failed several of them, probably because of my low morale whilst revising. Retaking them required more weekends and annual leave being spent away from my family, camped-out in libraries and&amp;nbsp;offices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This required much patience and generosity from Ritsya, who having not seen me for long periods during my doctorate expected us to have a more normal lifestyle when we came to London. I found it miserable to pause my social life and other interests whilst studying, and then I would try to rush back to them when I had the time, knowing that soon I’d have to pause them&amp;nbsp;again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I hadn’t already studied in Vienna, this process of working and studying in London would have been exciting and felt valuable or special. I’d passed enough exams though to know that they’re never as important as they’re made out to be, and whatever it was that was missing from my life wasn’t going to be found in another&amp;nbsp;qualification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the upside though, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACA&lt;/span&gt; is the most practical qualification I’ve gained and has taught me many useful aspects of business and finance. I’m glad to finally see business not as some mysterious system but something attainable and&amp;nbsp;understandable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="neighbourhood"&gt;Neighbourhood&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Living in London has also required a lot of time on trains — my door to desk commute is about an hour each way, and I’ve never lived somewhere in London that hasn’t felt transient. We’ve needed to live near a station and didn’t want to commute more than an hour and that’s put us in neighbourhoods with other young professionals who also don’t have long term plans (or financial ability) to stay in the city. We’re all looking to move on and move up as fast as possible.  I want to leave London partly because there are so many people with the same attitudes and priorities as my&amp;nbsp;own…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="corporate-culture"&gt;Corporate&amp;nbsp;Culture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in the office I spent the first few months figuring out how people were organised, how teams operated and how decisions were made. I think it took me about a year to feel like I understood how things really worked, and 1.5 years to feel like I could do all aspects of my job with certainty. There is a difference between how things are spoken about, and how things actually&amp;nbsp;happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My experience has been that performance is all that matters and behaviour is defined by self-interest. I don’t think this is different from previous environments I&amp;rsquo;ve worked in — academia isn&amp;rsquo;t any different&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and the construction industry certainly isn’t. I wonder if the only way people can endure it is if they’ve not experienced anything else, or think it normal, or necessary. I find myself wishing we could be kinder to each other, and that we could create structures that incentivise mutual&amp;nbsp;support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corporate finance usually appears clean and well presented. Its people appear dependable and capable. The culture is sanitised and there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of pressure to conform - you can see it in the clothes and accessories we wear and the jokes we tell each other in the&amp;nbsp;canteen. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came to see my office as a glass and steel cathedral. I read about the Middle East, and migrants arriving in Europe, and tower blocks burning, and felt really&amp;nbsp;disconnected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the high regard with which we hold ourselves, we don’t ask each other how we can help. Maybe we are too busy, or feel powerless to help. Apparently we do not know how to help, despite our wealth, talents, education and&amp;nbsp;connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember watching a man leave the office one day and thought that if he gave his whole career and left his firm after decades of service, there would be nothing left to identify him after a few weeks. The work will always get done. Market forces will dictate how the business adapts and grows. The City rolls&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Publications trump almost all other metrics, and the incentives to publish quantity over quality are such that risky or slow research is inexcusable. The metrics used to standardise success and allocate resources can be subverted just as well in academia as in any other industry. What management measures, the team prioritises.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"></category><category term="Career"></category><category term="Corporate"></category><category term="London"></category></entry><entry><title>Move</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/move.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-07-08T12:26:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-07-08T12:26:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-07-08:/move.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Training&amp;rsquo;s&amp;nbsp;over&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="ambition"&gt;Ambition&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I was 15, one of my ambitions has been to be an entrepreneur. I used to joke with my dad about buying him a nice boat one&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life so far has been predominantly about education, and that stage is over now. I’m walking away from what I&amp;rsquo;ve come to see as a lifestyle and career that has too many contradictions, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense to live like this. Ultimately I want to develop multiple sources of passive income. I want to&amp;nbsp;create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="summer-2017"&gt;Summer&amp;nbsp;2017&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last few months have been intense, with some weeks leaving me feeling ambitious and energetic, and others feeling anxious and overwhelmed. I need to get better at defining a goal, taking the quickest path there, and ignoring interesting&amp;nbsp;distractions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ritsya is brave enough and imaginative enough to force me to think big and consider how to live a better life. My biggest fear is that I screw it up, shooting myself in the foot and Ritsya and my daughter also. We were headed safely to an unremarkable existence and it would be terrible to swap that for something worse. That won&amp;rsquo;t&amp;nbsp;happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that I make better decisions and produce my best work under pressure, I thrive when I&amp;rsquo;m perceived as an underdog. I need to accept this without using it as a reason to be foolish. Whilst I don’t have a clear plan, or direction, or goal, (I have many of them) I’ve got skills and I want to see what I can make. I’ll never do my best work, using my most productive combination of skills and experiences, if I’m a cog in someone else&amp;rsquo;s&amp;nbsp;machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s safer being an employee than self-employed. I guess the price of removing self-employment risks is the difference between the value you generate for your employer and what you’re paid. I think those risks are overpriced, and most people are more capable than they realise. Sometimes you have to walk into a situation to find out how to make the most of it. And sometimes you have to leave a place in order to gain&amp;nbsp;perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="autumn-2016"&gt;Autumn&amp;nbsp;2016&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year my boss gave me some advice that was supposed to be encouraging. I’d requested to reduce my involvement with some stuff that was unrelated to my job so that I could contribute more to my team and still maintain some semblance of a work/life&amp;nbsp;balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My boss was pretty clear that reducing my involvement in the extra stuff would not be possible. During our conversation he advised me not to worry about how much I contributed to the team because “the work will get done anyway”. This was meant to be encouraging, but instead removed any conviction that the work I did was&amp;nbsp;important.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"></category><category term="Lifestyle"></category></entry><entry><title>Flee</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/flee.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-07-04T08:42:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-07-04T08:42:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-07-04:/flee.html</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Summer children &lt;/br&gt;
squeal and shriek, &lt;br&gt;
Watch wars. &lt;br&gt;
Excitement mounts. &lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How exotic. &lt;/br&gt;
Unexpectedly, &lt;br&gt;
Death arrives. &lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grow-up&lt;br&gt;
Grow old&lt;br&gt;
Face death &lt;br&gt;
Evade evil.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t tire. &lt;/br&gt;
World is fragile.&lt;br&gt;
Towers burn,&lt;br&gt;
Bridges bludgeon,&lt;br&gt;
Markets stab. &lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Got to get&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"></category><category term="Poetry"></category></entry><entry><title>Understanding VC Investment</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/investment.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-09T23:03:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-06-09T23:03:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-06-09:/investment.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;How to pitch to a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VC&lt;/span&gt;: Market, Management, Model,&amp;nbsp;Momentum&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I attended the &lt;a href="http://www.lis-summit.com/"&gt;Lisbon Investment Summit&lt;/a&gt; in June and wrote about my experiences &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/lis17.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. One of the best sessions was with &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Boris_Golden"&gt;Boris Golden&lt;/a&gt; called &amp;ldquo;Understand Investment&amp;rdquo;. These are my&amp;nbsp;notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;VC&lt;/span&gt;&amp;rsquo;s are seeking to identify high-potential startups, and then support and fund&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are looking for something that is innovative and&amp;nbsp;unproven.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A startup is not a company but an organisation searching for a business&amp;nbsp;model,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whilst executing and discovering a scalable way to&amp;nbsp;grow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Startups need money for ambitious but credible growth&amp;nbsp;plans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A typical stake for a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VC&lt;/span&gt; could be roughly&amp;nbsp;20%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;VC&lt;/span&gt;&amp;rsquo;s want an exit price of at least 100m, otherwise their business models don&amp;rsquo;t work&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$10m can seem a lot for a founder with a 30% stake, but it&amp;rsquo;s not enough to attract VCs, so aim&amp;nbsp;higher.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-to-pitch"&gt;How to&amp;nbsp;pitch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify specific people with real&amp;nbsp;needs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Size of&amp;nbsp;market&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why&amp;nbsp;now?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is your clear competitive advantage - why can no-one else do&amp;nbsp;this?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="market"&gt;Market&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find a large and attractive&amp;nbsp;market…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="management"&gt;Management&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build a smart, skilled and cohesive&amp;nbsp;team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With a strong ability to deliver quickly and to learn&amp;nbsp;quickly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That is ready to go big whatever it&amp;nbsp;takes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With a unique vision and&amp;nbsp;project-fit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="model"&gt;Model&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Valuable and differentiated&amp;nbsp;products&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Efficient go-to-market and growth&amp;nbsp;channels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Profitable monetisation&amp;nbsp;strategy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scalability and&amp;nbsp;defensibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="momentum"&gt;Momentum&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show traction and that you&amp;rsquo;ve cracked the important&amp;nbsp;problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show ambitous and credible growth&amp;nbsp;plans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With a capital-efficient growth&amp;nbsp;model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And a clear strategy to scale and&amp;nbsp;win&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Entrepreneurship"></category><category term="LIS"></category><category term="FinTech"></category><category term="Startup"></category><category term="Founder"></category></entry><entry><title>How to be an ambitious founder in Europe</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/ambitious.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-09T21:55:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-06-09T21:55:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-06-09:/ambitious.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Creating something that matters is hard. Learn to leverage your time, you can never get it back. Being a successful founder is not impossible, it is always&amp;nbsp;exciting.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Whilst at the &lt;a href="http://www.lis-summit.com/"&gt;Lisbon Investment Summit&lt;/a&gt; I went to a session called &amp;ldquo;What it means to be ambitious for founders in Europe&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/daedalium?lang=en"&gt;Oussama Ammar&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve written generally about the summit &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/lis17.html"&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oussama spoke with passion and humour. It&amp;rsquo;s clear that he cares about encouraging would-be founders and confronting some of the cultural hurdles that exist in Europe. These are my notes from the&amp;nbsp;session:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are serious about building something that matters then you have a great and exciting future&amp;nbsp;ahead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can never predict who will be successful and who will fail. There are a lot of dumb successful people and clever founders can&amp;nbsp;fail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s really important to learn how to leverage your time effectively. You can lose anything else and get it back but you can never recover the time you&amp;rsquo;ve already&amp;nbsp;spent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The only way to succeed is to try&amp;nbsp;hard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s hard to do something that&amp;nbsp;matters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Europe you need to be more ambitious than average (measured against other countries) because the environment makes it harder to be an entrepreneur. (Attitudes to risk, comfort, security, expectations of failure.. are all unhelpful for&amp;nbsp;founders.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not impossible, just harder. So be more&amp;nbsp;ambitious.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everyone is replaceable, no-one is&amp;nbsp;unique.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can always lose money and replace it. There is so much money in the&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take a look at Crunchbase and see the failure rate for companies that raised $1m - $10m, it is the same rate for those that raised&amp;nbsp;$10m+.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you lose money on a project you will learn things from that experience and you can leverage that&amp;nbsp;learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;… But you will never get back the time you&amp;nbsp;spent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zombies are companies that make enough money to survive but not enough to provide joy to the people in the company - aim high&amp;nbsp;and…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starting a company is a big deal, like starting a marriage. Think hard about what you will be doing, what problem you are trying to solve, who you will be working&amp;nbsp;with. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Europe there is not enough money to go around and this makes pitching hard. Silicon Valley doesn&amp;rsquo;t have this&amp;nbsp;problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On average a startup in Europe will raise less than a startup in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USA&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Europe is irrationally concerned about risk. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USA&lt;/span&gt; is less concerned with risk and this is very&amp;nbsp;helpful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So be pragmatic about&amp;nbsp;risk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Incorporate in London where the laws are good, even if you don&amp;rsquo;t want to operate in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt;. It has a better designed system of corporate law. Estonia is also&amp;nbsp;good. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="best-european-city-for-founders"&gt;Best European city for&amp;nbsp;founders&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;London, Paris,&amp;nbsp;Berlin..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There isn&amp;rsquo;t a best city because none are&amp;nbsp;holistic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;London has the&amp;nbsp;money&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paris has engineering and product development (and no-one outside Paris knows the products&amp;nbsp;exist)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Berlin has automation and execution, execution and&amp;nbsp;scaling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…You need to draw on all 3 of these cities, which when taken together can surpass Silicon&amp;nbsp;Valley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="anecdotes"&gt;Anecdotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The founder of Slack lives in Vancouver with his wife and kids. He spends 1 day each week in California and everyone thinks Slack is Californian due to good marketing. Forget national pride, be pragmatic. Leverage the&amp;nbsp;internet. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The founders of Airbnb would fly from New York to California for 1 day each week. They were originally in California where AirBnB started, but decided that if they could make it work in New York then AirBnB would be a success, so they moved to New York and flew back for meetings , etc. If you ask Europeans to come to a meeting in London (which is not as far as California is from New York) people start complaining and deciding they can&amp;rsquo;t be&amp;nbsp;bothered. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Entrepreneurship"></category><category term="LIS"></category><category term="Startup"></category><category term="FinTech"></category><category term="Europe"></category></entry><entry><title>The Lisbon Investment Summit</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/lis17.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-09T17:53:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-06-09T17:53:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-06-09:/lis17.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Lisbon investment Summit was full of Investors as well as Founders. The sessions were good enough but the real value was in the&amp;nbsp;conversations.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I attended the &lt;a href="http://www.lis-summit.com/"&gt;Lisbon Investment Summit&lt;/a&gt; on June 6 and 7 as part of the &lt;a href="http://www.oula.la"&gt;Oula.la&lt;/a&gt; InsurTech startup team with &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jd_sullivan?lang=en-gb"&gt;John Sullivan&lt;/a&gt;. It was the first startup conference I&amp;rsquo;d been to and I arrived hoping to have some useful conversations and understand more about the Fintech and startup spaces in Europe. As usual I wanted to focus on tech, finance and&amp;nbsp;blockchains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="who-was-there"&gt;Who was&amp;nbsp;there&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As well as some outstanding sessions there was a high ratio of investors to startups. This made talking to VCs, bankers and M&amp;amp;A lawyers really easy. I was happy to meet a London-based and Fintech-focussed &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VC&lt;/span&gt; when I sat down to have lunch, and thanks to interrupting a session to ask blockchain related questions on Day 1, a banker struck up a conversation with me over breakfast the next day. I met a lot of people across many relevant roles, and once I&amp;rsquo;ve worked through my notes and my new collection of business cards I hope to have some great follow-up&amp;nbsp;meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="useful-sessions"&gt;Useful&amp;nbsp;Sessions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most useful sessions for me&amp;nbsp;were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/ambitious.html"&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/span&gt;What it means to be ambitious for founders in Europe&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/daedalium?lang=en"&gt;Oussama Ammar&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="https://www.thefamily.co"&gt;TheFamily&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/investment.html"&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/span&gt;Understanding Investment&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Boris_Golden"&gt;Boris Golden&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="https://www.partechventures.com"&gt;Partech&amp;nbsp;Ventures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/span&gt;Building successful businesses on blockchain technologies&amp;rdquo; a panel discussion moderated by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/kloaec?lang=en"&gt;Kevin Loaec&lt;/a&gt;, founder of the &lt;a href="http://chainsmiths.com/"&gt;Chainsmiths&lt;/a&gt; blockchain consultancy, and including &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mir_btc"&gt;Mir Serena Liponi&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="http://www.blockchainlab.it/"&gt;Blockchain&amp;nbsp;Lab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blockchain session was valuable because it&amp;rsquo;s unusual to meet people who have been working in the blockchain space for several years. I&amp;rsquo;m always wary of being distracted by the hype and noise around developments in the blockchain space so I appreciated hearing some informed and level-headed&amp;nbsp;opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="political-support"&gt;Political&amp;nbsp;Support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opening session included a speech from the Mayor of Lisbon and the next day opened with a speech from the Secretary of Industry. Both speeches conveyed an open and progressive attitude to international cooperation aimed at promoting and supporting founders and startups in Portugal. The warm words were supported by practical measures including tax incentives and a state-backed scheme to match amounts contributed by private investors. It was really refreshing to hear a politician extol the virtues of multinational cooperation and bringing different cultures into Portugal. I wish Britain could do this&amp;nbsp;too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the topic of Brexit, which inevitably arose due to London&amp;rsquo;s present role as a centre of finance and innovation, it seems Europe is still expecting the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; to come to its senses, and cannot understand why it&amp;rsquo;s destroying its goodwill and reputation so&amp;nbsp;thoroughly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="overall"&gt;Overall&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two days in Lisbon were full of useful and energetic conversations and it was a great experience pitching &lt;a href="http://www.oula.la"&gt;Oula.la&lt;/a&gt; multiple times and talking about what we&amp;rsquo;re trying to do and how blockchains are a part of that. The opportunities to meet founders and investors are invaluable for making informed decisions. Lisbon is a beautiful city which I found easy to get around and always felt safe in. It&amp;rsquo;s also refreshingly &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/london.html"&gt;affordable!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Panoramic street" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/lis4.JPG"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Google talks" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/lis3.JPG"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Statue" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/lis1.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Entrepreneurship"></category><category term="FinTech"></category><category term="Startup"></category><category term="Europe"></category><category term="LIS"></category></entry><entry><title>London Rent vs. London Salaries</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/london.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-12T22:55:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-05-12T22:55:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-05-12:/london.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Living in London is only financially possible if you are either single or household income is more than&amp;nbsp;£60k/year.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Living in London is expensive, everyone in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; knows this. Everyone knows that this is mostly due to the price of property, which we all enjoy talking&amp;nbsp;about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve lived here for 3 years now, and when my wife and I were both working we lived comfortably. Two incomes under one roof is just fine. Not as fine as in many other cities, but reasonable. Just over a year ago my first child was born, and now that my wife&amp;rsquo;s maternity pay has ended we are a single income household. This is not&amp;nbsp;fine. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though I earn almost £50k/year, and any salary increase will be taxed at 40%, I cannot cover essential day-to-day costs. I&amp;rsquo;m in the 40% tax bracket, and my basic monthly outgoings exceed my monthly take home pay by £400. If my employer wanted to pay me enough to cover essential costs, it would cost them approximately double the shortfall due to tax. None of this makes&amp;nbsp;sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salaries and living expenses have become really&amp;nbsp;disconnected. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most people the most obvious way to increase wealth is to buy property. Mortgage repayments are cheaper than rent, and the value of the property increases over time. Double win. But there is a big hurdle to overcome before this is possible - saving money for a deposit on a house is often impossible without external help (i.e. the &amp;ldquo;Bank of Mum and Dad&amp;rdquo;), because so much of the money earnt must be spent on rent&amp;nbsp;first. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a trap. Repayments on a mortgage are cheaper than paying rent, but you cannot save enough for a deposit&amp;nbsp;because;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;so much of your salary goes to paying rent&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,&amp;nbsp;and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the average cost of a &lt;em&gt;flat&lt;/em&gt; in London is 500k&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, which means a 5% deposit is £25k — which is a higher deposit than you would need anywhere else in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt;, despite being the place you are least able to accumulate&amp;nbsp;it. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if my partner went back to work and we put our baby in childcare? Childcare is not cheap, and working would need to bring in more than the cost of childcare. This requires a higher than average salary from a graduate job, (which is the life stage when people might reasonably start having children), so unless both parents are unusually high earners that option isnt viable&amp;nbsp;either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Living in London is only financially possible if you are either single or household income is more than&amp;nbsp;£60k/year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;d be lucky to find a 1 bedroom flat for less than £1000/month&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href="http://www.rightmove.co.uk/house-prices/London.html"&gt;Rightmove&lt;/a&gt;, an estate agent with some useful price statistics.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"></category><category term="London"></category><category term="Rent"></category></entry><entry><title>Spare time</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/spare-time.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-13T21:15:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-08-13T21:15:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2016-08-13:/spare-time.html</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a list of interests I want to consider pursuing. I wrote it when I began to study for my last set of exams and my mind filled with things I&amp;rsquo;d rather be doing instead. Some of these interests are just me reacting to having no spare time for a few months, but others are decent goals and projects. Temporarily losing my spare time made me value it&amp;nbsp;more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="free-time" src="/images/spare_time.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote this post so that I could compare what I thought was important when I was busy to when I wasn&amp;rsquo;t. Writing the list allowed me to move on without forgetting. Here&amp;rsquo;s a break down of each&amp;nbsp;item:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/span&gt;Run 10k in 50 minutes&amp;rdquo; - This is easier than I imagined. When I wrote the list I could barely run 2k without stopping, but intended to go for a weekly run whilst studying. I&amp;rsquo;ve struggled to stay energetic and healthy during previous exam phases, so now I have a rule that I must do some mild exercise even if I think I can&amp;rsquo;t spare the time. I find running really lowers my stress levels, and increasing my heart rate and working up a sweat lets me sleep better
    and concentrate for longer. After a few weeks of minimal running, I could run 5k easily. If I kept at it, 10k in 50 mins would be easy. But point&amp;nbsp;2&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/span&gt;Be Insanity strong&amp;rdquo; - As in, do the Insanity workout programme. Again. I thought about it and decided to do P90x instead. Week 1 is going&amp;nbsp;great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/span&gt;Read the bible habitually&amp;rdquo; - When I was 17 I found out about Jesus and became a Christian. In the months and years after that I&amp;rsquo;d regularly read my bible almost every day and pray a lot. I wanted to understand, so I set a goal of 5 chapters each&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read through the new testament repeatedly and read most of the old testament during this time. I knew the scriptures well enough that a lot of sermons became boring and obvious - I&amp;rsquo;d already studied the bible passage being used. During this time I remember being aware that the way I thought was different to how it would have been otherwise. My perspectives were long-term and less me focused. I thought about what I was reading instead of the days&amp;rsquo; headlines or social chatter. I remember enjoying the benefits and thinking that I should keep this habit. The reasons why I think Christianity is so wonderful are well summarised in &lt;a href="http://messages.destinyedinburgh.com/sermon/the-gospel-we-preach-a-message-for-leaders"&gt;this sermon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s now 10 years later, and whilst my convictions are strong, my knowledge of the bible is sadly pretty fuzzy. My thinking is clouded by the perspectives contained in the media I consume and the conversations I&amp;rsquo;m part of. I strongly suspect I would be acting and
thinking differently if I read my bible more, but I don&amp;rsquo;t know what those differences would be. Trouble is, it&amp;rsquo;s often not obvious what the immediate benefits of reading the bible are, you have to work for it a bit. Praying for help is effective. The books in the bible were written to last through the ages and across all cultures, so it&amp;rsquo;s not surprising that they&amp;rsquo;re not as easy to read as something written for an English speaker in a hurry. I should stop being in a hurry, and stop prioritising only quantifiable&amp;nbsp;goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/span&gt;Think more&amp;rdquo; - On a similar note to 3, but less supernatural. If I spent less time consuming content and a little more looking around me or walking, I reckon I&amp;rsquo;d be more self-aware and make better decisions. This would probably lead to a happier, more satisfying&amp;nbsp;life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/span&gt;Pray more&amp;rdquo; - I don&amp;rsquo;t know why, but the creator of the universe wants me to talk and share my life with him. He cares about me. This makes no sense to me, at all. If I was God, I would not go out of my way to consider the views and concerns of a very flawed human. But
    when I pray, my prayers are very often answered. I should ask him about&amp;nbsp;this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/span&gt;Amazon seller?&amp;rdquo; - Amazon have this &amp;ldquo;Fulfilled by Amazon&amp;rdquo; service,
    which means you don&amp;rsquo;t even need to hold the stock you want to sell.
    If I choose the right products, import them cheaply from China and
    reselling  them on Amazon at a profit, I end up quids in for minimal
    effort and manageable risk. Sounds&amp;nbsp;intriguing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/span&gt;Blog about interesting data&amp;rdquo; - Here I am, blogging. I should stick
    to the main topic and get technical. I was inspired by this
    &lt;a href="http://www.curiousgnu.com/"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; in&amp;nbsp;particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/span&gt;Finish Coursera&amp;rdquo; - The data science specialization is great! It&amp;rsquo;s in R, and I want to focus on Python, but I&amp;rsquo;d still like to do it. I need to consider the opportunity cost of the time committed,&amp;nbsp;though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/span&gt;Read for fun, history, fiction&amp;rdquo; - When I started my job, in April 2014, I was half way through &lt;a href="https://read.amazon.co.uk/kp/embed?asin=B00796LLLK&amp;amp;asin=B00796LLLK&amp;amp;preview=newtab&amp;amp;linkCode=kpe&amp;amp;ref_=cm_sw_r_kb_dp_GP2Rxb3Q8MYC4"&gt;Savage Continent&lt;/a&gt;, which is an eye-opening and eye-watering history of Europe in the years after World War 2. I see Europe through different eyes because of it. However I only got half way though, and since April &amp;lsquo;14 I never felt I had the free time or energy to pick it back up. This should change. When I was a researcher, and when I was a student, I had so much more opportunity to develop my own pursuits. Since entering the corporate world, I find myself fighting a war of attrition to exert my personality onto my lifestyle. &lt;/br&gt; &lt;/br&gt; Read for fiction&amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;m unconvinced. What do you have at the end of it? What can you do with it? Maybe I&amp;rsquo;ve just been reading the wrong authors, but I&amp;rsquo;m going to leave this for now. Sure, you could gain an appreciation of a different time or place, but that appreciation comes via the fictional characters and events, its secondary. What about abstract constructs, perspectives, morals&amp;hellip; things that history books are ill-suited for? Great fiction would be essential for exploring these. But for now, I&amp;rsquo;ll prioritise point 3.&lt;/br&gt;  &lt;/br&gt; &lt;iframe style="max-width: 100%; float:middle" src="https://read.amazon.co.uk/kp/card?asin=B00796LLLK&amp;amp;asin=B00796LLLK&amp;amp;preview=inline&amp;amp;linkCode=kpe&amp;amp;ref_=cm_sw_r_kb_dp_GP2Rxb3Q8MYC4" width="336" height="550" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; &lt;/br&gt; &lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/span&gt;Do a photography project&amp;rdquo; - This I would love to do, but probably won&amp;rsquo;t. It would be a luxury, and the opportunity cost would be too great right now. I&amp;rsquo;d like to shoot a series of black and white portraits, and turn them into large prints. I think good portrait photography is uniquely impactful and moving, choosing B&amp;amp;W removes distractions and leaves a subjects humanity more&amp;nbsp;exposed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/span&gt;Have a list of business/product ideas&amp;rdquo; - There&amp;rsquo;s no excuse for this
    one, anyone can have several good ideas. It&amp;rsquo;s turning them into
    reality that takes skill. Need to have the ideas first,&amp;nbsp;though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/span&gt;Do a law &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MOOC&lt;/span&gt;&amp;rdquo; - i.e Study particular areas of law, in my own time
    and at my own pace. I studied a tiny bit of law during the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACA&lt;/span&gt;, and
    realised employment law or contract law could be really useful.
    (Same for the tax system - another surprise). We only had a brief
    introduction though, so if I could find the time I&amp;rsquo;d like to know&amp;nbsp;more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/span&gt;Do an InfoSec or Network Security &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MOOC&lt;/span&gt;&amp;rdquo; - Its super interesting,
    but not likely to be a good use of&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/span&gt;Learn to fight - Krav Maga / &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MMA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;rdquo; - Ever since watching The Bourne
    Identity I&amp;rsquo;ve wanted to learn Krav Maga, and &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/LybrzdG96_8"&gt;Georges
    St-Pierre&lt;/a&gt; made me want to train
    for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MMA&lt;/span&gt;. For now though, I&amp;rsquo;ll do P90x. I can reconsider in 90&amp;nbsp;days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" class="embed-responsive-item" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/u0_8dzaNxhg" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;  &lt;br&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/span&gt;Get out of London&amp;rdquo; - My contract ends in April 2017, next summer
    will be a crossroads. I hate the commute, I hate being constantly
    rushed. Living in other cities has been a lot more&amp;nbsp;pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"></category><category term="Habits"></category><category term="Advice"></category><category term="Reflection"></category></entry><entry><title>How to wake up early</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/how-to-wake-up-early.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-06T22:04:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-08-06T22:04:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2016-08-06:/how-to-wake-up-early.html</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For years I&amp;rsquo;ve wished that I could wake up early and use the quiet
pre-breakfast hours for distraction-free productivity. And for years I
have spectacularly failed at this. I love the quiet, distraction-free
hours at the end of the day too, as well as waking up slowly.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many famous leaders and politicians are known to start their days early,
and I would like to be able to do this too. After years of trying and
failing, I have had a&amp;nbsp;break-through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The secret of waking up early is&amp;nbsp;this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Become a&amp;nbsp;parent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the first couple of months with a&amp;nbsp;new-born:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will be well-practiced at quickly waking up at previously
    unthinkable&amp;nbsp;times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will be used to operating on less sleep than you ever thought&amp;nbsp;possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your beautiful child will become a reliable alarm clock, waking you
    up at the crack of dawn with cute smiles and increasingly insistent
    demands that you get up, play and make&amp;nbsp;breakfast.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have the freedom to begin sleeping and working when you want, I still believe this is a great option. I bashed out a PhD in 3.5 years during which I usually woke up late and began to work around lunch time! - Glorious autonomy!&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"></category><category term="Productivity"></category><category term="Sleep"></category></entry></feed>