<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>JohnMathews.eu - Technical/Civil Engineering</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/feed/technical/civil-engineering.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://johnmathews.eu/</id><updated>2016-10-02T00:06:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Silos: Introduction to my doctorate research</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/silos.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-02T00:06:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-10-02T00:06:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2016-10-02:/silos.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this post, I want to introduce my doctorate research without assuming any engineering&amp;nbsp;knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="background"&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Spring 2010 until the Autumn of 2013, I was a PhD candidate living
in Vienna, Austria and working at the University of Natural Resources
and Life Sciences. Before working in Vienna, I completed my Masters
degree in Civil and Environmental Engineering at the University of&amp;nbsp;Edinburgh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My research quantified the effects of changing the amount of gravity
acting on granular materials as they poured out of a&amp;nbsp;silo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="4 silos" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/silos1/4_silos.jpeg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="granular materials" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/silos1/granular_materials.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My PhD thesis and the short presentation I used when I defended&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Granular materials are a broard class of materials that are
encountered everyday - salt, pills, breakfast cereal, sand, rice, soil,
landslides, salt are all granular materials. They are ubiquitous and occur in
many different sizes and&amp;nbsp;varieties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Silos are a common type of container for storing granular materials. You
pour the granular material in from the top, store it for a while, and
then dispense the material in controlled quantities from the&amp;nbsp;bottom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="research-focus"&gt;Research&amp;nbsp;focus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My research focussed on quantifying how changes in gravity affected the
material contained inside a silo, particularly whilst the silo was being
emptied. This is pertinent because engineers and scientists do not yet
have a scientific understanding of how granular materials behave. Whilst
gravity clearly affects a granular materials, we cannot say exactly&amp;nbsp;how.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means we can&amp;#8217;t use analytical methods to quantify the physics that
occur in a real system. Instead we use empirical methods
(approximations, guesses, rules-of-thumb, and knowledge of what worked
in previous similar situations). This isn&amp;#8217;t necessarily bad, but it is
less efficient and less reliable than an analytical&amp;nbsp;approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="research-techniques"&gt;Research&amp;nbsp;techniques&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="physical-modelling"&gt;Physical&amp;nbsp;modelling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I built a small model silo (30cm tall) and put it into quite a large centrifuge (3 metre diameter). By rotating the model silo around the centre of the centrifuge at a constant speed I could simulate a higher gravity. I added high-speed cameras, pressure sensors and weighing
scales so that I could measure how the material was moving once I opened the silo outlet and the silo began to empty. Photos of the experimental model I built can be seen&amp;nbsp;below. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="numerical-modelling"&gt;Numerical&amp;nbsp;modelling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also programmed a computer model (using the commercial &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PFC&lt;/span&gt; 3D software
and working in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FISH&lt;/span&gt; scripting language) to simulate and investigate
if the same behaviours could be observed numerically as&amp;nbsp;physically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The class of computer model I used is known as &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DEM&lt;/span&gt; (Discrete Element
Modelling). These models work by considering every grain of material individually, usually as a
sphere. If one sphere overlaps with another (i.e. the distance between
the two particle centres is less than the sum of their radiuses) then a
force proportional to the overlap size repels the two spheres away from
each other. This simple approach is repeated over every grain or particle in the model, and produces life like behaviour in many situations. It has many advantages over &amp;#8220;continuum&amp;#8221; based techniques that model groups of grains as if they were all just one big particle with
unusual properties. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DEM&lt;/span&gt; has one massive limitation, though. It requires huge amounts of computational resources - and this limits its use in industrial scenarios outside. Until computers become much, much more powerful, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DEM&lt;/span&gt; will only be used for theoretical research and niche&amp;nbsp;applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="results"&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When gravity increases by a factor of $x$, both the discharge rate and local velocities within the silo increase by  $\sqrt(x)$&amp;nbsp;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s good to know if you&amp;#8217;re planning on storing stuff on the moon, but it&amp;#8217;s also a useful step towards explaining exactly why bulk granular materials behave the way they&amp;nbsp;do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="more-information"&gt;More&amp;nbsp;Information&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An overview of my research, my doctorate thesis and published papers can
be downloaded below. PDFs containing 3D models and movies require flash
to render, and Adobe Reader Desktop must be used in order to view&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/Mathews_J_2013_thesis.pdf"&gt;PhD Thesis&amp;nbsp;(2013)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/Mathews-Wu_2016_Model-tests-of-silo-discharge-in-a-geotechnical-centrifuge.pdf"&gt;Modeling silo discharge in a centrifuge (Powder&amp;nbsp;Technology)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/Mathews-etal_2013_Experimental-investigation-of-flow-and-segregation-behaviour-of-bulk-solids-in-silos-under-high-gravity-conditions.pdf"&gt;Experimental investigation of flow and segregation behaviour of bulk solids in silos under high gravity conditions (Particles 2013 conference&amp;nbsp;proceedings)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/Cabrera-et-al.pdf"&gt;Centrifugal modelling of granular flows (Eurofuge conference&amp;nbsp;proceedings)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/Mathews_J_2013_Defence_presentation.pdf"&gt;Overview of research (PhD defence,&amp;nbsp;2013)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Model silo and camera" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/silos2/model_silo_camera.jpeg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Model silo inside centrifuge" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/silos2/model_silo_in_centrifuge.jpeg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Silo opening mechanism" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/silos2/silo_open_mechanism.jpeg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Centrifuge" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/silos2/centrifuge.jpeg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Silo Model" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/silos2/silo_render.jpeg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Silo wall pressure mesasurements" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/silos2/silo_pressure_pads.jpeg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Particle Image Velocimetry result showing average flow velocities" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/silos2/silo_piv.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Technical/Civil Engineering"></category><category term="Doctorate"></category><category term="Granular Flow"></category><category term="Granular Materials"></category><category term="PhD"></category><category term="Research"></category><category term="Engineering"></category><category term="Silo"></category><category term="Thesis"></category><category term="Vienna"></category></entry></feed>