<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>blog - Bitcoin</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="feeds/bitcoin.tag.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2019-01-24T12:57:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Bitcoin Lightning</title><link href="bitcoin-lightning.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-01-24T12:57:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-01-24T12:57:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-01-24:bitcoin-lightning.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I set up a  node on the Bitcoin Lightning network and sent a payment of $0.005 which confirmed in a few&amp;nbsp;seconds.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the largest obstacles (second only to privacy in my opinion) to widespread adoption of Bitcoin is its limited volume. Bitcoin cannot faciliate payments fast enough such that it could compete with Visa or&amp;nbsp;Mastercard. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most interesting solution to this problem is the &lt;a href="https://lightning.network/"&gt;Lightning protocol&lt;/a&gt; - a separate protocol that sits ontop of the Bitcoin protocol (a so-called &amp;#8216;Layer 2&amp;#8217; solution). Lightning uses hashed time locked contracts (HTLCs) to trustlessly and privately move transactions off-chain. This allows payments to be faster, cheaper and more frequent. It also has interesting implications for enhancing&amp;nbsp;privacy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of resources about what the Lightning network is, why it&amp;#8217;s neccesary and how it works. There are also several good guides available about how to set up and maintain a node. I used a Raspberry Pi with an external hdd. It took a few attempts, mostly because it&amp;#8217;s my first time working with an unix operating system and I tried to move a swap file to a disk that wasnt formmated as&amp;nbsp;ext4&amp;#8230; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I&amp;#8217;ve opened and closed some channels, connected to peers, and made some transactions. I even bought some stickers using&amp;nbsp;Lightning!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find my node using these&amp;nbsp;details:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Alias: &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;johnmathews.eu&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
Public Key: &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;025469b50de125b4cd97457c0da67365519f0cd0f441c2ced0978fb6ae7802ae76&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
IP address: &lt;span class="m"&gt;85&lt;/span&gt;.145.183.145
Port: &lt;span class="m"&gt;9735&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some useful&amp;nbsp;resources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://explorer.acinq.co/n/025469b50de125b4cd97457c0da67365519f0cd0f441c2ced0978fb6ae7802ae76"&gt;Lightning network&amp;nbsp;explorer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://1ml.com/node/025469b50de125b4cd97457c0da67365519f0cd0f441c2ced0978fb6ae7802ae76"&gt;Lightning node&amp;nbsp;information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://incoherency.co.uk/blog/stories/spelunking-ln.html"&gt;Interesting things to&amp;nbsp;do&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Disintermediation"></category><category term="Bitcoin"></category><category term="Lightning"></category><category term="Crypto"></category></entry><entry><title>Sync a BTC node, quickly</title><link href="sync-bitcoin-core-node.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-13T20:34:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-10-13T20:34:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:None,2018-10-13:sync-bitcoin-core-node.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sync a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BTC&lt;/span&gt; node for the first time, quickly, on a spinning disk by moving chainstate to an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSD&lt;/span&gt; and symlinking to&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In order to run your own bitcoin node, or lightning node, you&amp;#8217;ll need to
download the entire bitcoin blockchain and then validate it. This takes ages on
a magnetic disk due to the random access speed of the contents of the
chainstate&amp;nbsp;directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To remove this bottleneck, move the chainstate directory to an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSD&lt;/span&gt; (its only
a few &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GB&lt;/span&gt;) and symlink to it from the bitcoin data directory. More details are
&lt;a href="https://en.bitcoin.it/wiki/Splitting_the_data_directory"&gt;on the Bitcoin wiki&lt;/a&gt;.
When the sync is complete, replace the symlink with the actual chainstate&amp;nbsp;directory.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Disintermediation"></category><category term="Bitcoin"></category><category term="btc-core"></category><category term="Blockchain"></category><category term="Node"></category></entry><entry><title>How to buy Bitcoin</title><link href="buying-btc.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-12-07T09:56:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-12-07T09:56:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:None,2017-12-07:buying-btc.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;What to consider before buying&amp;nbsp;Bitcoin&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently a few friends have asked me how they can buy Bitcoin. Here are a few things that come to&amp;nbsp;mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not your financial advisor and this is not financial advice. These are my personal opinions&amp;nbsp;only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#8217;t invest what you can&amp;#8217;t afford to&amp;nbsp;lose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the price falls 50%, you need to be able to wait whilst the price&amp;nbsp;recovers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write down the&amp;nbsp;following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How much you can afford to invest. Consider how much cash you will need over the next year, how long it would take to recover any losses,&amp;nbsp;etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How long you want to invest it&amp;nbsp;for&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How much you want to&amp;nbsp;make&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will need to get good at identifying and ignoring the following, even from your&amp;nbsp;friends:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hype&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fake&amp;nbsp;news &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fear, Uncertainty, Doubt (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;FUD&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#8217;t trust.&amp;nbsp;Verify.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Point 5 is really important and one of the best reasons to invest - money has an intensely psychological quality about it, and crypto currencies are the most intense trading experience there is right&amp;nbsp;now. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By putting something you care about in a risky situation (it is risky) you will experience anxiety and excitement. You need to control your psychology and identity when other people are trying to manipulate you. This is useful in all areas of&amp;nbsp;life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost no one has a clue what&amp;#8217;s happening. Conventional economists and traders certainly don&amp;#8217;t. This is crypto-economics and the rules haven&amp;#8217;t been worked out yet. We&amp;#8217;ve never had this tech before, and the internet has made everything - communication and innovation - much quicker. This is a powerful combination of factors and we haven&amp;#8217;t seen them play out&amp;nbsp;before. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take some time to read about the fundamentals and understand the tech as much as you can. Think about why people would behave in certain ways and what makes bitcoin useful, or not. Get started on this today, it will take some&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;YouTube has a tonne of videos, and these two sites are good and detailed (&lt;a href="http://lopp.net/bitcoin.html"&gt;one&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://nakamotoinstitute.org/"&gt;two&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Twitter has a lot of current and new information, but also a lot of bots and scammers spreading hype and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FUD&lt;/span&gt; (see point 4). You can see who I follow on &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/johnmathews/following"&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;re going to lose sleep over your investment, invest&amp;nbsp;less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#8217;t buy at an all time high. Do your research, wait for the price to correct.  &lt;em&gt;Prices fall.&lt;/em&gt; The &lt;a href="https://uk.tradingview.com/x/TrL9SA7o/"&gt;chart&lt;/a&gt; below shows the 20 day and 55 day moving average compared to the daily price. My opinion is that by early January the price will have returned to between the 20 day and 55 day average before beginning to rise&amp;nbsp;again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.coinbase.com"&gt;Coinbase&lt;/a&gt; is a user friendly and reputable exchange, there are other good exchanges&amp;nbsp;too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#8217;t make financial decisions when you&amp;#8217;re feeling rushed. Check your&amp;nbsp;psychology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;ve bought some Bitcoin or other cryptocurrencies, don&amp;#8217;t store them on an exchange. Transfer them to a wallet that you control. If you don&amp;#8217;t own your private key, you don&amp;#8217;t own the asset. If you don&amp;#8217;t know what that means, go to point&amp;nbsp;8. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leave a comment if you think I&amp;#8217;ve missed something or if you&amp;nbsp;disagree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="BTC hype" src="images/btc_hype.png"&gt;&lt;a href="https://uk.tradingview.com/x/TrL9SA7o/"&gt;&lt;p align="center"&gt;bigger&amp;nbsp;chart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I’m not your financial advisor and this is not financial advice. These are my personal opinions&amp;nbsp;only.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Disintermediation"></category><category term="Bitcoin"></category></entry><entry><title>Bitcoin compared to gold</title><link href="bitcoin-vs-gold.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-11-21T17:35:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-11-21T17:35:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:None,2017-11-21:bitcoin-vs-gold.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin will become a safe haven asset comparable to&amp;nbsp;gold&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A safe haven asset is something to buy during economic uncertainty. Historically, the safest asset you can buy has been gold. This is not because of anything inherently special about gold, but because that is what people believe to be the best long term method of storing&amp;nbsp;value. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People believe gold is special because they assume that in future other people will believe it&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;special.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Criteria for a safe haven&amp;nbsp;asset&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A safe-haven asset must fulfil the following&amp;nbsp;criteria:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Price isn&amp;#8217;t controlled by any single party, including a state or bank. The market is spread out beyond the reach of any one organisation. This is important because an asset which is issued, controlled or backed by an organisation has its value tied to the health of that&amp;nbsp;organisation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supply isn&amp;#8217;t controlled by any single party, including a state, bank or anyone else - it exists naturally and the rate at which it&amp;#8217;s produced or traded is beyond the control of any one&amp;nbsp;organisation. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supply is limited. The effort required to create the asset naturally limits the&amp;nbsp;supply.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The asset doesn&amp;#8217;t wear out or&amp;nbsp;expire.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;#8217;s prohibitively expensive to&amp;nbsp;fake.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Almost everyone considers it to be precious and&amp;nbsp;valuable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can be stored and transported simply. It&amp;#8217;s not delicate or&amp;nbsp;volatile.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For these reasons, and because of historical consensus, people have been happy to use gold as a store of value in times of economic uncertainty or for long durations. Other assets also meets these requirements to lesser&amp;nbsp;extents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bitcoin compared to&amp;nbsp;gold&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider why gold is so good as a safe haven asset and long term value store. For all the reasons above, bitcoin is better, except one: At present, not many people consider it to be precious and valuable, so the market is small. This will change as confidence and awareness increases, and the eco-system of services and applications&amp;nbsp;matures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fundamentals are already&amp;nbsp;established:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A decentralised network ensures that Bitcoin can&amp;#8217;t be regulated or controlled by a single government or organisation. The network can&amp;#8217;t be turned off or&amp;nbsp;controlled.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The present and future rate of supply is publicly available and inviolable. This increases market efficiency and creates more rational pricing than a market where the rate of supply is&amp;nbsp;unverifiable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supply is naturally (mathematically) limited using proof of work&amp;nbsp;algorithms. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bitcoin doesn&amp;#8217;t corrode or wear&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bitcoin is impossible to&amp;nbsp;fake.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bitcoin can be stored and transported more easily than gold. - If you can remember 24 words you can transport all your bitcoin effortlessly where ever you&amp;nbsp;go. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Read&amp;nbsp;more&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href="http://www.runtogold.com/the-great-bitcoin-bull-market-of-2017/"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;, published a week after I wrote this post, looks at different factors to consider when evaluating Bitcoin&amp;#8217;s value. It goes into a lot of detail, relative to what I&amp;#8217;ve seen in other&amp;nbsp;articles. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Disintermediation"></category><category term="bitcoin"></category><category term="gold"></category><category term="safe haven"></category></entry><entry><title>Hardware Wallets</title><link href="wallet.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-11-08T16:09:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-11-08T16:09:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:None,2017-11-08:wallet.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Current hardware wallets are technically good but are awkward to use. A good solution would solve the following&amp;nbsp;problems:&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;What is a hardware&amp;nbsp;wallet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A hardware wallet (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallet) is a physical device that stores the information required to access digital currency or assets. It is plugged into a computer via &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; in order to initiate or confirm transactions on the Bitcoin, Ethereum or other digital asset blockchain&amp;nbsp;networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are a secure method of storing cryptographic data. They are so secure that they can be used on a compromised computer. All that is needed to access funds using a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallet (in addition to the device itself) is a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PIN&lt;/span&gt; code which the user chooses. A single &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallet can store multiple currencies in multiple&amp;nbsp;accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallets are an easier solution than remembering a good password, and safer than storing the data in a file on my computer or&amp;nbsp;online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best known hardware wallet brands are &lt;a href="https://www.ledgerwallet.com/"&gt;Ledger&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://trezor.io/"&gt;Trezor&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallets are technically great, but their size and shape creates a bad user experience. A good hardware wallet should be convenient to use multiple times each day, like a credit card&amp;nbsp;is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Current hardware wallets don&amp;#8217;t fit into a (money) wallet and people don&amp;#8217;t want to carry more any objects in their pockets. They are too big and are a bad&amp;nbsp;shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallets look like they might belong on a keyring, but it&amp;#8217;s inconvenient and insecure to attach a credit card to a keyring and the same is true for an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallet. I might store my keys on a hook by my door, but I would never leave my wallet there overnight. I often want to keep my keys and money separate because I need my keys when I’m near my house, where I don’t need to buy stuff, and I need my money when I’m away from my house where I don’t need to unlock&amp;nbsp;anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to keep my bank cards and cash together in one safe place, and I don’t want to carry around a dongle as well. It&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;inconvenient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easier to have a separate dongle lost or stolen than something that would fit next to my credit card in my wallet. The inconvenience is a barrier to enjoying the advantages of digital&amp;nbsp;currencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;goal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallet that is the size and shape of a credit card, it could be 3 times thicker than a credit card and still fit in a normal wallet. It&amp;nbsp;needs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a display - it could be a low resolution b&amp;amp;w&amp;nbsp;display&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;two or more&amp;nbsp;buttons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to  plug into a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;port&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;securely sign transactions and create&amp;nbsp;addresses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Engineering"></category><category term="wallet"></category><category term="crypto"></category><category term="blockchain"></category><category term="bitcoin"></category></entry><entry><title>Encryption</title><link href="encryption.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-30T23:04:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-08-30T23:04:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-08-30:encryption.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Blockchains use Elliptical Curve Cryptography (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ECC&lt;/span&gt;) to authenticate users and authorise transactions. These notes introduce the field of cryptography and explains how modern cryptographic methods work. I wrote them to teach myself about encryption &lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin with the absolute basics, encryption generally works by taking a message and representing …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Blockchains use Elliptical Curve Cryptography (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ECC&lt;/span&gt;) to authenticate users and authorise transactions. These notes introduce the field of cryptography and explains how modern cryptographic methods work. I wrote them to teach myself about encryption &lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin with the absolute basics, encryption generally works by taking a message and representing it as a series of numbers &lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; which are then turned into a series of random looking numbers. Decryption works by turning the random looking numbers back into the original&amp;nbsp;message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The history of Cryptography can be split into classical and modern eras. Modern cryptography began in 1977 with the introduction of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSA&lt;/span&gt; and Diffie-Hellman algorithms.  Until then, Cryptography required using a single key (the secret code) to encrypt and decrypt the message. This was transferred from sender to receiver secretly, but not cryptographically. In classical cryptography, the code is a &lt;em&gt;shared&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;secret.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The modern era removed the requirement for a shared secret and instead used number theory as a basis for quantifying the strength of an encryption method. The strength of a modern cryptographic technique is quantifiable and provable by reference to number theory, rather than a users ability to transport or transfer a secret&amp;nbsp;code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern cryptography is defined by Public Key Cryptographic systems. They use one key (code) for encryption and another for decryption. The encryption key can be made public without any risk of the message being decrypted, and is therefore known as the public key. The key used to decrypt data is the private key, and must not be revealed. If a message is encrypted with the public key it can only be decrypted with the private&amp;nbsp;key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public Key Cryptographic (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PKC&lt;/span&gt;) systems use algorithms that are easy to process in one direction but difficult to reverse, which are known as mathematical trap-door functions. A simple example of a trap-door function is the product of two prime numbers. If two random prime numbers are chosen, it is trivial to find their product. However if only the product of the two numbers is known, it is relatively difficult to find either of the factors used to create the number (this is factorisation). This was first noticed in 1874, when &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Stanley_Jevons#Jevons.27_number"&gt;Jevons&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;remarked:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Can the reader say what two numbers multiplied together will produce the number 8,616,460,799? I think it unlikely that anyone but myself will ever&amp;nbsp;know.&amp;#8221;*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This simple problem shows that finding the product of two (secret) prime numbers is computationally simple, but factorising the result is not. This type of problem is a key feature of modern cryptography. Factoring prime numbers is a super famous mathematical problem, it was studied by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eratosthenes"&gt;Eratosthenes&lt;/a&gt; &lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in the 3rd century &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BC&lt;/span&gt; and more recently the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RSA_Factoring_Challenge"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSA&lt;/span&gt; Factoring Challenge&lt;/a&gt; has intended to track state-of-the-art factorisation techniques by issues cash prizes for the factorisation of products of large&amp;nbsp;primes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, the bigger the difference in difficulty between executing the function and reversing it, the better the cryptographic&amp;nbsp;technique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSA&lt;/span&gt; algorithm below uses factorisation as the foundation of its security, but factorisation is not the hardest problem to solve relative to the size of the keys required. Algorithms have been developed to factor the products of large prime numbers, and are much more efficient than randomly guessing possible factors. The greater the size of the primes being factored, the more efficient these algorithms become, and therefore the difference in difficulty between executing the function (multiplying two large primes) and reversing it (factorisation) becomes smaller as the size of the cryptographic key length increases. This is a problem because as public key cryptography becomes more commonly used the resources available to factor products of primes increases, and consequently larger keys are&amp;nbsp;required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, encryption techniques based on the difficulty of factorisation will become redundant as the difficulty gap between creating and solving them shrinks. A better trap door function is&amp;nbsp;required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Overview of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;algorithm&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Named after its founders (&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ron_Rivest" title="Ron Rivest"&gt;Ron Rivest&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adi_Shamir" title="Adi Shamir"&gt;Adi Shamir&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leonard_Adleman" title="Leonard"&gt;Leonard Adleman&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSA&lt;/span&gt; was one of the first public-key encryption algorithms and is still widely&amp;nbsp;used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSA&lt;/span&gt; (as well as other cryptographic techniques) makes use of a number line which loops back to zero after reaching a maximum value, rather than increasing indefinitely. This means that once a maximum number $n$ has been defined, if a number greater than $n$ is created the result simply loops around to 0 and begins counting from 0 again. i.e. if $n = 10$, then $7 + 5 = 12 - 10 = 2$. The result of a calculation on a looping number line may easily be found by doing long division and using the remainder as the final answer, i.e. $12 / 10 = 1$ with $2$&amp;nbsp;remaining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Generation of a pair of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;keys:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. Generate the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;module&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select two large random prime numbers, $p$ and $q$. They need to be random because anyone who knows or guesses them will be able to decrypt the&amp;nbsp;encryption.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calculate $n =&amp;nbsp;pq$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. Find derived number&amp;nbsp;(e)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; must be greater than 1 and less than $( p - 1)( q -&amp;nbsp;1)$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There must be no common factor for e and $( p - 1)( q - 1)$ except for 1. &lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:4"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3. Form the public&amp;nbsp;key&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The pair of numbers $(n, e)$ form the public key and can be made&amp;nbsp;public.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even though $n$ is public, it is so difficult to factor the product of 2 large prime numbers that an attacker would not be able to find its component primes in the time available. The strength of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSA&lt;/span&gt; rests entirely on the difficulty of factoring $n$ into its two component prime&amp;nbsp;numbers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4. Generate the private key&amp;nbsp;(d)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The private key is generated from using $p$, $q$ and e as inputs to the Extended Euclidean Algorithm. For a given set of values, there is a unique answer&amp;nbsp;$d$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$d$ is the inverse of $e$ modulo $( p - 1)( q - 1 )$. This means that $d$ is the number less than $( p - 1 ) ( q - 1 )$ such that when it is multiplied by e, it is equal to $1$ modulo $( p - 1 ) ( q - 1&amp;nbsp;)$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;example:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSA&lt;/span&gt; does not directly operate on strings as bits, it operates on numbers modulo (less than) $n$. and it is necessary to represent plain text as a series of numbers less than $n$. The dominant encoding on the internet is &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UTF-8"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UTF&lt;/span&gt;-8&lt;/a&gt;, which represents each upper case Latin letter as a number between 65 and 90. Using this encoding, a message &amp;#8220;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HELLO&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8221; would become &amp;#8220;$72, 69, 76, 76,&amp;nbsp;79$&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The maximum number $n$ needs to be the product of the two prime numbers $p$ and $q$. For this example choose $p = 7$ and $q = 13$, so $n  = 91$  &lt;sup id="fnref:5"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:5"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The public key component &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; can be any number we choose,  as long as there is no number other than 1 which is a common factor of &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; and $( p - 1 ) ( q - 1 )$. In our example, this requires that there be no common factor between 72 and e other than 1, so let &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; $=&amp;nbsp;5$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore our public key is (91, 5). This can be made available to anyone without messages being decrypted because of the difficulty of factoring the product of (very large) prime&amp;nbsp;numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the fact that we know 5 and 11 are the prime factors of 55 and e is 5, we can use the Extended Euclidean Algorithm  to compute our private key $d$, which is&amp;nbsp;29.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore when the prime factors 7 and 13 are used, the public key is (91, 5) and the private key is (91, 29). These parameters fully define a functional &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Encoding&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To encode a letter H in a message (&amp;#8216;H&amp;#8217; is $72$ in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UTF&lt;/span&gt;-8), we need to multiply it by itself $e$ times ($e = 5$), remembering to wrap around each time we pass our maximum value of $n =&amp;nbsp;91$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$72 \times 72 = 5184, 5184 / 91 = 56$ with $88$ remaining, (i.e. $5184 = 91 \times 56 + 88$). Therefore:
$72 \times 72 = 5184 = 88$
$88 \times 72 = 6336 = 57$
$57 \times 72 = 4104 = 9$
$9 \times 72 = 648 =&amp;nbsp;11$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore the encrypted value of &amp;#8220;H&amp;#8221; is&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8220;$11$&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the method for each character in the message &amp;#8220;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HELLO&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8221; results in the encoded message&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8220;\$11,62,20,20,53\$&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To decrypt the message, we take each number and multiply it by itself $d$ times, ($d=29$) wrapping around each time we pass&amp;nbsp;$91$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$11 \times 11 = 121 = 30$
$30 \times 11 = 330 = 57$
&amp;#8230;
$57 \times 11 = 627 = 81$
$81 \times 11 = 891 =&amp;nbsp;72$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we&amp;#8217;re back to our original&amp;nbsp;encoding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Files&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spreadsheet I used to calculate the encrypted and decrypted values can be downloaded &lt;a href="RSA-Example.xlsx"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A simple python script to encrypt and decrypt a message is &lt;a href="AES_Example.py"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It uses the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AES&lt;/span&gt; encryption&amp;nbsp;method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used the explanations &lt;a href="http://www.tutorialspoint.com/cryptography/public_key_encryption.htm"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/a-relatively-easy-to-understand-primer-on-elliptic-curve-cryptography/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; a lot.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A simple example is $A=1, B=2$ etc&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eratosthenes invented his famous &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sieve_of_Eratosthenes"&gt;sieving algorithm&lt;/a&gt; which finds all the primes up to a given limit.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this is the case then e and ( p - 1) ( q - 1 ) are called &amp;#8220;coprime&amp;#8221;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:4" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whilst the Extended Euclidean Algorithm is apparently simple to compute, its description is not. Therefore I&amp;#8217;ve used the same numbers in the following example as in the tutorials &lt;a href="http://www.tutorialspoint.com/cryptography/public_key_encryption.htm"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://arstechnica.com/security/2013/10/a-relatively-easy-to-understand-primer-on-elliptic-curve-cryptography/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:5" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Disintermediation"></category><category term="Encryption"></category><category term="RSA"></category><category term="DLT"></category><category term="Blockchains"></category><category term="Bitcoin"></category><category term="Digital Currencies"></category><category term="Public Key Cryptography"></category></entry><entry><title>Digital currencies: the basics</title><link href="digital-currencies-the-basics.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-19T21:02:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-08-19T21:02:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-08-19:digital-currencies-the-basics.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Digital currencies are often discussed in the context of finance, technology and economics. The Blockchain - the technology which applications like Bitcoin are built on - is significant because it removes the need for trust or an intermediary between unrelated parties transacting with each other. So far, the most influential and famous …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Digital currencies are often discussed in the context of finance, technology and economics. The Blockchain - the technology which applications like Bitcoin are built on - is significant because it removes the need for trust or an intermediary between unrelated parties transacting with each other. So far, the most influential and famous digital currency is&amp;nbsp;Bitcoin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is intended to introduce the basic concepts of digital currencies and the problems a distributed ledger system needs to&amp;nbsp;overcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is a digital&amp;nbsp;currency?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A digital currency is an internet based medium of exchange. Units of digital currency are not printed, are not physical, and represent nothing. A unit of currency is produced by running algorithms to solve complex mathematical problems. When a solution is found, a unit of currency (for example, 1 Bitcoin) is&amp;nbsp;generated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;If the currency represents nothing, why is it&amp;nbsp;valuable?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because people believe that in future, other people will believe it does, and because people are willing to trade real goods and services in exchange for&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the same as for dollars, sterling and euros (fiat currencies) which also don&amp;#8217;t represent anything physical. (Although these examples are  supported by laws or&amp;nbsp;regulation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, creating a new currency without the support of government hasn&amp;#8217;t been practical&amp;nbsp;because:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A central bank was required to control the physical creation of new currency (otherwise people would create counterfeit currency, decreasing scarcity and moving its value towards&amp;nbsp;zero)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An intermediary (a bank) was required for all large or remote transactions, to make sure that the amount of money each party owns is correctly recorded and updated in a ledger (preventing double spending of&amp;nbsp;funds)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technological breakthrough was preventing double spending without requiring an intermediary. This is made possible by using cryptographic techniques developed over the last few decades, and cheap, powerful computers which have only recently become&amp;nbsp;available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Central and distributed&amp;nbsp;ledgers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With conventional currencies everyone&amp;#8217;s balance and transactions are recorded in one central ledger (a list showing how much money each account has) and each account holder only has access to their own balance and transactions. With digital currencies, a copy of the entire ledger (every transaction ever made by everyone) is held on each computer (or node), and anyone can see everyone&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;transactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conventionally, if two parties wish to make a remote transaction then they need a bank to be the intermediary. The bank mediates by updating the central ledger to record the change in each parties funds as a result of the transaction. This is how one party knows if the counter-party is able to pay, and how payment is confirmed. If there is only one copy of the ledger, maintained by the bank, then the bank must be involved in every transaction between its account holders. This need for an intermediary increases the complexity and cost of doing&amp;nbsp;business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sending&amp;nbsp;money&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To send money, a message is broadcast to the network that the amount in your account should decrease and the amount in another account should increase. Each computer in the network (a node) which receives this message will check its authenticity, make the changes, and pass the message along to other&amp;nbsp;nodes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What problems does blockchain&amp;nbsp;solve?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a transaction to be accepted and entered into the distributed ledger, its authenticity needs to be verified. Because the ledger is distributed, everyone can see everyone else&amp;#8217;s transactions. Therefore user authentication and transaction authorisation needs to be possible without compromising a user&amp;#8217;s ability to send secure payments in&amp;nbsp;future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also the problem of double spending - because the currency is neither physical, printed or representative of anything, how do you prevent a user from spending their currency more than once, or simply creating as much new currency as they&amp;nbsp;want?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another problem is the addition of new transactions to the ledger from many unrelated users. If each party has their own copy of the ledger, updating (or changing) it as they want, how would the ledgers completeness and accuracy be assured? How would you update your ledger to take account of transactions between third parties, and how would you know the order in which they occurred?&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The blockchain is remarkable because it is the first technology to solve all of these problems. Future posts will consider each of these problems are&amp;nbsp;overcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the Byzantine Generals problem, which is nicely described in the introduction of 
&lt;a href="http://research.microsoft.com/en-us/um/people/lamport/pubs/byz.pdf"&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Disintermediation"></category><category term="Bitcoin"></category><category term="Cryptocurrencies"></category><category term="Cryptography"></category><category term="Digital Currencies"></category><category term="Finance"></category><category term="Fintech"></category></entry></feed>