<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>blog - bitnation</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="feeds/bitnation.tag.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2017-11-22T16:49:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Pangea</title><link href="pangea.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-11-22T16:49:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-11-22T16:49:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:None,2017-11-22:pangea.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Communities will always need to create reliable and enforceable agreements with each&amp;nbsp;other.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many countries the ability to create legally binding agreements is not available to average citizens. Legal services are often unaffordable and opaque, or service providers are corrupt. Legal services are in need of&amp;nbsp;disruption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Pangea&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bitnation (who I consult for) intends to address this problem by empowering people to self-organise and self-govern. We are building a platform called Pangea which allows users to create, notarise and arbitrate contracts according to a jurisdiction which each party joins voluntarily, irrespective of their geographical&amp;nbsp;location. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pangea is a smart phone app that looks and feels like a chat app, the back-end (called Panthalassa) is an encrypted mesh network hooked up to the Ethereum&amp;nbsp;blockchain. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Rewarded for doing good, empowered to be a responsible&amp;nbsp;citizen&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Pangea, people are incentivised to be good citizens by receiving rewards for doing good, rather than being coerced by the threat of punishment for bad&amp;nbsp;behaviour. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This platform would fulfil a vast and unmet need, particularly in countries whose legal systems function poorly. On Pangea, a user voluntarily chooses which jurisdiction to be a part of. Contracts are then notarised, executed and arbitrated according to that jurisdiction. Users voluntarily join a decentralised borderless voluntary nation (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DBVN&lt;/span&gt;) and will receive tokens (Pangea Arbitration Tokens) as a reward for good behaviour. The tokens will be tradable and will be used as payment on Pangea for notarisation and arbitration&amp;nbsp;services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Combining a store of value and access to legal&amp;nbsp;services&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Societies cannot escape their need to use currency as stores of value. They also cannot escape their need to create reliable and enforceable agreements (contracts) with each&amp;nbsp;other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generating Bitcoin through proof of work occurs because individuals believe that Bitcoin will be continuously used — that it will meet an ongoing need to transact using a decentralised and disintermediated&amp;nbsp;method. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generating &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PAT&lt;/span&gt; by being a good citizen will occur because individuals believe that Pangea will be continuously used  — that it will meet an ongoing need to create enforceable agreements using a voluntary and geographically agnostic (and decentralised)&amp;nbsp;method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is much still to say about the Pangea platform and the mechanisms which will make it function. Please give feedback and ask questions in the comments. To find out more, visit the &lt;a href="http://bitnation.co"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Disintermediation"></category><category term="bitnation"></category><category term="pangea"></category></entry><entry><title>Bitnation</title><link href="bitnation.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-14T11:25:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-09-14T11:25:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:None,2017-09-14:bitnation.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m about to begin consulting for &lt;a href="http://bitnation.co"&gt;Bitnation&lt;/a&gt; as their finance&amp;nbsp;officer.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;I&amp;#8217;m&amp;nbsp;Consulting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next week I begin working with &lt;a href="http://bitnation.co"&gt;Bitnation&lt;/a&gt; as their finance officer. I&amp;#8217;m excited about this because I get to work on a really ambitious project using new technology to do something innovative and&amp;nbsp;valuable. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bitnation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bitnation&amp;#8217;s purpose is to offer the same services as governments do, in a way that delivers more benefit to&amp;nbsp;users. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the West this may not immediately sound like a big deal. Our governments are fairly organised and the services are usually &amp;#8220;good enough&amp;#8221;. Most significantly, we are not used to thinking about &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ID&lt;/span&gt; services (passports, visa, drivers licences) or registration services (land registry, marriage certificates) as a service that we are customers of - like our internet service provider, or our electricity&amp;nbsp;supplier. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many parts of the world dysfunctional or unjust governments represent a huge obstacle to improving everyday life, the progress and achievement that many people can hope to realise is limited because of&amp;nbsp;this. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there was a viable alternative to a passport from a jurisdiction renowned for forgery, or a credit rating that acknowledged your land holdings despited your governments inability to maintain a credible database, then you could begin to travel, trade and enjoy the benefits that citizens of many western states take for&amp;nbsp;granted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m excited that I get to use my skills in an innovative tech company that is aiming to do something really&amp;nbsp;positive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Services include secure &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ID&lt;/span&gt; systems, asset registry and dispute resolution. Identification (in particular) is an area full of problems, and blockchain tech could offer some really significant improvements. Bitnation wants to create a platform where voluntary nations can be created and administered, and where people can choose what jurisdictional system they are part of. If this is widely implemented it will be&amp;nbsp;unprecedented. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jurisdictions would offer their own services according to their own principles, and because they are easy to create and membership is voluntarily, jurisdictions would compete to attract citizens. This should lead to improvements for the users of each service, and is intended to provide an alternative to the slow, expensive and opaque processing methods commonly associated with services from geographically defined&amp;nbsp;nationstates. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Disintermediation"></category><category term="Bitnation"></category><category term="Blockchain"></category><category term="Disintermediation"></category><category term="Identity"></category><category term="Consulting"></category><category term="Finance"></category></entry></feed>