<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>blog - Blockchain</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="feeds/blockchain.tag.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2018-10-13T20:34:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Sync a BTC node, quickly</title><link href="sync-bitcoin-core-node.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-13T20:34:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-10-13T20:34:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:None,2018-10-13:sync-bitcoin-core-node.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sync a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BTC&lt;/span&gt; node for the first time, quickly, on a spinning disk by moving chainstate to an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSD&lt;/span&gt; and symlinking to&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In order to run your own bitcoin node, or lightning node, you&amp;#8217;ll need to
download the entire bitcoin blockchain and then validate it. This takes ages on
a magnetic disk due to the random access speed of the contents of the
chainstate&amp;nbsp;directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To remove this bottleneck, move the chainstate directory to an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSD&lt;/span&gt; (its only
a few &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GB&lt;/span&gt;) and symlink to it from the bitcoin data directory. More details are
&lt;a href="https://en.bitcoin.it/wiki/Splitting_the_data_directory"&gt;on the Bitcoin wiki&lt;/a&gt;.
When the sync is complete, replace the symlink with the actual chainstate&amp;nbsp;directory.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Disintermediation"></category><category term="Bitcoin"></category><category term="btc-core"></category><category term="Blockchain"></category><category term="Node"></category></entry><entry><title>Hardware Wallets</title><link href="wallet.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-11-08T16:09:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-11-08T16:09:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:None,2017-11-08:wallet.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Current hardware wallets are technically good but are awkward to use. A good solution would solve the following&amp;nbsp;problems:&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;What is a hardware&amp;nbsp;wallet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A hardware wallet (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallet) is a physical device that stores the information required to access digital currency or assets. It is plugged into a computer via &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; in order to initiate or confirm transactions on the Bitcoin, Ethereum or other digital asset blockchain&amp;nbsp;networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are a secure method of storing cryptographic data. They are so secure that they can be used on a compromised computer. All that is needed to access funds using a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallet (in addition to the device itself) is a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PIN&lt;/span&gt; code which the user chooses. A single &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallet can store multiple currencies in multiple&amp;nbsp;accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallets are an easier solution than remembering a good password, and safer than storing the data in a file on my computer or&amp;nbsp;online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best known hardware wallet brands are &lt;a href="https://www.ledgerwallet.com/"&gt;Ledger&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://trezor.io/"&gt;Trezor&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallets are technically great, but their size and shape creates a bad user experience. A good hardware wallet should be convenient to use multiple times each day, like a credit card&amp;nbsp;is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Current hardware wallets don&amp;#8217;t fit into a (money) wallet and people don&amp;#8217;t want to carry more any objects in their pockets. They are too big and are a bad&amp;nbsp;shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallets look like they might belong on a keyring, but it&amp;#8217;s inconvenient and insecure to attach a credit card to a keyring and the same is true for an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallet. I might store my keys on a hook by my door, but I would never leave my wallet there overnight. I often want to keep my keys and money separate because I need my keys when I’m near my house, where I don’t need to buy stuff, and I need my money when I’m away from my house where I don’t need to unlock&amp;nbsp;anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to keep my bank cards and cash together in one safe place, and I don’t want to carry around a dongle as well. It&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;inconvenient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easier to have a separate dongle lost or stolen than something that would fit next to my credit card in my wallet. The inconvenience is a barrier to enjoying the advantages of digital&amp;nbsp;currencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;goal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallet that is the size and shape of a credit card, it could be 3 times thicker than a credit card and still fit in a normal wallet. It&amp;nbsp;needs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a display - it could be a low resolution b&amp;amp;w&amp;nbsp;display&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;two or more&amp;nbsp;buttons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to  plug into a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;port&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;securely sign transactions and create&amp;nbsp;addresses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Engineering"></category><category term="wallet"></category><category term="crypto"></category><category term="blockchain"></category><category term="bitcoin"></category></entry><entry><title>Bitnation</title><link href="bitnation.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-14T11:25:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-09-14T11:25:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:None,2017-09-14:bitnation.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m about to begin consulting for &lt;a href="http://bitnation.co"&gt;Bitnation&lt;/a&gt; as their finance&amp;nbsp;officer.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;I&amp;#8217;m&amp;nbsp;Consulting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next week I begin working with &lt;a href="http://bitnation.co"&gt;Bitnation&lt;/a&gt; as their finance officer. I&amp;#8217;m excited about this because I get to work on a really ambitious project using new technology to do something innovative and&amp;nbsp;valuable. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bitnation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bitnation&amp;#8217;s purpose is to offer the same services as governments do, in a way that delivers more benefit to&amp;nbsp;users. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the West this may not immediately sound like a big deal. Our governments are fairly organised and the services are usually &amp;#8220;good enough&amp;#8221;. Most significantly, we are not used to thinking about &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ID&lt;/span&gt; services (passports, visa, drivers licences) or registration services (land registry, marriage certificates) as a service that we are customers of - like our internet service provider, or our electricity&amp;nbsp;supplier. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many parts of the world dysfunctional or unjust governments represent a huge obstacle to improving everyday life, the progress and achievement that many people can hope to realise is limited because of&amp;nbsp;this. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there was a viable alternative to a passport from a jurisdiction renowned for forgery, or a credit rating that acknowledged your land holdings despited your governments inability to maintain a credible database, then you could begin to travel, trade and enjoy the benefits that citizens of many western states take for&amp;nbsp;granted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m excited that I get to use my skills in an innovative tech company that is aiming to do something really&amp;nbsp;positive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Services include secure &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ID&lt;/span&gt; systems, asset registry and dispute resolution. Identification (in particular) is an area full of problems, and blockchain tech could offer some really significant improvements. Bitnation wants to create a platform where voluntary nations can be created and administered, and where people can choose what jurisdictional system they are part of. If this is widely implemented it will be&amp;nbsp;unprecedented. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jurisdictions would offer their own services according to their own principles, and because they are easy to create and membership is voluntarily, jurisdictions would compete to attract citizens. This should lead to improvements for the users of each service, and is intended to provide an alternative to the slow, expensive and opaque processing methods commonly associated with services from geographically defined&amp;nbsp;nationstates. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Disintermediation"></category><category term="Bitnation"></category><category term="Blockchain"></category><category term="Disintermediation"></category><category term="Identity"></category><category term="Consulting"></category><category term="Finance"></category></entry></feed>