<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>blog - Crypto</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="feeds/crypto.tag.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2019-01-24T12:57:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Bitcoin Lightning</title><link href="bitcoin-lightning.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-01-24T12:57:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-01-24T12:57:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-01-24:bitcoin-lightning.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I set up a  node on the Bitcoin Lightning network and sent a payment of $0.005 which confirmed in a few&amp;nbsp;seconds.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the largest obstacles (second only to privacy in my opinion) to widespread adoption of Bitcoin is its limited volume. Bitcoin cannot faciliate payments fast enough such that it could compete with Visa or&amp;nbsp;Mastercard. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most interesting solution to this problem is the &lt;a href="https://lightning.network/"&gt;Lightning protocol&lt;/a&gt; - a separate protocol that sits ontop of the Bitcoin protocol (a so-called &amp;#8216;Layer 2&amp;#8217; solution). Lightning uses hashed time locked contracts (HTLCs) to trustlessly and privately move transactions off-chain. This allows payments to be faster, cheaper and more frequent. It also has interesting implications for enhancing&amp;nbsp;privacy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of resources about what the Lightning network is, why it&amp;#8217;s neccesary and how it works. There are also several good guides available about how to set up and maintain a node. I used a Raspberry Pi with an external hdd. It took a few attempts, mostly because it&amp;#8217;s my first time working with an unix operating system and I tried to move a swap file to a disk that wasnt formmated as&amp;nbsp;ext4&amp;#8230; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I&amp;#8217;ve opened and closed some channels, connected to peers, and made some transactions. I even bought some stickers using&amp;nbsp;Lightning!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find my node using these&amp;nbsp;details:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Alias: &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;johnmathews.eu&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
Public Key: &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;025469b50de125b4cd97457c0da67365519f0cd0f441c2ced0978fb6ae7802ae76&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
IP address: &lt;span class="m"&gt;85&lt;/span&gt;.145.183.145
Port: &lt;span class="m"&gt;9735&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some useful&amp;nbsp;resources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://explorer.acinq.co/n/025469b50de125b4cd97457c0da67365519f0cd0f441c2ced0978fb6ae7802ae76"&gt;Lightning network&amp;nbsp;explorer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://1ml.com/node/025469b50de125b4cd97457c0da67365519f0cd0f441c2ced0978fb6ae7802ae76"&gt;Lightning node&amp;nbsp;information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://incoherency.co.uk/blog/stories/spelunking-ln.html"&gt;Interesting things to&amp;nbsp;do&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Disintermediation"></category><category term="Bitcoin"></category><category term="Lightning"></category><category term="Crypto"></category></entry><entry><title>Hardware Wallets</title><link href="wallet.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-11-08T16:09:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-11-08T16:09:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:None,2017-11-08:wallet.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Current hardware wallets are technically good but are awkward to use. A good solution would solve the following&amp;nbsp;problems:&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;What is a hardware&amp;nbsp;wallet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A hardware wallet (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallet) is a physical device that stores the information required to access digital currency or assets. It is plugged into a computer via &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; in order to initiate or confirm transactions on the Bitcoin, Ethereum or other digital asset blockchain&amp;nbsp;networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are a secure method of storing cryptographic data. They are so secure that they can be used on a compromised computer. All that is needed to access funds using a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallet (in addition to the device itself) is a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PIN&lt;/span&gt; code which the user chooses. A single &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallet can store multiple currencies in multiple&amp;nbsp;accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallets are an easier solution than remembering a good password, and safer than storing the data in a file on my computer or&amp;nbsp;online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best known hardware wallet brands are &lt;a href="https://www.ledgerwallet.com/"&gt;Ledger&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://trezor.io/"&gt;Trezor&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallets are technically great, but their size and shape creates a bad user experience. A good hardware wallet should be convenient to use multiple times each day, like a credit card&amp;nbsp;is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Current hardware wallets don&amp;#8217;t fit into a (money) wallet and people don&amp;#8217;t want to carry more any objects in their pockets. They are too big and are a bad&amp;nbsp;shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallets look like they might belong on a keyring, but it&amp;#8217;s inconvenient and insecure to attach a credit card to a keyring and the same is true for an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallet. I might store my keys on a hook by my door, but I would never leave my wallet there overnight. I often want to keep my keys and money separate because I need my keys when I’m near my house, where I don’t need to buy stuff, and I need my money when I’m away from my house where I don’t need to unlock&amp;nbsp;anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to keep my bank cards and cash together in one safe place, and I don’t want to carry around a dongle as well. It&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;inconvenient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easier to have a separate dongle lost or stolen than something that would fit next to my credit card in my wallet. The inconvenience is a barrier to enjoying the advantages of digital&amp;nbsp;currencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;goal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HW&lt;/span&gt; wallet that is the size and shape of a credit card, it could be 3 times thicker than a credit card and still fit in a normal wallet. It&amp;nbsp;needs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a display - it could be a low resolution b&amp;amp;w&amp;nbsp;display&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;two or more&amp;nbsp;buttons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to  plug into a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;port&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;securely sign transactions and create&amp;nbsp;addresses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Engineering"></category><category term="wallet"></category><category term="crypto"></category><category term="blockchain"></category><category term="bitcoin"></category></entry></feed>