<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>blog - Data</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="feeds/data.tag.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2016-08-03T13:04:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Jupyter (iPython) notebooks + Pandas</title><link href="Jupyter-ipython-notebooks-pandas.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-03T13:04:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-08-03T13:04:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-08-03:Jupyter-ipython-notebooks-pandas.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When working with more data than can fit in an Excel file, or when you
want to be sure the data won&amp;#8217;t be edited, you usually need to interact with
the data by writing&amp;nbsp;scripts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest time sinks (for me) when working with these tools
(&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACL …&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When working with more data than can fit in an Excel file, or when you
want to be sure the data won&amp;#8217;t be edited, you usually need to interact with
the data by writing&amp;nbsp;scripts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest time sinks (for me) when working with these tools
(&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACL&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt;, Python) is debugging, and working out exactly where in the
chain of individual commands something unexpected happened. Even with
only a modest page of code, I can quickly find myself rerunning the
entire script multiple times and commenting-out and uncommenting
multiple lines in order to understand what&amp;#8217;s really going on. If you
have a time consuming task at the start of your script, such as a
summarise and sort command, the extra time required can be even greater.
This leads to interrupted flow and&amp;nbsp;concentration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pandas is a python package to manipulate large datasets, the Jupyter
notebook is an application which allows the user to run a python script
in chunks, and output the results of each chunk before continuing. You
can re-run a previous chunk without returning to the beginning, and
change the code as you go along. This is amazingly flexible and&amp;nbsp;intuitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently worked through an exceptionally good Pandas tutorial recorded
at PyCon 2015. &amp;#8220;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/5JnMutdy6Fw"&gt;Pandas from the ground
up&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8221; is well structured, clear, has good
scope and the resources are available to download from
&lt;a href="https://github.com/brandon-rhodes/pycon-pandas-tutorial"&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;.
Brandon Rhodes gives you a good working foundation for using Pandas and
the Jupyter notebook to manipulate datasets using&amp;nbsp;Python.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Tools"></category><category term="Data"></category><category term="Jupyter Notebook"></category><category term="Pandas"></category><category term="Python"></category></entry></feed>