<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>John Mathews - Non-technical</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/feeds/non-technical.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://johnmathews.eu/</id><updated>2021-05-27T15:28:49+02:00</updated><entry><title>Questions for good references</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/questions-for-good-references.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-05-27T15:28:49+02:00</published><updated>2021-05-27T15:28:49+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-05-27:/questions-for-good-references.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Use the following questions to get better references:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What was the problem you had before you used the solution I helped develop?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What did the frustration feel like as you tried to solve the problem?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What was different about the solution I worked on compared to previous efforts?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take us to the moment you realized our solution was actually working to solve
   the problem?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What does life look like now that the problem is being solved?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customize the text as necessary, for products or services, complete solutions
are a component of a larger solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Download a form &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/reference-questions.docx"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Entrepreneurship"/><category term="marketing"/></entry><entry><title>Building A Story Brand</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/building-a-story-brand.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-05-17T13:15:07+02:00</published><updated>2021-05-17T13:15:07+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-05-17:/building-a-story-brand.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;WIP&lt;/span&gt; - I’m still reading this book and editing these notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="toc"&gt;&lt;span class="toctitle"&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/span&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#premise"&gt;Premise&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#stories"&gt;Stories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#hero"&gt;Hero&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#problem"&gt;Problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#guide"&gt;Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#plan"&gt;Plan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#a-call-to-action"&gt;A Call To Action&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#what-is-at-stake"&gt;What is at stake?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#avoid-failure"&gt;Avoid Failure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#end-with-success"&gt;End with Success&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#people-want-your-brand-to-participate-in-their-transformation"&gt;People want your brand to participate in their transformation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h1 id="premise"&gt;Premise&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People want to &lt;strong&gt;survive and thrive&lt;/strong&gt;. They are their own protagonist and they
   have problems. They don’t want to waste energy figuring out if you can help them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good marketing makes the &lt;strong&gt;benefit obvious&lt;/strong&gt;. How does your product improve
   someones ability to “survive and thrive”?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cut through noisy and challenging world by having a super &lt;strong&gt;quick and easy to
   understand message&lt;/strong&gt;. Don’t be clever, be clear. Don’t make the customer spend
   calories trying to figure out how they will benefit from your product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stories are a great way to combat noise and get the attention because they
   organise information in an intuitive way. People are compelled to &lt;strong&gt;pay
   attention until all the “story gaps” have been closed&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could a caveman look at your website and answer these questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do you &lt;strong&gt;offer&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will it &lt;strong&gt;improve&lt;/strong&gt; my life?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the &lt;strong&gt;next steps&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Story Gaps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A gap between a character and what they want. Will they find their way to success, overcome their challenges, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cadence and momentum are defined by the creation and fulfillment of story gaps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you fail to define something that the customer wants, you fail to open a story gap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This makes the story uninteresting because there isn’t a question that requires an answer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Story gaps work because we want things to resolve. It’s like singing twinkle
twinkle little star but stopping before the “are” on the last line. You need to
hear the last note of the melody for the tune to feel complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pare down the customers desire to a single focus. Make your brand known for
single specific desire and helping people get it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t clutter the story by diluting the hero’s desire with other desires. You
can eventually develop subplots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Apple&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Apple released the Lisa computer in 1983, Jobs bought a 9 page ad in the
New York times listing the computers features. When jobs returned to Apple
after being fired, (and after partly founding Pixar, which tells stories) apple
became a customer centric company, and their marketing was about the customers.
9 pages became 2 words - “think different”. A message about their customers, and
their customers need to survive and thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple isn’t the hero in the “think different” brand. The customer is. It’s the
same with Nike. Apple plays a role more like Q in James Bond, giving the hero
what they need to win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="stories"&gt;Stories&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a &lt;strong&gt;Hero&lt;/strong&gt; → has a &lt;strong&gt;Problem&lt;/strong&gt; → and meets a &lt;strong&gt;Guide&lt;/strong&gt; → who gives them a &lt;strong&gt;Plan&lt;/strong&gt; → and calls them to &lt;strong&gt;Action&lt;/strong&gt; → that ends in &lt;strong&gt;Success&lt;/strong&gt; → and helps them avoid &lt;strong&gt;Failure&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="story stages" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/building-a-story-brand/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/7storystages.png" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/building-a-story-brand/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/7storystages.png 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/building-a-story-brand/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/7storystages.png 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/building-a-story-brand/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/7storystages.png 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/building-a-story-brand/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/7storystages.png 1600w" style="margin-left: 0;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="hero"&gt;Hero&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The customer, not you. You are the guide. The customer is the main character in
their life and is battling internal and external adversity it order to survive
and thrive. Heroes have weaknesses, the guide is usually the strongest character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A story starts with a character who wants to  overcome external challenges that
pose internal and philosophical problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your first task is to create the story gap “Will they get what they want?” You
need to define the characters ambition in the opening section, so that the
reader knows what is at stake and what kind of a story it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="problem"&gt;Problem&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you identify a customers problem then you show that you understand them. This
is a hook into the story because they relate to your narrative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more we talk about the problems our customers are experiencing, the more
interest they will have in our brand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every story needs a villain, which is the personified problem. The germs are
personified, envy is personified, etc. The diminished social status is
personified by someone with more status being villainized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;villain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;should be &lt;strong&gt;relatable&lt;/strong&gt; - readers should recognize that the villain should be disdained.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;should be a &lt;strong&gt;root source&lt;/strong&gt; - frustration is what the villain makes us feel. High taxes are the cause, and are therefore the villain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;should be &lt;strong&gt;singular&lt;/strong&gt; - just one villain, keep it simple to cut through the noise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;should be &lt;strong&gt;real&lt;/strong&gt; - don’t be a fear monger. Fight a real problem on behalf of your customers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three types of &lt;strong&gt;problem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;External&lt;/strong&gt; - A barrier to stability that must be removed - My business isn’t growing fast enough, profits are too small.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Internal&lt;/strong&gt; - I have self-doubt. Do I have what it takes to succeed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Philosophical&lt;/strong&gt; - I deserve to be successful, my hard work should be rewarded. Failure would be unjust.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;villain&lt;/strong&gt; initiates an &lt;strong&gt;external&lt;/strong&gt; problem that causes the &lt;strong&gt;hero&lt;/strong&gt; to encounter an &lt;strong&gt;internal&lt;/strong&gt; problem that is &lt;strong&gt;philosophically wrong&lt;/strong&gt; or unjust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the (story specific) external problem is to manifest the (relatable by the audience) internal problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customers are much more motivated to solve internal problems than they are external.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choose a &lt;strong&gt;desire relevant to their survival&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conserving or accumulating resources (financial or time)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gaining status or building a social network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being generous - Most people are not as Darwinian as we’ve been led to believe they want to be empathetic and caring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The desire for meaning - Give customers an opportunity to be generous and participate in something greater than themselves (“the chief desire of man is not pleasure, but meaning”).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Translate the &lt;strong&gt;external problem&lt;/strong&gt; into several survival categories - put your solution in
the context of a type of survival they they want. Otherwise there isn’t a story gap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only reason that customers buy is because the external problem being solved
is causing an &lt;strong&gt;internal frustration&lt;/strong&gt;. If you identify that frustration, put it into
words and verbally offer to solve it along with the original problem then you
bond with your customer because you’ve positioned yourself more deeply into
their internal narrative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Philosophical problems&lt;/strong&gt; are important because people want to be involved in
something larger than themselves. It adds depth and meaning. Representing (and
solving) a philosophical problem gives customers a way of expressing their
values that they wouldn’t otherwise have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can &lt;strong&gt;resolve all three problems in one shot&lt;/strong&gt;, then the audience experiences
a wave of relief and pleasure, and they will love the story. Like when Anakin
Skywalker blows up the Deathstar by aiming the perfect shot, he defeats the
external problem (the enemy army), his internal problem (no more self doubt) and
the philosophical problem (justice is served)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Frame your &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CTA&lt;/span&gt; as the action that must be taken to close the final story gap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is there a &lt;strong&gt;single villain&lt;/strong&gt; that your brand stands against?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What &lt;strong&gt;external problem&lt;/strong&gt; is that villain causing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How is the external problem making your customer feel?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why is it unjust for people to suffer because of that villain?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our hero is being challenged - will they be able to solve their problem? The
only way to find out is to engage with the brand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="guide"&gt;Guide&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customers aren’t looking for another hero, they’re looking for a guide who can
help them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A persons life is made up of many acts - doorways of no return. And whilst each
life is unique, we all have common chapters. We are all on transformational
journeys with common elements. In stories, events mark the beginning and end of
chapters. In stories, these events are instigated by external actors called guides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heroes need a guide who is &lt;strong&gt;trustworthy&lt;/strong&gt; and earns &lt;strong&gt;respect&lt;/strong&gt;. If they didn’t
need a hero their wouldn’t be a story. Everyone is looking for a guide to help
them solve their problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Just like in stories, humans wake up each morning self-identifying as a hero.
They are troubled by internal, external and philosophical issues. And they know
they can’t solve their issues on their own.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This insight has consequences, it means the story isn’t about us but about
others. We can aspire to be guides for others, but not the hero to others. It
shows why the search for meaning is innate, but can only be resolved by
unbecoming a hero. Stop losing sleep over the success of your company and start
losing sleep over the success of your customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In stories, heroes are not the strongest characters, they have self-doubt and are
often ill-equipped. They are often reluctant, and are thrown into the story by
outside events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The guide has already “been there and done that” and has conquered the hero’s
internal and philosophical challenges in their own backstory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The guide is the one with authority. Much more authority than the hero. But the
main character is the hero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who realize that the epic story of life is not about them end up winning
in the end. This is paradoxical. Those who think they are a hero and win usually
end up being remembered as a villain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Characteristics of a guide&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empathy and Authority are a precise one-two punch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;1. Empathy&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we empathise with customers we show that we understand them, and
understanding produces trust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People want to be &lt;em&gt;seen, heard and understood&lt;/em&gt;. This is the essence of empathy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;we understand how it feels to …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;em&gt;no-one should have to experience …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;em&gt;like you, we are frustrated by …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expressing empathy isn’t difficult. Once you’ve identified your customers
internal problem, let them know that you understand and would like to help them
find a resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brains like to conserve calories, energy, effort, time, so when a customer
realises they have a lot in common with a brand, they fill in any gaps with
trust. A customer will “batch” their thoughts, which means they are thinking in
chunks rather than in details. Commonality, whether in music taste or values, is
a powerful marketing tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;2. Authority&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one likes a know-it-all and no one wants to be preached at… But people &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;
want you to establish &lt;strong&gt;competence&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When looking for a guide, a hero trusts someone who has &lt;em&gt;demonstrable competence&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The guide should have some serious experience helping other heroes win their day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The guide doesn’t need to be perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are four ways to add authority (competence) to your marketing without
being arrogant:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Testimonials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logos&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Statistics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Awards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;A good first impression&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meeting a brand is like meeting a person,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can you help them live a &lt;strong&gt;better life&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can they &lt;strong&gt;associate their identity&lt;/strong&gt; with your brand?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can I &lt;strong&gt;respect&lt;/strong&gt; this brand?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can I &lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; this brand?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1 id="plan"&gt;Plan&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story was started be identifying something that the hero wants.&lt;br/&gt;
Then intrigue was created by defining their problem. The audience want to know
if we can help them overcome their problem.
Then we introduced ourself as the guide, and established authority and empathy
and trust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making a purchase is a characteristic of a committed relationship. The
commitment means there is a potential downside, they could waste their time and
money and feel foolish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine a customer trying to cross a river to get to their purchase. They can
hear the sound of a waterfall downstream. If they try to cross, by making a
purchase, there is a chance that something bad could happen. Put stones in the
river so they know how to cross, step by step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stones are the plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a movie, the guide gives the hero a plan. The plan tightens the focus of
the movie and creates a “path of hope” for the hero that might, possibly, lead
to the resolution of the hero’s problems. It creates a story gap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All effective plans do one of two things:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;remove a sense of risk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;clarify how to do business&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we don’t guide customers, they experience a little bit of confusion and use
that confusion as an excuse to not purchase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though the setup or purchase or after-purchase steps are obvious to us,
they are not obvious to customers. Give them a plan and they will feel more
confident about purchasing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Process Plan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The minimal (3 - 6) steps required to buy &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; get benefit from the
product after purchase, or a mixture of both. E.g.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make an appointment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allow us to create a customized plan.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let’s execute the plan together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A process plan removes confusion from the customers journey. When they see the
plan they think “oh that’s not difficult, I can do that” and then they purchase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A post-purchase process plan would alleviate confusion about how the customer
would &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt; the product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Agreement Plan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agreement plans are about alleviating fears. It’s a list of agreements you make
with the customer that are designed to alleviate their fears of doing business
with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An agreement plan can also work to highlight shared values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Give the agreement plan a good name and it can increase the perceived value of
your product. “the easy-installation plan”, “your best nights sleep ever”, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agreement plans can work in the background, they don’t have to be on the landing
page, though they could be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make an agreement plan by creating a list of all the things a customer could be
fearful about when doing business with you (haggling for price, interacting with
a pushy salesman, buying a lemon/defective product) and then create an promise
that would nullify that fear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customers want to know where you can take them. Unless you can take them
somewhere they want to go, why would they listen?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The marketing goal is that every potential customer knows where we want to take
them. Define a desire for your customer, and your marketing story will have a
powerful hook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heroes trust a guide who has a plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People are looking for a philosophy then can embody, or a series of steps they
can take to solve their problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Two kinds of plan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agreement Plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Process Plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both types work by earning trust and offer the custom a clear path to stability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="a-call-to-action"&gt;A Call To Action&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, we’ve defined a &lt;strong&gt;desire&lt;/strong&gt;, identified their &lt;strong&gt;challenges&lt;/strong&gt;,
&lt;strong&gt;empathized&lt;/strong&gt; with them, established our &lt;strong&gt;competency&lt;/strong&gt; and given them a
&lt;strong&gt;plan&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In stories, characters never take action on their own, there is always an
outside force (the guide) challenges them to make a change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heroes need to be challenged by external forces. Calls to action should be
clear, and should be repeated over and over. Above the fold, in the center of
the page. Also in the navbar. And also repeatedly as they scroll down the page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customers are bombarded with adverts and calls-to-action all day every day. They
are ignoring things and filtering out noise all the time. So don’t be shy or
subtle. Be very clear. Make it very simple. If you have confidence in your
product, make confident calls to action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Direct Calls&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;buy now&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;schedule an appointment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;order now&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;call today&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Register today&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repeat the same (singular, simple) call to action again and again down the page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Transitional Calls&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download our free &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; guide to growing your business&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free information - advice, guides, whitepapers, reports&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Giving something away for free&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Testimonials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Samples&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free-trials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good transitional &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CTA&lt;/span&gt; does three things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Establish expertise and authority, and positions you as a leader&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create reciprocity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positions you as a guide&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use both kinds in your messaging, and customers will understand (without burning
calories) what you (the guide) want them to do (the plan) to solve their problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heroes don’t take action by themselves, they &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be challenged. It’s just not
interesting if the hero can solve their own problems without an externality,
this is just how stories (and humans) work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Characters only take action when challenged by an outside force.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="what-is-at-stake"&gt;What is at stake?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stories live and die by a single question; “What is at stake?” If nothing can be
gained or lost then nobody cares. If there is nothing at stake in the story then
there is no story, it’s just not interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is no benefit to buying the product, then why buy it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have to show the customer the cost of &lt;em&gt;not buying&lt;/em&gt; the product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="avoid-failure"&gt;Avoid Failure&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story remains intersting as long as the hero is teeting on the edge between
success and failure. A hero in a story only ever has 2 motivations - to escape
pain or experience something good. Life is like that too, our desire to avoid
pain motivates us to make a change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There needs to be meaninful consequential stakes in the story, otherwise it isnt
interesting. Each scene needs to move the hero either closer to or further from
their tragic external threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A brand needs to answer the “what if I don’t buy” question because otherwise the
customer can ask “so what?” - the stakes need to be clearly, simply, concisely
communicated. Probably stake, not stakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can do it humorously. and only lights - it is salt to add flavor, not a
main-serving of fear. Compare the fear to the peace and stability that could be
achieved. If you show the pain “before” and contrast it to peace and stability
“after” then you’ve also opened and closed a story loop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blog titles, email subjects, headlines, can all contain elements of potential
failure to convey a sense of urgency. Bring up the negative stakes a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People fear losing \&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(100 more than they desire gaining \\)&lt;/span&gt;100 - loss and pain is
more motivating than reward and peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let the reader know they are vulnerable to a threat. “X% of Y get W”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let the reader know that since they &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; vulnerable, they should take action
   to reduce their vulnerability. “Make sure this doesnt happen and protect yourself”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give the customer a clear, concise simple plan to reduce their
   vulnerability. “We offer the thing you need”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Challenge people to take the next step right now. the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CTA&lt;/span&gt;. “Call us today to
   arrange an appointment”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agitate a bit of fear, and then return the reader to peace and prosperity, all
within 1 or 2 paragraphs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What are you helping your customers avoid?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s only a little salt to add flavor. If its too little, customers wont know
why your product is important. If its too strong it’ll be off-putting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="end-with-success"&gt;End with Success&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People want to change their lives and be taken into a new reality. Tell them how
their lives are going to improve - peace, status, confidence, abilities, preparedness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People want a vision of a happy ending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;We’re going to put a man on the moon”&lt;/em&gt; vs &lt;em&gt;“We would like a highly competitive and successful space program”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Answer each of these questions with a “before your brand” column and an “after your brand” column:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do they have?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are they feeling?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What’s an average day like?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is their status?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will show you how your customers lives will change and give lots of good
copy for your marketing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talk about the end vision really clearly. And use images of
happy/successful/powerful people enjoying the benefits of your product. Say the
benefits loudly, confidently, clearly, simply, repeatedly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talk about your end-vision for their lives once theyve benefited from your service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Show the customer a vision of how great their life will be if they do business
with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the end of the story should be a list of resolutions to your
customers problems. How do they feel and how have philosophical/justice
questions been resolved?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stories usually end in 1 of three ways:
1. The hero gains some status or power
    * Offer access - get a free coffee.
    * Offer a premium - skip the line.
    * Create scarcity - write “limited” on it.
    * Identity association - wear a Rolex and be associated with what Rolex stands for.
2. The hero has become unified with someone that makes them whole
    * The hero needed something they couldn’t get themselves, and external provision has saved them.
    * Reduced anxiety.
    * Reduces effort.
    * More time.
3. The hero has some internal realisation (coming of age) that gives them
   confidence to overcome their shortcomings and become “whole” and wise.
   They can achieve inner-peace and know that they have reached their potential
    * inspiration - chariots of fire - you can also run really fast
    * acceptance - fashion brands doing positive body image
    * transcendence - greater purpose and meaning - fair-trade coffee&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans are looking for resolution to their external, internal and philosophical
problems. They can achieve this though (among other things) status,
self-realization, self-acceptance, and transcendence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you product or service can help people achieve this then it should be a
central part of your brand promise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="people-want-your-brand-to-participate-in-their-transformation"&gt;People want your brand to participate in their transformation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are looking for a guide. Everybody wants to change either into someone
better or someone more self-accepting. You are helping them become wiser,
fitter, more equipped, accepted or peaceful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does the customer want to become? What is their aspirational identity? What
kind of person do they want to be? How do they want their friends to talk about them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Readers needs to be told very clearly how much the hero has changed and how far
they’ve come. Usually, the hero is deeply flawed right up until the final
climactic scene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A hero needs someone else to step into their life, tell them they are different
and special and better. That someone is a guide, that’s you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Offering an aspirational identity to our customers adds a lot of value to our
products and services. Realise that your customers want to transform and improve themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not all elements of a story should be used evenly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.3/latest.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';

    var configscript = document.createElement('script');
    configscript.type = 'text/x-mathjax-config';
    configscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'none' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        availableFonts: ['STIX', 'TeX']," +
        "        preferredFont: 'STIX'," +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";

    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(configscript);
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/><category term="reading"/><category term="marketing"/><category term="communication"/><category term="book"/></entry><entry><title>My Life Expectancy</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/my-life-expectancy.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-05-12T10:59:32+02:00</published><updated>2021-05-12T10:59:32+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-05-12:/my-life-expectancy.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="key-points"&gt;Key points:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weight doesn’t matter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be in “excellent” health.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workout 3 or 4 times a week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drink liquor (or red wine) 3 or 4 times a week (after each workout).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try to be happy, optimistic and relaxed. What are you working so hard for
   anyway? You need something to do, someone to love, something to hope for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1 id="longevity-calculations"&gt;Longevity Calculations&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was playing with the life expectancy calculator at &lt;a href="https://www.blueprintincome.com/tools/life-expectancy-calculator-how-long-will-i-live/"&gt;blueprintincome&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id="sf-my-life-expectancy-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-my-life-expectancy-1" title="There is also a more detailed calculator at projectbiglife, its calibrated for Canadian citizens."&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and was surprised to find that their regression technique gives me
a 50% chance of living to 95! I’d expected a result closer to 80.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After printing out a &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/90-year-life-calendar.jpg"&gt;90 year calendar&lt;/a&gt;, my next
thought was to play with the calculator to find the maximum age I could have a 50% chance of reaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing the factors below would apparently give me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;75% chance of living to 92&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;50% change of living to 101&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;25% chance of living to 107&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="dont-workout-every-day"&gt;Don’t workout every day&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no additional benefit from working out more than 4 times a week.
Once you’re fit and working out 4 times a week it doesn’t matter if you do
more exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being in “excellent” health is better than being in “very good” health though,
so make the workouts count. I guess if it didn’t make a difference then it
wouldn’t be excellent in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="drink-more-alcohol"&gt;Drink more alcohol&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was surprised that having 3-4 drinks each week increases your life
expectancy. I thought that it was best to not drink any alcohol at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should be drinking red wine or liquor 3 or 4 times each week. Liquor increases
longevity in men, but reduces longevity for women. Red wine increases longevity in
women, but has no effect in men&lt;sup id="sf-my-life-expectancy-2-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-my-life-expectancy-2" title="Alcohol consumption in later life and reaching longevity: the Netherlands Cohort Study "&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I guess I
should drink some rum after each workout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="weight-doesnt-make-a-different"&gt;Weight doesn’t make a different&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to their regression, my expected longevity is unchanged within a
weight range of 78kg - 90kg. I guess it’s much more important that I’m in
“excellent” health, working out 4 times a week and having some wine, rum, or
whiskey after each workout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="but-its-just-statistics"&gt;But it’s just statistics&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The calculator only asks for quantifiable or physical attributes. It doesn’t
consider emotional, relational or spiritual factors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-my-life-expectancy-1"&gt;There is also a more detailed
calculator at &lt;a href="https://www.projectbiglife.ca/life-expectancy-calculator"&gt;projectbiglife&lt;/a&gt;, its calibrated for Canadian citizens. &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-my-life-expectancy-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-my-life-expectancy-2"&gt;&lt;a href="https://academic.oup.com/ageing/article/49/3/395/5730334"&gt;Alcohol consumption in later life and
reaching longevity: the Netherlands Cohort Study
&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-my-life-expectancy-2-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="regression"/><category term="statistics"/><category term="life-expectancy"/><category term="death"/></entry><entry><title>Reading - April 2021</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/reading-april-2021.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-04-21T12:55:20+02:00</published><updated>2021-04-21T12:55:20+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-04-21:/reading-april-2021.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;div class="toc"&gt;&lt;span class="toctitle"&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/span&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#the-architecture-behind-a-one-person-tech-startup"&gt;The Architecture Behind A One-Person Tech Startup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#boring-tech-behind-a-one-person-saas"&gt;Boring tech behind a one person SaaS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#djangos-place-in-a-web-development-world"&gt;Djangos place in a web development world&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#cache-invalidation"&gt;&lt;s&gt;Cache invalidation&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#vim-abbreviations"&gt;Vim abbreviations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#to-fix-the-social-sciences-look-to-the-dark-ages-of-medicine"&gt;&lt;s&gt;To fix the social sciences, look to the “dark ages” of medicine&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#emotional-resilience-in-leadership-report"&gt;Emotional resilience in leadership report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#3-virtues-of-a-programmer"&gt;3 virtues of a programmer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#is-webassembly-magic-performance-pixie-dust"&gt;Is WebAssembly magic performance pixie dust?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#yamauchi-no10-family-office"&gt;Yamauchi No.10 Family Office&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#improve-and-extend-your-text-objects-with-targetsvim"&gt;Improve and Extend Your Text Objects With targets.vim&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#a-vim-guide-for-adept-users"&gt;A Vim Guide for Adept Users&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#deep-dive-in-cors"&gt;Deep dive in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CORS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#the-tty-demystified"&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TTY&lt;/span&gt; demystified&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Articles and blog posts I saved to read later:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the-architecture-behind-a-one-person-tech-startup"&gt;&lt;a href="https://anthonynsimon.com/blog/one-man-saas-architecture/"&gt;The Architecture Behind A One-Person Tech Startup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An article by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/anthonynsimon"&gt;Anthony Najjar Simon&lt;/a&gt; about how he runs his one-man SaaS using Django.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low stress, one-person company, run from a flat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-funded, taking things slow - &lt;em&gt;he likes taking things slow&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grateful to be standing on the shoulders of the open source giants who went ahead and made the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OSS&lt;/span&gt; stack we all enjoy and benefit from.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your own context matters when choosing a tech stack. There is no “holy grail”. I guess this means that you should use what you’re familiar with and what is &lt;em&gt;boring&lt;/em&gt; for you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses K8s on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AWS&lt;/span&gt;. He says “dont fall into the trap of thinking you need to use it too” - expertise with these tools was learnt over several years fighting fires on the day job.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Productive because he used the tools he is most familiar with and he can focus on shipping.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Django, Celery, PostgreSQL, Python, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AWS&lt;/span&gt;, Redis. - same as MoneyBar and PipPip.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="boring-tech-behind-a-one-person-saas"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.listennotes.com/blog/the-boring-technology-behind-a-one-person-23/"&gt;Boring tech behind a one person SaaS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The tech-stack keeps evolving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Boring” means “what I’m familiar with so that I can focus on the business”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of his time is spent talking to people and thinking. He spends 15% of his time on engineering. Probably it was more when he was setting stuff up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The methods described in the post are &lt;strong&gt;definitely not the best way&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;em&gt;It’s just one way of doing engineering in a very specific type of business. It’s not the only way.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Django, Celery, PostgreSQL, Python, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AWS&lt;/span&gt;, Redis. - same as MoneyBar and PipPip.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses Ansible for provisioning machines. - &lt;span class="caps"&gt;YAML&lt;/span&gt; files. Should look into this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Good enough for now”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Doesn’t use &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CI&lt;/span&gt; tools, he uses Ansible with a shell script he wrote.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses &lt;a href="https://www.datadoghq.com/"&gt;Datadog&lt;/a&gt; for monitoring and alerting, and PagerDuty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses &lt;a href="https://rollbar.com/"&gt;Rollbar&lt;/a&gt;, which seems similar to Sentry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses Slack, not to talk with humans, but integrations with Rollbar and Datadog, and also &lt;a href="https://api.slack.com/messaging/webhooks"&gt;slack incoming webhooks&lt;/a&gt; to be notified when someone signs up or does something interesting like deletes a thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make a “ding” sound whenever someone signs up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He’s &lt;em&gt;always very careful about operational stuff&lt;/em&gt; to prevent downtime and outages. Servers are over-provisioned to protect against spikes caused by sudden media interest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoids working from home or cafe cos its more productive in an office. Productivity is important - make every minute count. He doesn’t often work more than 8 hours/day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He optimizes for spending less time and making money instead of more time and saving money.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses &lt;code&gt;Vagrant&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;virtualbox&lt;/code&gt; on an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MBP&lt;/span&gt; so that dev work is on the same systems as prod infra.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses 1 monolithic repo. Likes this approach.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;He uses contractors&lt;/em&gt;!!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Usually, the biggest obstacle to building and shipping things is overthinking. What if this, what if that. You are not important at all and no one cares. No one sees. Even if you screw up the initial product launch, no one will care because they’re not looking. Only when you’ve proved that you deserve their attention will you have any attention and visibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://hackernoon.com/think-big-start-small-act-fast-6fdab1f771ea"&gt;Think big, start small, act fast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use boring technology, or whatever tech you want. Just make sure you’re solving an actual problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ignore the &lt;a href="https://stevemcconnell.com/articles/cargo-cult-software-engineering/"&gt;cargo cult people&lt;/a&gt; and ignore the noise. Keep calm and carry on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="djangos-place-in-a-web-development-world"&gt;&lt;a href="https://thenewstack.io/djangos-place-in-a-web-development-world-ruled-by-react/"&gt;Djangos place in a web development world&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not everything needs to be an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SPA&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Django is a back-end framework, it’ll work with an front-end framework, because separation of concerns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To use django with an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SPA&lt;/span&gt;, you could use &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DRF&lt;/span&gt;, or just normal views that return &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JSON&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reading this makes me want to check out React to see what all the fuss is about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="cache-invalidation"&gt;&lt;s&gt;&lt;a href="https://yihui.org/en/2018/06/cache-invalidation/"&gt;Cache invalidation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id="vim-abbreviations"&gt;&lt;a href="https://jovica.org/posts/vim_abbreviations/"&gt;Vim abbreviations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cool and all, but not as powerful as snippets I think.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Auto correcting typos: teh -&amp;gt; the&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expanding phrases: kr -&amp;gt; kind regards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi-line text expansion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It really seems similar to what I’m using UltiSnips for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I found &lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/30266587/snippets-vs-abbreviations-in-vim"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; question on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SO&lt;/span&gt; comparing abbreviations and snippets. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TLDR&lt;/span&gt;: It’s easier to add and maintain snippets than abbreviations, and you have less boilerplate with snippets than abbreviations, especially in complex cases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="to-fix-the-social-sciences-look-to-the-dark-ages-of-medicine"&gt;&lt;s&gt;&lt;a href="https://thereader.mitpress.mit.edu/social-sciences-dark-ages/"&gt;To fix the social sciences, look to the “dark ages” of medicine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id="emotional-resilience-in-leadership-report"&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/18FfZ86PGA_uSFf425EzKXAmiFQLFBPqjqPN7iu1TZRw/preview?pru=AAABdEZGCv8*_gdPBrQH8tAPyvMfLk6Unw"&gt;Emotional resilience in leadership report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id="3-virtues-of-a-programmer"&gt;&lt;a href="http://threevirtues.com/"&gt;3 virtues of a programmer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laziness - The quality that makes you go to great effort to reduce overall energy expenditure. It makes you write labor-saving programs that other people will find useful and document what you wrote so you don’t have to answer so many questions about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Impatience - The anger you feel when the computer is being lazy. This makes you write programs that don’t just react to your needs, but actually anticipate them. Or at least pretend to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hubris - The quality that makes you write (and maintain) programs that other people won’t want to say bad things about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also, I read a quote somewhere saying the mark of a great program is having people use it in ways you didn’t expect, or something like that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="is-webassembly-magic-performance-pixie-dust"&gt;&lt;a href="https://surma.dev/things/js-to-asc/"&gt;Is WebAssembly magic performance pixie dust?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id="yamauchi-no10-family-office"&gt;&lt;a href="https://y-n10.com/"&gt;Yamauchi No.10 Family Office&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A beautifully designed website.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="improve-and-extend-your-text-objects-with-targetsvim"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.barbarianmeetscoding.com/blog/exploring-vim-plugins-improve-and-extend-your-text-objects-with-targets-vim"&gt;Improve and Extend Your Text Objects With targets.vim&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id="a-vim-guide-for-adept-users"&gt;&lt;a href="https://thevaluable.dev/vim-adept"&gt;A Vim Guide for Adept Users&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to manipulate multiple quickfix and location lists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are digraphs and how to use them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Useful keystrokes in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;INSERT&lt;/span&gt; mode.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Useful keystrokes in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VISUAL&lt;/span&gt; mode.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vim regular expressions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using shell commands in Vim.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Folding content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="deep-dive-in-cors"&gt;&lt;a href="https://ieftimov.com/post/deep-dive-cors-history-how-it-works-best-practices/"&gt;Deep dive in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CORS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the-tty-demystified"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.linusakesson.net/programming/tty/index.php"&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TTY&lt;/span&gt; demystified&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;ps 1&lt;/code&gt; - see which processes are running or sleeping. &lt;code&gt;WCHAN&lt;/code&gt; tells you which
    kernel event a waiting processing is awaiting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="reading"/></entry><entry><title>Tweets - April 2021</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/tweets-april-2021.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-04-21T10:39:48+02:00</published><updated>2021-04-21T10:39:48+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-04-21:/tweets-april-2021.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;div class="toc"&gt;&lt;span class="toctitle"&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/span&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#front-end"&gt;Front-End&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#entrepreneurship"&gt;Entrepreneurship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#mental-models"&gt;Mental Models&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#agency"&gt;Agency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#razors"&gt;Razors&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#crypto"&gt;Crypto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h1 id="front-end"&gt;Front-End&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt; 6 website for top landing page inspiration&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;• onepagelove .com by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/robhope?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@robhope&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt;• lapa .ninja by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/nguyendangtinh?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@nguyendangtinh&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt;• landingfolio .com by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dannypostmaa?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@dannypostmaa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;• saasframe .io by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AntoineMilkoff?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@AntoineMilkoff&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;• saaslandingpage .com by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Cruip_com?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@Cruip_com&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt;• saaspages .xyz by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Versoly?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@Versoly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Jim Raptis (@d__raptis) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/d__raptis/status/1382240459288895491?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;April 14, 2021&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="entrepreneurship"&gt;Entrepreneurship&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;anyone interested in a fun &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/microacquire?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@microacquire&lt;/a&gt; challenge?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;maybe 90 or 180 days from start to finish to build and sell a tiny company in public?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;would be really great M&amp;amp;A practice for my fellow founders&lt;/p&gt;— Jim Bisenius (@jim_bisenius) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jim_bisenius/status/1382169652403564546?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;April 14, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="mental-models"&gt;Mental Models&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;Tobi's favorite example of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FIRST&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PRINCIPLES&lt;/span&gt; is a Truck driver.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;His truck was sat still for 8 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HOURS&lt;/span&gt; on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;THANKSGIVING&lt;/span&gt; waiting for his cargo to be unloaded when he realized…&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;“Why not take the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WHOLE&lt;/span&gt; trailer off the back of my ship rather than unloading + reloading each item?”&lt;/p&gt;— George Mack (@george__mack) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/george__mack/status/1262509025515786248?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;May 18, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;LUTKE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEARNING&lt;/span&gt; 6 - &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TALENT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STACK&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LED&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BY&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CURIOSITY&lt;/span&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MBA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;He didn't have an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MBA&lt;/span&gt;. He didn't grind 100-hour workweeks. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Instead, he played video games (which led to coding) and he snowboarded (which led to an online snowboarding store). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This 'Talent Stack' led to Shopify.&lt;/p&gt;— George Mack (@george__mack) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/george__mack/status/1262509059841953801?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;May 18, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A super long thread, worth reading it all:
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;Josh Waitzkin might be the most &lt;span class="caps"&gt;INTERESTING&lt;/span&gt; person alive.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;He doesn't have Twitter. And he barely uses the internet.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;I've compiled my favorite 5 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MENTAL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MODELS&lt;/span&gt; of his below.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;THREAD&lt;/span&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;— George Mack (@george__mack) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/george__mack/status/1292206014746558471?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;August 8, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="agency"&gt;Agency&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;1/ &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HIGH&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AGENCY&lt;/span&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Once you &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SEE&lt;/span&gt; it - you can never &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UNSEE&lt;/span&gt; it. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Arguedbly the most important personality trait you can foster. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;I've thought about this concept every week for the last two years since I heard &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/EricRWeinstein?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@EricRWeinstein&lt;/a&gt; discuss it on &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/tferriss?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@tferriss&lt;/a&gt;' podcast. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;THREAD&lt;/span&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;— George Mack (@george__mack) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/george__mack/status/1068238562443841538?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;November 29, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="razors"&gt;Razors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;THREAD&lt;/span&gt;: 15 of the most useful razors and rules I've found.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Rules of thumb that simplify decisions.&lt;/p&gt;— George Mack (@george__mack) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/george__mack/status/1350513143387189248?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;January 16, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="crypto"&gt;Crypto&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt; Now let’s compare this to the stock-to-flow model. Below I added in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;S2F&lt;/span&gt; model, which is the aforementioned inflation rate regressed against price. /10 &lt;a href="https://t.co/eGRXIux6K2"&gt;pic.twitter.com/eGRXIux6K2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Jurrien Timmer (@TimmerFidelity) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/TimmerFidelity/status/1382026424014548995?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;April 13, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Bitcoin?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#Bitcoin&lt;/a&gt; is looking strong at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSI&lt;/span&gt; 92. Still not above &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSI&lt;/span&gt; 95 like 2017, 2013 and 2011 bull markets. I calculated &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BTC&lt;/span&gt; price needed for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSI&lt;/span&gt; 95 at April close: $92K. Let's see what the Coinbase &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IPO&lt;/span&gt; will do today🚀 &lt;a href="https://t.co/UTvdFWFhDK"&gt;pic.twitter.com/UTvdFWFhDK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— PlanB (@100trillionUSD) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/100trillionUSD/status/1382282077429719040?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;April 14, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="twitter"/></entry><entry><title>Over-Engineering this blog</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/over-engineering-this-blog.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-04-05T11:54:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-04-05T11:54:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-04-05:/over-engineering-this-blog.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the last few weeks I’ve spent an unreasonable amount of time and energy
making unnecessary improvements to this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of these improvements are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding keyboard shortcuts (type &lt;code&gt;?&lt;/code&gt; to find out which).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/Adding-search.html"&gt;Implementing&lt;/a&gt;, then
   &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/fuse-search.html"&gt;reimplementing&lt;/a&gt;, and then optimizing client
   side fuzzy search.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using &lt;code&gt;src-set&lt;/code&gt; to serve responsive images
   (&lt;a href="https://github.com/pelican-plugins/image-process"&gt;Image-Process&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lazy loading images to make this site load faster.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compressing page files using &lt;code&gt;brotli&lt;/code&gt; and also &lt;code&gt;gzip&lt;/code&gt;
   (&lt;a href="https://github.com/kurtmckee/pelican_precompress"&gt;Precompress&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trying (and ultimately failing) to avoid a “white flash” when dark mode is
   chosen and a new page loads (&lt;a href="https://github.com/tailwindlabs/tailwindcss/discussions/3904"&gt;Github
   discussion&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not really sure why I did it. It makes almost no difference to anyone but
me. It felt a bit compulsive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like tinkering, and it’s nice to build something that will continue to work
with no maintenance. I tell myself that over the next few years I will gain the
benefits of these features even when I’ve forgotten I implemented them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s taught me a lot of JavaScript, which is a great language to be familiar
with - it’s everywhere. I would warmly encourage someone younger than myself to
pursue interests for the sake of curiosity and fun. And there is a very high
chance that even if no-one uses the shortcuts except me, my new javascript
skills will come in useful somewhere else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even if they do I’m not sure its a good enough reason - things should be
built when they solve a present problem, not over-engineered for what-ifs and
maybes. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/You_aren%27t_gonna_need_it"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;YAGNI&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I
wouldn’t let myself do this in a professional capacity. There is a tension
between being curious and being focussed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not really sure that I need to justify myself. Its a hobby, I wanted to do
it, I enjoy tinkering with web technologies and learning new things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But also, I lost sleep over this - I stayed up too late, and let it put
pressure on other things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that being curious, and making room to play with interesting things, has
been one of the most useful approaches to personal development and up-skilling
myself. But there must be a limit..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a tension between wasting my time and taking a risk, and it will take
a few years before I know for sure if these efforts were worthwhile, or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it’s not fun, don’t do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Successful business owners seem to be very good at leaving things alone once
they’re “good enough”, and not being perfectionists. In fact, I think that
being a perfectionist is antithetical to being an entrepreneur. I am not a
perfectionist, I’m just really curious and have a big appetite for learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this “appetite for learning” stops me from focussing. I let myself become
distracted by adding new features to this blog, when instead I should zoom out
a bit and think about working towards a more substantial and meaningful goal,
to the exclusion of more minor goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that good entrepreneurs are very focussed, to a fault. I am not that
focussed. I am too distracted by life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a balancing act, there is a tension between being emotionally and
physically present with my family and friends, and ignoring as many things as
possible so that I can focus on doing something meaningful that is necessarily hard.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Technical/Web"/><category term="blog"/><category term="javascript"/><category term="self-reflection"/></entry><entry><title>Regrets Of The Dying</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/regrets-of-the-dying.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-02-01T22:52:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-02-01T22:52:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-02-01:/regrets-of-the-dying.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wish that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’d had the courage to live a life true to myself, not the life others expected of me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I hadn’t worked so hard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’d had the courage to express my feelings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I had stayed in touch with my friends.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’d let myself be happier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…the five most common regrets of terminally ill patients, as described by a
palliative care nurse&lt;sup id="sf-regrets-of-the-dying-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-regrets-of-the-dying-1" title="Source"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-regrets-of-the-dying-1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://bronnieware.com/blog/regrets-of-the-dying/"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-regrets-of-the-dying-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/></entry><entry><title>A List Of Unconnected Thoughts And Aphorisms</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-02-01T22:27:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-02-01T22:27:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-02-01:/a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do the people you care about love you back?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It does not matter how slowly you go as long as you do not stop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assume that nobody is going to help you, and nobody is going to stop you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Money is (just) fuel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets talk about the end. My current self, existing now, is to be seen in
    the context of my end, and my beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you want money, ask for advice. When you want advice, ask for money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You follow the rules of war for you, not your enemy. You fight by rules to
   keep your
   humanity.&lt;sup id="sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-1" title="source"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to be a top performer in any field you must become abnormal.
   Normal is average, which by definition, is far below the top! “We can always
   be average and do what’s normal. I’m not in this to do what’s normal.”
   –Kobe Bryant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Becoming Abnormally Good&lt;sup id="sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-2-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-2" title="source"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; at something:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No reasonable excuses - don’t make (reasonable) excuses that let you off the hook. You need the negative emotions that leads to inspired decision making.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not Worrying About What You Can’t Control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know it’s best to be genuinely friendly no matter who you’re trying to
    get information out of, thanks in part to the work of Hanns Scharff and a
    slew of studies on interrogation
    techniques&lt;sup id="sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-3-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-3" title="source"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.globalo.com/history-wwii-charlie-brown-franz-stigler-incident/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-2"&gt;&lt;a href="https://capitalandgrowth.org/answers/Article/3217401/Become-Abnormal"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-2-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-3"&gt;&lt;a href="https://psmag.com/social-justice/nazi-interrogator-revealed-value-kindness-84747"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-3-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/></entry><entry><title>Notes From An Interview With Geoffrey Hinton</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/notes-from-an-interview-with-geoffrey-hinton.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-02-01T22:17:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-02-01T22:17:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-02-01:/notes-from-an-interview-with-geoffrey-hinton.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read the literature, but don’t read too much&lt;/strong&gt; of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust your intuitions&lt;/strong&gt;, because if you don’t trust them then there’s no point&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="quo"&gt;‘&lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This person is either drunk or stupid&lt;/strong&gt;‘ - feedback on one of his papers that went on to become significant &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For creative researchers; read a bit of the literature and notice something that you think everybody is doing wrong. (I guess &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GH&lt;/span&gt; is contrarian in this sense)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look for a problem that doesn’t feel &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt;. Then figure out how to do it right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people tell you that your (contrarian) approach is just no good, just keep at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either your intuitions are good or they’re not. If they are good then you should follow them and you will eventually be successful. If they are bad then it doesn’t matter what you do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might as well trust your intuitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you try to replicate a published paper you discover all the little tricks needed to make it work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never stop programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you give a student something to do and they are a bad student then they’ll come back and say it didn’t work. They’ll say this because of some little decision they made which they didn’t realise was crucial. But if you give it to a good student, you can give them anything and they will come back and say it works&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read enough so that you start developing intuitions, and then trust your intuitions and go for it! - Don’t be too worried if everybody else says its nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think it’s a really good idea, and others tell you its complete nonsense, then you know you are really onto something!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One example of this is when Ramford and I first came up with variational methods, I sent a mail explaining it to a former student, who showed it to his colleagues. He told me that they said ‘Either this guy is drunk or he is just stupid’. They really really thought is was nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe that is partly because of how i explained it - I explained it in intuitive terms, but when you have what you think is a good idea and other people think it is complete rubbish, that is the sign of a really good idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See if you can find an advisor who has beliefs similar to your own, because if you work on stuff that your adviser feels deeply about, then you’ll get a lot of good advice and time from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read enough so that you can &lt;em&gt;trust your intuitions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/></entry><entry><title>Questions For Interesting Conversations</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/questions.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-02-01T22:05:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-02-01T22:05:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-02-01:/questions.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s the &lt;strong&gt;best piece of advice&lt;/strong&gt; you ever received?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What would you say to your &lt;strong&gt;18-year-old self&lt;/strong&gt; if you had a chat with them today?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever &lt;strong&gt;lost or rejected a friend&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tell me about &lt;strong&gt;a time when you changed your mind&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What have you been &lt;strong&gt;thinking about lately&lt;/strong&gt;? What’s on your mind?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you work in a language that’s not your mother tongue? &lt;strong&gt;What’s it like to live in translation&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is a &lt;strong&gt;choice between remembering and forgetting&lt;/strong&gt;, do you lean towards the side of forgetting?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Were you raised for &lt;strong&gt;autonomy or loyalty&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was there ever a moment where you thought, &lt;strong&gt;‘I’m giving up’&lt;/strong&gt; — what did you do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Was your identity given to you or chosen by you&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/></entry><entry><title>Photographs</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/photographs.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-22T11:42:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-22T11:42:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-22:/photographs.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/polder.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Polder and windmill" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/polder.jpeg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/polder.jpeg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/polder.jpeg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/polder.jpeg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/polder.jpeg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/dog_walker.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="dog walker" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/dog_walker.jpeg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/dog_walker.jpeg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/dog_walker.jpeg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/dog_walker.jpeg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/dog_walker.jpeg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/stompetoren.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="stompetoren" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/stompetoren.jpeg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/stompetoren.jpeg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/stompetoren.jpeg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/stompetoren.jpeg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/stompetoren.jpeg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/geese_on_polder.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="geese_on_polder" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/geese_on_polder.jpeg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/geese_on_polder.jpeg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/geese_on_polder.jpeg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/geese_on_polder.jpeg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/geese_on_polder.jpeg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/bridges_and_gates.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="bridges and gates" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/bridges_and_gates.jpeg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/bridges_and_gates.jpeg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/bridges_and_gates.jpeg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/bridges_and_gates.jpeg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/bridges_and_gates.jpeg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/clouds_and_lake.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="clounds above a lake" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/clouds_and_lake.jpeg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/clouds_and_lake.jpeg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/clouds_and_lake.jpeg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/clouds_and_lake.jpeg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/clouds_and_lake.jpeg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/sunset-turbines.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="sunset turbines" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/sunset-turbines.jpeg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/sunset-turbines.jpeg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/sunset-turbines.jpeg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/sunset-turbines.jpeg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/sunset-turbines.jpeg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/boat_in_mist.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="boat in the mist" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/boat_in_mist.jpeg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/boat_in_mist.jpeg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/boat_in_mist.jpeg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/boat_in_mist.jpeg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/boat_in_mist.jpeg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/path_to_knowwhere.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="path going nowhere" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/path_to_knowwhere.jpeg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/path_to_knowwhere.jpeg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/path_to_knowwhere.jpeg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/path_to_knowwhere.jpeg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/path_to_knowwhere.jpeg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/path_to_the_stars.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="path to the stars" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/path_to_the_stars.jpeg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/path_to_the_stars.jpeg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/path_to_the_stars.jpeg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/path_to_the_stars.jpeg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/path_to_the_stars.jpeg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/floating_huts.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="floating huts" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/floating_huts.jpeg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/floating_huts.jpeg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/floating_huts.jpeg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/floating_huts.jpeg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/photos/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/floating_huts.jpeg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Other"/></entry><entry><title>Mental Models I Used To Use</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/mental-models-i-used-to-use.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-20T16:48:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T16:48:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-20:/mental-models-i-used-to-use.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The rules&lt;sup id="sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-1" title="or policies"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and mental models that helped me
succeed in one season or phase of life may not be the best for the next phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a list of a few mental models I remember being concious of in previous
years. Probably I’ve already forgotten some.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Always ask “why…”&lt;/em&gt;. Be obsessive about this. It’s going to make things
    harder for a while before things get easier. You’ll find difficult answers
    that you otherwise wouldn’t. If you’re only concerned with the present then
    its true that ignorance is bliss, but otherwise it’s a liability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;What if…”&lt;/em&gt; is another good question to ask a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adapt&lt;/em&gt; to the situation, don’t make it adapt to you if you have any
    choice. Be kind of like water, going around things and through the gaps.
    Look for the edges and the gaps, the parts that aren’t well known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Let people talk&lt;/em&gt; as much as they want to. Shut up and listen. If they
    mean you harm or don’t respect you then it’ll become more obvious the more
    they keep talking. If they mean you well or they’re saying something
    useful, you will benefit more from letting them talk more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inversion&lt;/em&gt; - it can be hard to know if you should do something, but how
    would you feel if you didn’t do it, or if it didn’t happen?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Regrets are inevitable&lt;/em&gt;, everyone has them. Same as making mistakes. Let
    your regrets be for things that you did do, and not what you didn’t do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are willing to try something, fail at it, and still be glad that you
    tried, then you should almost definitely do it. Commit to it and enjoy the
    experience! Don’t be scared, or at least, be scared &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; optimistic and
    happy&lt;sup id="sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-2-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-2" title="Courage isn’t the absence of fear. It’s being scared and doing     the right thing anyway."&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is beauty and luxury in being in such a bad spot that you are backed
    into a corner with seemingly no way out. Things become black and white,
    instead of shades of gray, and that will make priorities and options much
    clearer. You are likely to work very efficiently and effectively in this
    scenario, and you will learn important things about yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I’m older and I have responsibilities, I can’t ever let things
become so bad that a situation becomes black and white. I have to
navigate a world of grays. If they do become black and white, I’ll
already have a long list of failings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was younger, things were more fragile. My resources were smaller and
things could quickly flip from good to bad. Enjoy the few benefits that a
situation like that gives, because (hopefully) once its gone its gone for good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to solve a problem is to prevent it from occurring in the first
    place. Succeeding at this will bring its own challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take responsibility for things you are not responsible for, kind of. Do it
    deliberately and for your own benefit, but don’t forget that you are only
    pretending that it’s your responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do this, you will force yourself to understand a situation more
deeply and from other peoples perspectives. This will let you learn faster
and help you in future. Keep this at arms length though - it’s make-believe
and you need to be able to switch it on and off. It’s a toy for you to play
with. This seems to be what “extreme responsibility” is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think its important to have mental models that you’re comfortable with,
because it lets you make decisions quickly and consistently. But understand
that &lt;a href="https://fs.blog/2015/11/map-and-territory/"&gt;the map is not the
territory&lt;/a&gt;, and these are just
tools in a toolbox.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-1"&gt;or policies &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-2"&gt;Courage isn’t the absence of fear. It’s being scared and doing
    the right thing anyway. &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-2-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/></entry><entry><title>What’s So Different About Now</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/whats-so-different-about-now.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-20T14:44:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T14:44:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-20:/whats-so-different-about-now.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I think we are less aware of our ignorance than previous generations. It is
easy to implicitly assume that all useful information is available to us, and
that we are therefore more informed than we really are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is because the internet has made information more accessible
and global air travel have made the world feel smaller.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whilst an individual would hopefully never pretend to know everything, I think
its easy to assume that the right information exists and is being used by the
people to whom it is relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the accessibility of all information has put us in a situation similar to
information scarcity. We still need to actively search for the information we
want, because the information that comes to us easily or for free is not equal
to what we find when we apply effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can easily have so many short pieces of news or information that I am
always slightly overwhelmed. The pace of modern communications encourages me to
never slow down enough to form my own questions or frame my own arguments. I
can always find &lt;em&gt;an&lt;/em&gt; answer to my questions, but when was the last time I checked
that whoever gave it to me wasn’t going to profit from it?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Social"/></entry><entry><title>Predicting the Future using Human Nature and Technology</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/what-happens-next.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-20T14:05:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T14:05:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-20:/what-happens-next.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Predicting the future sounds like a tough problem, but we try to do it all the
time without realising it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We predict the future when we think about how risky or scary something is, or
when we think about what’s really going to change because of an announcement or
press release. We try to predict the future when we’re at the supermarket
checkouts and we try to pick the queue that will move the fastest. I always
seem to pick the wrong one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There must be a million ways of trying to predicting the future but all the good
ones are models which reduce complexity and emphasise key considerations. One
of them could be comparing the influence of human nature and technology on the
outcome, and then comparing the event to what’s happened before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human nature doesn’t change, so if something is driven by fear or greed then it
probably doesn’t matter what century it occurs in. Technology &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; change, and
if something is enabled or prevented due to technological progress then the
date is important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is driving the scenario? Is it human nature or technology? Supermarket
checkouts are mostly manual and require a couple of adults to work together, so
human nature has a much bigger role on efficiency than tech. Young men will
stack and pack quickly, old women will be the opposite. What types of shopping
bags they have, or how they pay, or even how many items they’re buying, are
probably not going to lead you to the right decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same probably works for getting through airport security.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Social"/></entry><entry><title>Financial Doom And Gloom</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/financial-doom-and-gloom.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-19T14:57:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-19T14:57:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-19:/financial-doom-and-gloom.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Financial crises seem to happen fairly regularly so they shouldn’t be
unexpected. But no-one seems particularly concerned about our current financial
system, at the moment our attention is controlled by other threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m concerned that a lot of money has been injected into the money supply but
we haven’t seen any inflation. And I am concerned that the price of stocks
is no longer related to the value created by the company but instead by macro economics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a terrible time to be a value investor. This should be an alarming
statement. Value investing should &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; be a decent way to make money
unless markets are broken. If the price of something doesn’t represent its
value then a correction is inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interest rates are really low at the moment so if you have spare money and you
want to make it work for you then where do you put it? Not into a bank account,
because interest rates are low&lt;sup id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-1" title="Why are interest rates low? Because confidence in the economy is low, so central bankers have to lower interest rates to make it 1. Cheaper for a business to borrow money to invest in their business and therefore easier for a business investments to be profitable, and 2. So that its more attractive for investors to use their capital to invest in a business  (which grows the economy) relative to depositing spare cash in a bank account (which is safer but a less efficient way to deploy capital). Interest rates affect the relative risk-reward ratios of different investment strategies"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and not into government debt, because
the yield is so low. It has to be stocks if you want the value of your
investments to increase meaningfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But everyone is doing this which drives the price up, and because their price
is increasing they increase even further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that the main reason for concern is super low interest rates and
massive increases in the money supply, but there are a couple of other factors
that are also contributing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easier than ever for retail investors to participate in the stock market,
and this seems like a good idea. Democratization. However if retail investors
have influence to effect prices, and they themselves can be manipulated or
influenced regarding what or when they buy or sell, then that is likely a new
kind of threat to financial stability. We’ve never seen social media combined
with quick, cheap investment services for amateurs before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Index funds are also more popular than ever&lt;sup id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-2-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-2" title="Index Funds Are the New Kings of Wall Street"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; - the efficacy of index investing
relative to traditional funds that use stock pickers is very high over medium
or long time horizons because index funds are much cheaper. But if index
funds become too large then they end up influencing the market in predictable
and rigid ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Index funds cannot choose what they buy or how much they buy - they just track
the index. If a company’s stock crosses certain thresholds, their stock has
to be bought or sold. It seems like its possible to create feedback loops where
funds have to buy more of a rising stock, which increases its scarcity and
price, which then requires index funds to purchase more of the same stock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The amount of euros in existence in 2019 was 90% more than in
2010.&lt;sup id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-3-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-3" title="statista"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
But inflation between 2010 and 2020 is
13%.&lt;sup id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-4-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-4" title="in2013dollars.com"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Why is that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the price of something doesn’t represent its value, then a correction is inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-1"&gt;Why are interest rates low? Because
confidence in the economy is low, so central bankers have to lower interest
rates to make it 1. Cheaper for a business to borrow money to invest in their business and
therefore easier for a business investments to be profitable, and 2. So that
its more attractive for investors to use their capital to invest in a business 
(which grows the economy) relative to depositing spare cash in a bank account (which is safer but a less efficient way to deploy capital). Interest rates affect the relative risk-reward ratios of
different investment strategies &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-2"&gt;&lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20210119144242/https://www.wsj.com/articles/index-funds-are-the-new-kings-of-wall-street-11568799004"&gt;Index Funds Are the New Kings of Wall Street&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-2-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-3"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/254220/value-of-euro-coins-in-circulation-since-2002/"&gt;statista&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-3-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-4"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.in2013dollars.com/europe/inflation/2010"&gt;in2013dollars.com&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-4-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Social"/></entry><entry><title>Why I Want To Write Regularly</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/why-i-want-to-write-regularly.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-18T11:51:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-18T11:51:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-18:/why-i-want-to-write-regularly.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve started writing more frequently. I want to do this because I often have
thoughts which I’d like to explore and develop further but rarely do. Writing
forces me to organise my thoughts and look at how substantial they really are,
or aren’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is truth in the saying that “to know a thing you need to be able to teach
it” &lt;sup id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1" title="Wikipedia article, and some external validation."&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
, and writing well has several similarities to teaching. Can I really copy a
collection of thoughts from my head to yours?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Powerful ideas are resilient and have many consequences. The older I get the more I believe
that ideas matter&lt;sup id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2" title="A complimentary notion is that asking the right question is more important than finding the right answer. I guess asking the right question is always necessary, but finding the right answer is only sometimes sufficient. Sometimes you can get the answer a bit wrong if you asked the right question, and still get enough benefits to avoid the problem."&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. They have so many
subtle consequences. They are the first
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domino_effect"&gt;dominos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t expect writing regularly to become a permanent habit - it doesn’t need
to be. But I do want to focus on it for awhile so that I become significantly
better. It’s a skill that has too many benefits to be ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blogs I remember most are focussed and unapologetic about their priorities.
Most of them have a lot of text and do not focus on design. They make it easy
to read content and don’t spend time or attention on header images or styling. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I redesigned this blog I had default settings that asked me to supply an
image for each post, and for a summary, and a suggested tweet. None of it was
necessary and whilst they all tried to make the blog better they ended up
making it harder to write. These peripheral features added complexity and
distracted from the main thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They’re are still there if I want to use them but they are not set up
to be used by default anymore. They’ve been moved to the background and if I
forget they exist then that’s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt; - it just shows they weren’t as important in
practice as I thought they would be. I was probably just having fun adding new
features and working out how to build them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/You_aren%27t_gonna_need_it"&gt;You Ain’t Gonna Need
It&lt;/a&gt;, mate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1"&gt;Wikipedia
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Learning_by_teaching"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;, and some
&lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20210118112910/https://digest.bps.org.uk/2018/05/04/learning-by-teaching-others-is-extremely-effective-a-new-study-tested-a-key-reason-why/"&gt;external
validation&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2"&gt;A complimentary notion is that asking the right question is more
important than finding the right answer. I guess asking the right question is
always necessary, but finding the right answer is only sometimes &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Necessity_and_sufficiency"&gt;sufficient&lt;/a&gt;.
Sometimes you can get the answer a bit wrong if you asked the right question,
and still get enough benefits to avoid the problem. &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/></entry><entry><title>Using RSS</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/using-rss.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-14T16:52:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-14T16:52:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-14:/using-rss.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Updated: 10 Feb 2021&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found a &lt;a href="https://brandur.org/fragments/rss-abandon"&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; which is
surprisingly similar to my thoughts on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; feeds, but better presented and
thought through. The post mentions the idea that “&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; is about capturing the
long tail of blogs that don’t post frequently”
&lt;sup id="sf-using-rss-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-using-rss-1" title="https://marco.org/2013/03/26/power-of-rss"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This idea crystalised why I was so glad I’d started using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; feeds
again. If readers use &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt;, then authors don’t need to concern themselves with
attention. This removes pressure on the author to post
frequently and lets them focus on quality over quantity. News feeds and ad
supported platforms have fundamentally different mechanics and incentives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; I can let good quality content come to me, on its own schedule. I
don’t need to remember to look for it, and the authors don’t need to remind me
that they exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="google-reader"&gt;Google Reader&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; is a very effective way of having good quality information
come to you. Back in 2008, I used to use Google Reader to subscribe to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt;
feeds. I was an aspiring photographer back then and I remember being subscribed
to around 80 blogs. Each day I’d read articles from whoever had posted
something new, without needing to visit their websites or remember who they are
or that I’d subscribed to their blog. The authors didn’t need to optimize their
output according to an opaque and changing algorithm either - they didn’t need
to optimize article length, tags, post frequency, image inclusion or linked
content. They could write how they wanted to, which I suspect leads to higher
quality content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="social-media"&gt;Social Media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years later Google Reader was closed down, presumably because using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt;
didn’t fit with Googles advertising model. I was unaware of it at the time but
I imagine it sent shockwaves through blogging communities and probably upended
many businesses. I mostly stopped reading blogs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook was growing fast, Instagram felt new and exciting, and content was
moving onto ‘platforms’, or into walled gardens. And as they kept on growing
the average quality of the content decreased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter is like this now I think. There are some real diamonds to be found from
time to time, but there’s a lot of mud too. Mostly its just mud, but the
occasional diamond can have outsized benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; isn’t like this. I choose the contents of my ‘news feed’, and
each article can be much longer than a Tweet, or a caption to a photo, or a
status update. It’s hard to write well and to create an interesting or useful blog
post, and that makes it harder to dilute quality with entertaining
distractions. I have complete control about what content I see, and I can
change it whenever I want. The process is designed around me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="reeder5"&gt;Reeder5&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used &lt;code&gt;netNewsWire&lt;/code&gt; for a few weeks, but it couldn’t sync between my laptop
and phone, so I bought &lt;code&gt;Reeder 5&lt;/code&gt;. It’s got a few unusual design patterns, but
 it works well and has all the features I want. I’ve been unsubscribing from
 email newsletters and subscribing to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; feed instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It keeps my inbox quieter, and it feels good to have a ‘separation of
 concerns’. It makes it easier to read interesting content without being distracted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-using-rss-1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://marco.org/2013/03/26/power-of-rss"&gt;https://marco.org/2013/03/26/power-of-rss&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-using-rss-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/></entry><entry><title>Why Talk About Jesus?</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/faith-in-jesus.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-05T18:24:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-05T18:24:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-05:/faith-in-jesus.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="start-with-happiness"&gt;Start with happiness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems to me that I am much happier as a Christian than I would be if I
weren’t. By “being a Christian” I mean following Jesus - trying my best to act,
think and speak like he want’s me to because I’m grateful that he did what I
believe he did. I believe he died for my sins and is now alive, having been
miraculously resurrected by his father&lt;sup id="sf-faith-in-jesus-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-faith-in-jesus-1" title="And many other things also."&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
(who is now my father too).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not just an intellectual exercise. I believe that Jesus is alive because I
seem to have experienced his companionship and intervention in my day-to-day
life. This is unusual, mind boggling, and makes things significantly more
complicated than if I thought he were dead. Nonetheless it seems to be true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not like I see supernatural intervention every day or anything, but there
have been various times - too many to discard - when my prayers have been
answered in practical ways (I’ll leave out the intangible for now) that have
surprised me and given me a lot of respect for the risen Jesus doing what its
said he’d do in the bible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="obvious-answers"&gt;Obvious answers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was this time I was in Yemen trying to get back to my room across town,
at night and during a storm. I was lost and couldn’t read Arabic to understand
which bus to get. So I prayed, and two buses later I got off at the right stop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another example, I was getting a haircut in Liverpool Street Station in London,
and as I was sitting in the chair someone took my work bag. When I came to pay,
I realised my laptop and wallet had gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trying to find a stolen bag in central London feels ridiculous. Even so, I spent
a few hours wondering around the alleys and parks looking for it, and I
resigned myself to some awkward conversations and using most of my next salary
to replace the stolen computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To my surprise, my parents-in-law prayed about it and were really confident it
would come back to me, which seemed super unlikely. A few days later I received
a call from an office worker in the Gherkin building - my bag was under his
desk and he wanted to know if I’d like to collect it. I guess I’ll try not to
make the same mistake twice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other example I tend to remember happened not long after I’d first moved to
Vienna. I was feeling lonely and isolated and I was wondering how on earth I
was going to find some sort of normal that was healthy and sustainable. Try as
I might, I wasn’t enjoying things at all and was feeling stressed and
overwhelmed. I remember walking up this steep hill in the 18th district towards
my office, and repeatedly praying this really simple prayer ‘God, please help,
please help, please help..’. It was that simple because I couldn’t think of
anything more useful to say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing dramatic happened that day, or even that week as far as I can remember.
But when I look back, it was a turning point when things started getting better
instead of worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suppose you can call this last example an intangible answer to prayer. Maybe
it is, but I think anyone whose grappled with overwhelming loneliness or panic
would say that the emotions become all too tangible at times. Being in a
different emotional state seemed to make a tangible difference to just about
every area of life. Eating, productivity at work, relationships with friends
and colleagues, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is only the beginning of why I think Jesus is alive and why I think
Christianity is a real and living faith. It’s not primarily a tradition, a worldview or a set of rules and ideals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christianity is a relationship with Jesus. He did lots of amazing things that
have let me have a very practical relationship with him. It’s an almost
unbelievable premise from which to live a life. It has so many implications.
And it holds up to scrutiny and my experiences bear it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-write-this"&gt;Why write this?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite Jesus’ incredible works and their implications, modern Christianity
seems to be in a really confused and ineffective state. Ideas and thoughts
about Christianity-the-faith have become mixed up with cultural christianity,
or christian politics and traditions. These are each different things, and unless we distinguish between them with the words we use, we are going to find it hard to think and communicate clearly. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suspect that we are in a negative cycle of imprecise thinking leading to imprecise articulation, which leads to further imprecise thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless we can talk and think about one thing at a time, atomically&lt;sup id="sf-faith-in-jesus-2-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-faith-in-jesus-2" title="from first principals"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; if necessary, we take on the additional risks of
reaching the wrong conclusions personally, or arguing with others due to
misunderstandings rather than actual disagreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should try to create a more precise vocabulary to navigate our Christian
lives, so that we can think clearly about the experiences and questions we have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imprecise thinking is frustrating, and conversations are less effective when
there’s an increased risk of disagreement or misunderstanding what someone
else means. This makes it harder to talk about our faith, which makes talking
less common, and this creates room for misunderstanding or apathy, or missed
opportunities, or sadness.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-faith-in-jesus-1"&gt;And many other things also. &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-faith-in-jesus-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-faith-in-jesus-2"&gt;from
first principals &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-faith-in-jesus-2-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Other"/></entry><entry><title>Product-Led Growth</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/product-led-growth.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-12-08T12:59:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-08T12:59:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-12-08:/product-led-growth.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My notes on &amp;ldquo;Product-Led Growth&amp;rdquo; by Wes&amp;nbsp;Bush&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="part-1-design-your-strategy"&gt;Part 1: Design your strategy&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-1-why-is-product-led-growth-of-rising-importance"&gt;Chapter 1: Why is product-led growth of rising importance?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product-Led Growth is a go-to-market (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt;) strategy that relies on using your product as the main vehicle to acquire, activate and retain customers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product-Led Growth (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLG&lt;/span&gt;) means that every team influences the product:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marketing - how can our products generate a demand fly-wheel?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sales - how can we use the product to qualify our prospects for us?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customer Success - how can we create a product that helps customers become successful beyond our dreams?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By having every team focussed on the product, you create a culture that is built around enduring customer value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By leading with the product throughout the org, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PL&lt;/span&gt; companies get&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shorter sales cycles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lower Customer Acquisition Costs (CACs)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;higher Revenue Per Employee (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPE&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; strategy is an action plan that specifies how a company will reach target customers and achieve a competitive advantage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In order to select a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt;, you first need to understand:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;market conditions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;competitive positioning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ideal customer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;product offering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowing these elements will help you choose the correct &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; that will
   acquire, retain and grow you customer base in the most capital-efficient way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sales-Led Go-To-Market Strategies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Profit Centers: Sales, Marketing, Customer Success&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cost Centers: Engineering, Product&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advantages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Annual Contract Value (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACV&lt;/span&gt;) can be very high&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enterprise first solutions that are very complex and therefore need a high-touch sales model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the Total Addressable Market (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;TAM&lt;/span&gt;) is very small, because your market is super niche, you can quite easily talk to almost all market participants. (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLG&lt;/span&gt; is built for large TAMs)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s great for new categories of product where education is required, because you need to change how people approach a problem. This takes time and requires education.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is turn requires that you understand your customers pain points, objections, core problems. If you jump to quickly a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLG&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; strategy then you risk a high church rate because you haven’t understood or educated
your customers well enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disadvantages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sales cycles are very long&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Life Time Value (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;LTV&lt;/span&gt;) must be high enough to recoup the investment in
  &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAC&lt;/span&gt;. This often requires charging the customer a premium. This premium
  price isn’t because the product is amazing, or more valuable to the
  customer, but because the customer acquisition model is more expensive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you use a Sales-Led &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt;, you need to watch out for competitors who can
  sell more efficiently, or have a more efficient Customer Acquisition
  Model. They can steal your market share by offering the same product with
  at a lower price.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customer Acquisition methods are super leaky. Most marketing-qualified leads (MQLs) never result in a closed deal, this is partly because:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it encourages markets to gate content in order to hit their &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MQL&lt;/span&gt; goals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it focusses on content consumption as a leading indicator of intent.
  (but reading a white-paper or brochure doesn’t mean I’m going to buy
  the thing).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the entire process rewards creating friction in the buying process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consequently, there is often a disconnect between marketing and sales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Product-Led Go-To-Market Strategies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Switching from Sales-Led &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; to Product-Led &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; creates a defensive moat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A product led marketing team asks “How can we use the product to qualify our prospects for us?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A product led customer success team asks “How can we create a product that helps customers be successful without our help?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A product-led engineering team asks “How can we create a product with a quick time-to-value?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Growth is much faster, because:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you need fewer resources to scale,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the top of the customer funnel is much wider.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAC&lt;/span&gt; is much lower&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Higher &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPE&lt;/span&gt; (revenue per employee)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User experience is better&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-2-free-freemium-or-demo"&gt;Chapter 2 - Free, Freemium or Demo&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MOAT&lt;/span&gt; framework to pick the right &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; strategy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt;arket Strategy - Dominant? Disruptive? Differentiated?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;O&lt;/strong&gt;cean Conditions - Blue or Red?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;udience - Do you have a top-down or bottom-up marketing strategy?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;ime to Value - How much time do you need for a customer to
  experience the value?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dominant - Do it better than the competition &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; charge a lower price&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is your &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TAM&lt;/span&gt; big enough?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does your product solve a specific job significantly better and at lower cost than anyone else on the market?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can the user realize significant ongoing value quickly with little or no help?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you want to be the undisputed market leader?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Differentiated - Pick and win a fight against an industry giant&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Main line of defense against the giant is specialization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on an underserved niche&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do a specific job better than the competition but charge significantly more&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is not a one-size-fits-all model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free trials and demos work well here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because its specialized, combining freemium with quick time-to-value is difficult&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Main competitive advantage is how you solve your customers problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does your market have underserved customers?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TAM&lt;/span&gt; big enough?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;is the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACV&lt;/span&gt; high enough?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Could prospects experience a Magic Moment during a free trial?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disruptive - Charge less for an inferior product (e.g. Canva, Google docs)&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build a simpler product that solves a specific pain point, and because its simpler, its faster, you can charge less, and its more appropriate to some over-served or priced-out customers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s a scaled-down product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Costs must be low&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product must be easy to use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TAM&lt;/span&gt; large enough?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can on-boarding be completely self-service?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freemium model thrives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-3-red-ocean-or-blue-ocean-markets"&gt;Chapter 3 - Red-Ocean or Blue-Ocean markets?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Red-ocean companies try to outperform their rivals in order to grab a larger share of the existing market. As the market gets crowded, opportunity for profit and growth reduces. Products become commodities. Cut-throat competition turns the waters red.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue-ocean companies access untapped market space and create demand. They have opportunity for highly profitable growth. Competition is irrelevant. Create and capture new demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some markets will be red-ocean, but a particular niche within it will be blue ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue Oceans require educating the customer to create the demand. This is high-touch, and often a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; strategy isn’t going to work. It needs to be sales-led in order to educate the customer enough. But if Time-To-Value (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;TTV&lt;/span&gt;) is short then &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLG&lt;/span&gt; could be great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Red Oceans need big wide funnels in order to compete, and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; strategies work great. They’re defensible, keep costs low and make sales cycles short.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-4-top-down-or-bottom-up-selling-strategy"&gt;Chapter 4 - Top-Down or Bottom-Up selling strategy?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLG&lt;/span&gt; works for bottom-up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High touch sales-led strategies work for Top-Down enterprise sales strategies, where the product is super complex and the sales cyccle is very long.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top-Down (Sales team is the growth engine):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Additional Services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lower customer churn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Poor revenue distribution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Long sales cycles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free Trial sometimes works&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bottom-Up (Product is the growth engine):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wider top-of-funnel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Predictable sales figures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revenue diversity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scalable fast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small contracts only&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;non-paying customers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;expertise shortage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;upfront investment as non-paying customers drain resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freemium&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free-Trial&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-5-time-to-value"&gt;Chapter 5 - Time-to-Value&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much time until you deliver on your promise to prospects?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much time until the product sells itself?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; strategies require fast time-to-value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rank your uses across 2 dimensions and group into 4 quadrants. The dimensions are Ability (low - high) and Motivation (low - high)&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low Motivation - Low Ability = Mission Impossible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High Motivation - Low Ability = Rookie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low Motivation - High Ability = Veteran&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High Motivation - High Ability = Spoiled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Figure out your top two quadrants. Unless all your users are Spoiled, you need to decrease Time-To-Value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How motivated are your users?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is your product easy for your target audience to use?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can users experience the core value (magic moment?) without hand-holding?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="part-2-build-your-foundation"&gt;Part 2 - Build Your Foundation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-7-build-a-product-led-foundation"&gt;Chapter 7 - Build a product-led foundation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A positive feedback loop:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understand&lt;/strong&gt; your value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Communicate&lt;/strong&gt; it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deliver&lt;/strong&gt; on your promise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-8-understand-your-value"&gt;Chapter 8 - Understand your value&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re selling live-chat software, you’re not really selling live-chat software, you are selling a new and better way to acquire customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are selling the outcome, the result, the why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pain makes us want to change so that we can avoid or prevent the pain altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pain is product agnostic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three reasons why people buy a product:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Functional Outcome - the core task that needs to get done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emotional Outcome - how a customer wants to feel or avoid feeling as a result of the functional outcome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social Outcome - how a customer wants to be perceived by others by using
   your product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In every software, there are usage patterns that point towards to core outcomes that are most important to customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest differences between sales-led and product-led companies is that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SL&lt;/span&gt; companies monitor usage patters to see if users are accomplishing meaningful outcomes. These outcomes are referred to as &lt;strong&gt;value-metrics&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A value-metric is the way you measure value exchange in your product&lt;/strong&gt;. They are the linchpin to successful execution of a product-led &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; strategy because you are aligning your revenue model directly with your customer acquisition model. Because your value metrics play a vital role in how you price your product, set up your monitoring, and build your team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Value metrics could be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for Vimeo, number of videos uploaded by the user.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for Slack, number of messages sent by the user&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for PayPal, amount of revenue generated by the user (processed?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;strong&gt;functional&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;outcome based&lt;/strong&gt; value metrics. Functional value metrics are “per user” or “per 100 videos”. Pricing scales around functions of usage. Outcome based value metrics charge based on the outcome, e.g. how many views a video received, or how much money a customer made when using your payment process method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many SaaS companies rely on feature differentiation as a way to justify higher prices, but this produces higher churn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Value metrics outperform feature differentiation with upto 75% less churn…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome based value metrics reduce church by an additional 40%. Apparently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A good value metric is easy for a customer to understand. They need to immediately understand what they’re paying for and where they fit in your packing/pricing structure. If you’re in an established market, it makes senses to look at what the competition charges.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A good value metric is aligned with the value that the customer receives through the product. Consider the low-level components of your high-level outcome. E.g. what low level actions are necessary to get the end result?  Sending lots of messages? Meeting lots of people? Finding lots of things?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A good value metric grows with your customers usage of the valuable outcome. If customers get incredible value from the product, charge them more because the product is worth it. Also, if they aren’t getting much value from the product, charge them less.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t do user based pricing if you want to get lots of users - its a conflict of interests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you’re small, you can try different pricing strategies and iterate to success.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask yourself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do my best customers do?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do my best customers not do?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What features did my best customers try first when they were on-boarding?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the similarities along my best customers that led to success?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For churned customers, what were the main differences between them and the
   best customers? Were they in the ideal audience? Why did they church? What
   did they do or not do that good customers didn’t?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Entrepreneurship"/><category term="marketing"/><category term="startups"/></entry><entry><title>The Mom Test</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/mom-test.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-12-04T16:07:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-04T16:07:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-12-04:/mom-test.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My notes on &amp;ldquo;The Mom Test&amp;rdquo; by Rob Fitzpatrick. It&amp;rsquo;s called the Mom Test because it leads to questions that even your mom couldn&amp;rsquo;t lie to you&amp;nbsp;about.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask good questions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid bad data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep it casual.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push for commitment and advancement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frame the meeting well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on the right, tight, customer segment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prep well, take good notes, review your notes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class="toc"&gt;&lt;span class="toctitle"&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/span&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#chapter-1-opinions-are-worthless"&gt;Chapter 1 - Opinions are worthless&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#chapter-2-avoid-bad-data"&gt;Chapter 2 - Avoid bad data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#chapter-3-ask-the-important-questions"&gt;Chapter 3 - Ask the important questions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#chapter-4-keep-it-casual"&gt;Chapter 4 - Keep it casual&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#chapter-5-the-currencies-of-conversation"&gt;Chapter 5 - The currencies of conversation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#chapter-6-finding-good-conversations"&gt;Chapter 6 - Finding good conversations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#chapter-7-choosing-you-customers"&gt;Chapter 7 - Choosing you customers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#chapter-8-getting-the-most-from-the-conversations-by-prepping-and-reviewing"&gt;Chapter 8 - Getting the most from the conversations by prepping and reviewing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-1-opinions-are-worthless"&gt;Chapter 1 - Opinions are worthless&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anything involving the future is an overly optimistic lie.&lt;/strong&gt;
You want objective facts about what happened in the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find out if people care about your idea by never mentioning it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Forcing yourself not to mention your idea will force you to ask better questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure your questions pass the mom test:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Talk about their lives, not your idea.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask about specific objective events in the past, not hypothetical scenarios.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spend most of your time listening, not talking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-2-avoid-bad-data"&gt;Chapter 2 - Avoid bad data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You aren’t allowed to tell them what their problem is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They aren’t allowed to tell you what to build.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bad data includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compliments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fluff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hypotheticals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ideas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-3-ask-the-important-questions"&gt;Chapter 3 - Ask the important questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should be terrified of at least one of the questions you ask in each conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search out the scary questions you’ve been unintentionally avoiding. What’s the worst thing a prospect could say? What’s the scariest question you could ask?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A good way to find scary questions is to imagine that your company has failed and then to ask why.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you get an unexpected answer to one of your questions and it doesn’t have any effect on what you’re going to do, then was it really worth asking it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;General advice for hard things includes asking hard questions. Imagine you were delegating the task, what would you tell the person to do? That’s you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can ask about money.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Love bad news - if you find out that your idea is fundamentally flawed you’ve just saved a tonne of time and energy and money. Move on. It’s getting you closer to the truth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bad news isn’t the result of an opinion. No one knows if your idea will work, only the market knows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opinions don’t count.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lukewarm response to your idea can be a great conversation, because you realise that your idea isn’t a great idea. Lukewarm means they don’t care enough to buy the first (worst) version before it’s ready.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look before you zoom. Don’t focus on details too soon, you need to understand the big picture first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have &lt;strong&gt;product risk&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;customer risk&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product risk&lt;/strong&gt; - can I build it and grow it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Customer risk&lt;/strong&gt; - is there a big enough group of people who are going to buy it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pre-plan a list of the 3 most important questions (including a scary one) before every meeting or conversation. Be ready with these. They should change from week to week. As you get good quality answers to existing questions you can bring in new questions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-4-keep-it-casual"&gt;Chapter 4 - Keep it casual&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Problem -&amp;gt; Solution -&amp;gt; Sales &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Normally you would have 3 meetings with a client when you make a big sale. This lets you do each stage really well without blurring the data:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify your prospect’s problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explain your solution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sell the solution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identifying a problem doesn’t have to be a meeting, keep it casual and you will get more honest feedback much faster. It works better as a chat when people are relaxed and saying what they really think.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It take 5 minutes (max) to identify if a problem exists and is important.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Give as little info as possible about your idea whilst still nudging the conversation along&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-5-the-currencies-of-conversation"&gt;Chapter 5 - The currencies of conversation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In early stage sales, the main goal is learning. Money is a side-effect.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will they spend &lt;strong&gt;money&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;time&lt;/strong&gt;, or &lt;strong&gt;reputation&lt;/strong&gt; on your solution?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If someone is willing to risk reputation, or spend time or money on your idea, then you can believe that they’re interested.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hearing a compliment means they’re trying to get rid of you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it’s a bad meeting or you’re not sure what they really think, push for a commitment of some kind. Ask them to spend time, reputation or money and you’ll see what they really think.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If they aren’t excited (not just interested, but in pain and excited for your solution) then you need to find that out &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ASAP&lt;/span&gt;. It’s still a good meeting if you can discover this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are you offering pain relief medication?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lead isn’t a real lead until you’ve given them a concrete chance to reject you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask learning questions by using the Mom Test, then confirm by selling it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need &lt;strong&gt;crazy customers&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They have a painful and expensive problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They know they have a painful and expensive problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They have the money to pay you to solve it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They already have their own bad solution to this terrible problem, and
  yours is clearly better&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A crazy customer doesn’t say “yeah that’s great, I’m really interested, let me know when its ready”. They say “&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AHHH&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;THIS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;THE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WORST&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PART&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OF&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MY&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LIFE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AND&lt;/span&gt; I &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WILL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PAY&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;YOU&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RIGHT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NOW&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TO&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FIX&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IT&lt;/span&gt;!”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A crazy customer will front you the money when all you have is a barely functional prototype made of duct-tape&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A crazy customer is the person reading you blog, searching for workarounds, when you haven’t spent loads of marketing and lead generation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep a crazy customer close - they’ll stick with you when times are tough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-6-finding-good-conversations"&gt;Chapter 6 - Finding good conversations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vision -&amp;gt; Framing -&amp;gt; Weakness -&amp;gt; Pedestal -&amp;gt; Ask&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep having conversations until you stop hearing new stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If it’s a topic you both care about, find an excuse. You’ll both enjoy the chat. You don’t need to mention your idea if it breaks the premise.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Warm introductions are the ideal way to start a new conversation. 6 degrees of freedom in the world, so find someone who knows someone who knows them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cold calls - LinkedIn, maybe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Serendipity - be prepared, be bold.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a good excuse - hustle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Landing pages - so that googling the problems brings them to you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organise an event - bring the businesses together for an event. You’ll be considered an expert because you’re facilitating it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Become a subject matter expert&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaking and teaching engagements - you get to have strong opinions, and you’ll be respected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-7-choosing-you-customers"&gt;Chapter 7 - Choosing you customers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Startups don’t starve, they drown. In options, choices, ideas. You get overwhelmed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose a good customer segment, focus on it, and don’t get distracted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the beginning:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google - PhD students.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PayPal - eBay.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evernote - Moms with recipes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It will look obvious with hindsight, probably not so obvious before you’ve figured it out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you can’t get a consistent answer to a question, maybe you’re speaking to different segments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you aren’t finding &lt;strong&gt;consistent problems and goals&lt;/strong&gt; then you don’t have a specific enough customer segment.&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Within the group, which type of person would want it the most?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would everyone within the group want to buy/use it? Or only some?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why does the subset want it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does everyone in the group have the same motivation?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What other motivations are there?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who else (outside the group) has these motivations?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go for &lt;strong&gt;Who-Where&lt;/strong&gt; pairs of segments. “Finance professionals who run marathons”..&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You want customers who are reachable, profitable, and personally rewarding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good segments are usually “who-where” pairs. If you don’t know where to find your customers, keep slicing until you do. Make sure the segment is reachable, profitable, and personally rewarding&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-8-getting-the-most-from-the-conversations-by-prepping-and-reviewing"&gt;Chapter 8 - Getting the most from the conversations by prepping and reviewing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prepare well&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have your &lt;strong&gt;three big questions&lt;/strong&gt; ready, including the scary ones.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Know who you are speaking to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Know what commitment and next-steps you want to push for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spend up to an hour writing down:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your best guesses about what you think they’ll say.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What they care about.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What they want.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a focussed segment, you’ll only need to do this occasionally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you come across a question which can be answered using the internet, use the internet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take good notes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask if you can record the audio.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Record emotions as well as words. Verbatim alone isn’t always accurate 6 months later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use shorthand for follow up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Observe and record emotions - happy, angry, meh, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pains and obstacles are a lot more important if someone is embarrassed or angry when they’re talking about them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dig into the big emotions, find out what’s causing them, or why its a big deal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review your notes&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meta - which questions went well or not?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What were the answers to the scary questions?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can you do better next time?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What were the clear signals? What signals did you miss?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Entrepreneurship"/><category term="book"/></entry><entry><title>Obviously Awesome</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/obviously-awesome.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-12-03T15:46:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-03T15:46:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-12-03:/obviously-awesome.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My notes on &amp;ldquo;Obviously Awesome&amp;rdquo; by April&amp;nbsp;Dunford&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Intro&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In order to do better marketing, understand your value and differentiators better&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand what makes a best-fit customer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positioning is a fundamental input to every business tactic you use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you fail at positioning, you fail at marketing and sales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positioning is “conext setting” for products&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customers need to be able to easily understand&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What your product does&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why it is special&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why it matters to them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your prospects can’t figure out what your product does quickly, they will
   invent a position for you. It might hide your key strengths or misunderstand
   your value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find people to demo your product to, then ask them to describe it back to
   you. Do the same with existing customers. If they’re not saying the same
   thing then you have a positioning problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Products with strong positioning:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find the best kind of customer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the value obvious&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sell quickly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="part-1"&gt;Part 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Positioning as context&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Without positioning to guide us, we don’t know how to understnad a product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positioning lets us make assumptions about&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who a product is for&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what its main features are&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how much it costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Without it we would be paralyzed by choice, and we wouldnt be able to make
   sense of all the products around us. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The context and purpose of a product from the founders/engineers perspective
   are often different to those of the prospect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Products can be positioned in multiple ways, and often the best positioning
   is not the default positioning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bad positioning makes it harder for prospects to figure out if your product
   is worth thinking about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positioning requires considering:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customers point of view - what problem/pain does it solve&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ways your product is uniquely different&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The characteristics of a potential customer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The best market context to make your value uniquely obvious&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Five (plus one) components of effective positioning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Competitive Alternatives - if you didn’t exist, what would your customers
   use instead?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Its what your prospects would use to do the task if your product didn’t
   exist. It could be excel, or pen and paper. It could be nothing, (in
   which case maybe you product doesn’t solve a real pain point.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You probably know a lot more about your market, and problem, and
   alternative solutions, than your prospects do. (“Doing nothing” could be
   an opportunity, not a red flag.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Its important to understand what customers will compare your product
   with, because this is how they will define “better”. Is it “easier” than
   a pen and paper?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customers might never have purchased a solution like yours before.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unique Attributes - What do you have that alternative do not?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Could be:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivery Model (online vs offline, installed on-site vs not)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Business model (rental vs purchase)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specific expertise (data scientist with financial and back-end web
   dev expertise)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Value (and quantifiable objective proof) - What value do the attributes
   enable for customers?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If unique attributes are your secret sauce, the value is why someone
   might care about your secret sauce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fact based, provable, demonstrable, quantifiable, objective. Third party
   opinions are relevant. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Target market characteristics - Who cares a lot about that value?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on customers who are most likely to purchase quickly, wont ask for
   discounts, will tell their friends about you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should clearly identify who these are and &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identity what sets them apart from other groups of customers. Why are
   they uniquely likely to buy from you when others wouldnt or would take
   longer to consider and make a purchase&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Market Category - What context makes your value obvious to the ideal
   customer?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Declaring that your product exists in a certain market triggers a
   powerful set of assumptions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make these assumptions help you, not hinder you. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When presented with your product, customers will try to use what they
   already know to figure out what your product is all about and why its
   special. You want them to be able to do this really quickly and easily. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make these assumptions work for you, not against you. You won’t have to
   list every feature, because most of them will be assumed by the context
   of the market category. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get it right, and sales efforts (copy) wont be wasted battling those
   assumptions, but can instead build off of them to show secret sauce and
   value more obviously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Bonus) Relevant Trends - what trends make your product relevant right
   now?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Used carefully, trends can show prospoects why they should pay attention
   to your product right now. Increases urgency.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can increase urgency, excitement, coolness, credibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;but the trend must be directly relevant, practically and objectively applicable. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blockchains, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AI&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ML&lt;/span&gt; are trends - they are relevant to multiple markets. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of these components is relevant to the others&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Entrepreneurship"/><category term="marketing"/><category term="positioning"/><category term="startups"/><category term="book"/></entry><entry><title>How I learnt to code</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/How-I-learnt-to-code.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-12-01T13:51:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-01T13:51:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-12-01:/How-I-learnt-to-code.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;4 years ago I started learning how to code, and it was difficult! It still is
difficult, but I now have a collection of tools and perspectives that make it
less daunting. Leveling up requires one more abstraction
to wrap my head around, or one more &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; to understand. I can do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I don’t think it needed to be so difficult, so now I’m building &lt;a href="https://codeschoolmeta.com"&gt;Code
School Meta&lt;/a&gt; to make it easier to learn how to code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning to code has been fun, ultimately successful, and life changing (hello
job security!) but at the beginning it was sooo slow, and super tricky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imposter syndrome is real, and I definitely felt it. I hadn’t taken any classes
in computer science, and I felt like I knew almost nothing about anything. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process began with Pandas, a (&lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt;) Python analytics library. Spreadsheets
were slowing me down at work, and I was bored. I found this &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/5JnMutdy6Fw"&gt;great
tutorial&lt;/a&gt; by Brandon Rhodes. From there I found
out about Jupyter Notebooks, and then I found about Github pages and how to
make a blog using &lt;a href="https://blog.getpelican.com/"&gt;pelican&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That led to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; (and also JavaScript, which I tried very hard to avoid
for as long as possible). I felt like a monkey bashing a keyboard as I tried to
make &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; elements do what I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unusally, I think Git was next. Mainly because I found this &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/rys-git-tutorial.html"&gt;amazing
tutorial&lt;/a&gt; to help me learn. It made Git seem &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt;,
and also helped &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; make more sense too. Bonus!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suddenly realized that great learning materials are crucial if I was going to
keep momentum and keep on enjoying the thrill of seeing the computer do
something I hadn’t made it do before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now I’m now working on &lt;a href="https://codeschoolmeta.com"&gt;Code School: Meta&lt;/a&gt;. It’s
an online community to make it easier to teach yourself how to code - less
confusion about how to get started or what to learn next, more encouragement,
and lots of high quality resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’d like to know more, please &lt;a href="https://codeschoolmeta.com"&gt;check it out&lt;/a&gt;
and sign up for updates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/><category term="learning"/><category term="code"/></entry><entry><title>The 1-Page Marketing Plan</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/1-page-marketing-plan.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-11-19T15:50:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-19T15:50:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-11-19:/1-page-marketing-plan.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My notes on &amp;ldquo;The 1-Page Marketing Plan&amp;rdquo; by Allan&amp;nbsp;Dib&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Marketing has three phases&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Before (prospect) - get people to know you and indicate interest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;During (lead) - get the to like you and buy from you for the first time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After (customer) - get them to trust you, buy from you regularly, and refer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new customers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marketing is &lt;em&gt;strategy&lt;/em&gt;, all the other things are &lt;em&gt;tactics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Jargon free definition of marketing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advertising&lt;/strong&gt; - The circus is coming to town, you paint a sign saying “Circus coming to town on Saturday”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Promotion&lt;/strong&gt; - Put the sign on the back of an elephant and walk it into town&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Publicity&lt;/strong&gt; - Walk the elephant through the mayors flower beds and let a newspaper write about it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Public relations&lt;/strong&gt; - Get the mayor to laugh about it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sales&lt;/strong&gt; - the town people go to the circus, you explain how much fun the entertainment is, they buy some tickets, you answer their questions, they spend lots of money on food, games, shows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marketing&lt;/strong&gt; is the plan that made the whole thing happen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Entrepreneurship"/><category term="Marketing"/><category term="book"/></entry><entry><title>Learning to market</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/marketing-101.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-11-19T12:40:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-19T12:40:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-11-19:/marketing-101.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve learnt many things this year by being a solo technical founder, but so far marketing isn&amp;rsquo;t one of them. I&amp;rsquo;m trying to change&amp;nbsp;that.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Since April I’ve been able to work full time as a solo founder. I’ve challenged
myself to build something useful enough that customers would want to pay for it
and in the process of seeking that goal I’ve become a much better and more
rounded developer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been working solo for about 7 months now, and in that time I’ve begun
using test driven development, I’ve built non-trivial data driven web apps
using Django, and I’ve learnt how to deploy and monitor those apps in
production and make them performant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve made two main apps; &lt;a href="https://moneybar.nl"&gt;moneybar.nl&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://pippip.email"&gt;pippip.email&lt;/a&gt;, and I’ve learnt so much. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m realising though, that I still have much to learn in other spheres. Being a
great developer is deeply meaningful to me. It’s literally a bucket list item
for me and I intend to be writing code as long as I live. But there is no point
creating products if no one knows they exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where marketing and positioning comes in. Right now it feels like I
know nothing about how to get users, or validate an idea, or position a
product. These are all super necessary and super unknown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a more meta level, I’m confronted with the lost benefits of working with
co-founders, or of having friends doing similar things. I want to work faster
and make progress more efficiently. I need to be part of a community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working in isolation does have its advantages, though. I’m self-taught and
self-directed, figuring out the contours of uncharted territory and creating my
own personal map. In my mind, I have a deep and almost personal relationship
with the coding abstractions and tools I’ve learnt to work with. Classes and
functions, strings and floats, literally have (to me) their own textures,
colors and weights when I think or dream about them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It feels like I can pick up these abstractions as if they were physical objects
and turn them around to examine them. Place them next to each other and compare
the differences. Run thought experiements. In my experience, this kind of
relationship and affection simply doesn’t happen when taking a class or
following someone elses schedule. It’s satisying to feel ownership of a skill
like this, and it’s one of the primary reasons I consider coding to be similar
to a craft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having said all that, now that I realise I need to validate my product,
position it, and figure out marketing, I’ve stopped writing code, put down my
tools, and I’m going to learn marketing. I’ve bought some books. Maybe I’ll
post some reviews here later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In no particular order here is what I plan to read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 1-Page marketing plan, by Allan Dib Obviously Awesome, by April Dunford&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lean Analytics, Hooked, How to build habit-forming products, by Nir Eyal The&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mom Test, by Rob Fitzpatrick&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is marketing, by Seth Godin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product-led growth, by Wes Bush&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t know if I’ve covered 90% of the distance required or 50%. It’s
exhausting but I’m here for the journey not the destination.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Entrepreneurship"/><category term="marketing"/><category term="growth"/></entry><entry><title>Pippip.Email</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/pippip.email.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-10-28T13:37:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-10-28T13:37:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-10-28:/pippip.email.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="pippip"&gt;&lt;a href="https://pippip.email"&gt;PipPip&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6 weeks ago I had an idea for a product whilst reading a news article. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be great if the writing and sending of important messages could be
separated, so that I could write something long before I needed to send it, and
know that then sending would happen at the right time without having to think
about it. This could be useful for sending my daughter a message on her 15th
birthday, or to my wife on our 10th anniversary. I also designed a check-in
mechanism, so that messages could be sent if I disappeared or pass away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://PipPip.email"&gt;PipPip&lt;/a&gt; is the result - event-driven and scheduled email delivery, from days to decades&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re working on validating the idea and finding the right niche audience. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Entrepreneurship"/><category term="PipPip"/></entry><entry><title>Between Clients</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/between-clients.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2019-10-08T16:05:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-10-08T16:05:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2019-10-08:/between-clients.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As a freelance data scientist, I use time between client engagements to up-skill and pursue professional interests that I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t otherwise be able&amp;nbsp;to.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At the end of the summer I had time between engagements to work on some side projects and grapple with some new (to me) libraries and technologies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;During August and September 2019, I:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practiced creating websites using the &lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com"&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt; web-framework&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigated and demo’ed &lt;a href="https://pypi.org/project/django-plotly-dash/"&gt;django-plotly-dash&lt;/a&gt; - a library that allows exposing &lt;a href="https://dash.plot.ly"&gt;Plotly Dash&lt;/a&gt; apps to django projects&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Built a personal finance dashboard using &lt;a href="https://dash.plot.ly"&gt;Plotly Dash&lt;/a&gt; and began turning it into a web app using &lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com"&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://pypi.org/project/django-plotly-dash/"&gt;django-plotly-dash&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interviewed for a role at &lt;a href="https://coinmetrics.io"&gt;CoinMetrics.io&lt;/a&gt; and created &lt;a href="https://blog.johnmathews.eu/btc-fork-analysis.html"&gt;this investigation&lt;/a&gt; as a technical exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Created a company “&lt;a href="https://atlasdata.nl"&gt;Atlas Consulting Internatonal&lt;/a&gt;” to facilitate life as a freelance data scientist and consultant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spent a lot of time working at the cafe in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IKEA&lt;/span&gt; because my co-working space wouldn’t let me stay late or work on public holidays&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduced myself to this &lt;a href="http://haarlemoffice.nl"&gt;new coworking space&lt;/a&gt; and suggested we could work together to create the best tech-focussed startup hub and coworking space in the Netherlands. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bought our first car. It required a lot more time and research than I expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Created &lt;a href="http://www.texnidata.com"&gt;Texni Data Consultancy&lt;/a&gt; with Dan Caputo to provide data strategy consultancy services. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Built the website for &lt;a href="http://www.texnidata.com"&gt;Texni Data&lt;/a&gt; using django and deployed it to Heroku with a custom domain name. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deployed a django app to &lt;a href="https://cloud.google.com"&gt;Google Cloud Platform&lt;/a&gt; using &lt;a href="https://cloud.google.com/appengine/"&gt;App Engine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Created a &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu"&gt;business website&lt;/a&gt; to represent my work as a freelance data scientist and made my &lt;a href="https://blog.johnmathews.eu"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; a subdomain of this site. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moved my blog off of github pages and onto &lt;a href="https://firebase.google.com"&gt;firebase&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks Github for several years of simple trouble free hosting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experimented with using storage buckets on Google Cloud Platform to host static sites and serve them over &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSL&lt;/span&gt;. My conclusion is that serving static sites using storage buckets is great - it’s simple, quick and cheap (free). But adding &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSL&lt;/span&gt; proved too difficult. I spent too many hours trying to create a loadbalancer that would work for both the root domain &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu"&gt;johnmathews.eu&lt;/a&gt; and also a subdomain &lt;a href="https://blog.johnmathews.eu"&gt;blog.johnmathews.eu&lt;/a&gt;. In the end I found out about firebase. Firebase is also quick and cheap (free) and simple enough to pick-up quickly. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Created a photo book using &lt;a href="https://www.photobox.co.uk"&gt;PhotoBox&lt;/a&gt; that turned out great. It covers the last 3.5 years and is mostly full of snapshots of our kids and selfies with Ritsya.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chose a primary school for my daughter to go to next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Social"/><category term="Freelance"/></entry><entry><title>Bakke-Rij</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/bakkerij.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2018-06-11T13:09:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-06-11T13:09:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2018-06-11:/bakkerij.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a great example of a creative and innovative coworking&amp;nbsp;space.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently began working in a new coworking space, sharing an office unit with another entrepreneur. What makes this coworking space unique is it’s conversion from an industrial bakery to a coworking space. Where the machinery once stood, converted shipping containers with glass walls have become offices for startups and freelancers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The skylights, glass walls and bright colors create a light and airy atmosphere, and the space seems popular with designers and founders working in creative industries. It’s an energetic space with a creative feel to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bakke-Rij" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/bakkerij1.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/bakkerij1.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/bakkerij1.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/bakkerij1.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/bakkerij1.jpg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bakke-Rij" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/bakkerij2.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/bakkerij2.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/bakkerij2.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/bakkerij2.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/bakkerij2.jpg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Entrepreneurship"/><category term="coworking"/><category term="Netherlands"/><category term="Haarlem"/></entry><entry><title>Reading: April 2018</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/reading-april-2018.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2018-06-04T15:52:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-06-04T15:52:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2018-06-04:/reading-april-2018.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A list of interesting things. June&amp;nbsp;2018&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="articles"&gt;Articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fs.blog/mental-models/"&gt;Mental models&lt;/a&gt; A comprehensive list organised around different disciplines. It a long read but probably one of the most easy to apply and tangibly useful articles I’ve read recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/vb.html"&gt;Life is short&lt;/a&gt; - Is life actually short, or would we always want more time, no matter how much we could have?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.eugenewei.com/blog/2018/5/21/invisible-asymptotes"&gt;Invisible asymptotes&lt;/a&gt; - A well written and long look at various facets of business strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://osam.com/Commentary/factors-from-scratch"&gt;Factors from scratch&lt;/a&gt; - Investing: A unified framework to explain how factors work. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://kottke.org/18/06/a-sad-update-about-a-scissors-maker-that-went-viral"&gt;This is tragic&lt;/a&gt; - “…But I do think this highlights the potential disconnects between mental health &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; business, publicity &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; success, and success &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; happiness. The internet can seem so intimate but ultimately it’s a thin view of an individual’s or company’s reality.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://statico.github.io/vim3.html"&gt;Vim&lt;/a&gt; after 15 years&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2018/03/27/a-complete-guide-to-cyprocurrency-regulations-around-the-world.html?__source=sharebar%7Clinkedin&amp;amp;par=sharebar"&gt;Cryptocurrency regulations around the world&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.lrb.co.uk/v40/n13/john-lanchester/after-the-fall"&gt;On the 2008 financial crisis&lt;/a&gt; - “I’m not sure if it’s philosophically possible for an action to be both necessary and a disaster, but that in essence is what the bailouts were.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="podcasts"&gt;Podcasts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/whatbitcoindid"&gt;Jill Carlson&lt;/a&gt; on the “What Bitcoin Did” podcast. “For the first time there is no longer a monopoly on the creation of value or monetary systems, that is really What Bitcoin Did.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/deVoaRTfVqs"&gt;Georges St-Pierre&lt;/a&gt; on the Joe Rogan podcast. A long and candid conversation from one of the world’s best athletes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/KqhRZfKRriU"&gt;Ricardo Spagni&lt;/a&gt; a.k.a Fluffypony on Monero vs Bitcoin, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EOS&lt;/span&gt;, the current bear market, Tari, and ASICs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="resources"&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lots of &lt;a href="https://vincentarelbundock.github.io/Rdatasets/datasets.html"&gt;data sets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/><category term="reading"/><category term="learning"/></entry><entry><title>Live near the ocean</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/ocean.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-11-23T18:48:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-11-23T18:48:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-11-23:/ocean.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Being near water is&amp;nbsp;better.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;California&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="California" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/california3.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/california3.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/california3.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/california3.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/california3.jpg 1600w"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="California" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/california7.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/california7.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/california7.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/california7.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/california7.jpg 1600w"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="California" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/california9.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/california9.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/california9.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/california9.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/california9.jpg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Dorset&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Dorset" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/dorset.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/dorset.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/dorset.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/dorset.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/dorset.jpg 1600w"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="Dorset" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/beach.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/beach.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/beach.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/beach.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/beach.jpg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Acapulco&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Acapulco" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/mex1.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/mex1.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/mex1.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/mex1.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/mex1.jpg 1600w"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="Acapulco" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/mex2.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/mex2.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/mex2.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/mex2.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/mex2.jpg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Dublin&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Dublin" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/dublin.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/dublin.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/dublin.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/dublin.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/dublin.jpg 1600w"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="Dublin" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/dublin1.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/dublin1.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/dublin1.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/dublin1.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/dublin1.jpg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Netherlands&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Hague" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/hague.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/hague.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/hague.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/hague.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/hague.jpg 1600w"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="Hague" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/amsterdam3.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/amsterdam3.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/amsterdam3.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/amsterdam3.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/amsterdam3.jpg 1600w"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="Hague" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/amsterdam1.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/amsterdam1.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/amsterdam1.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/amsterdam1.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/amsterdam1.jpg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="water"/></entry><entry><title>I’m a chartered accountant</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/chartered.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-10-19T21:56:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-10-19T21:56:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-10-19:/chartered.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve qualified as a chartered accountant and will soon become a member of the Institute of Chartered Accountants in England and&amp;nbsp;Wales&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year I qualified as a chartered accountant. Qualification requires
passing 15 exams and gaining 3150 hours of work experience. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To celebrate passing your exams and verify your success, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ICAEW&lt;/span&gt; print the
names of everyone who passed in an advert in the Financial Times. This happened
for me on the 26 January.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="exam pass list in the financial times" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/exam_pass_list.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/><category term="ICAEW"/><category term="ACA"/><category term="Accounting"/></entry><entry><title>Coworking in Dublin</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/coworking.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-09-15T11:55:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-09-15T11:55:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-09-15:/coworking.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A review of eight coworking spaces in&amp;nbsp;Dublin&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week I arrived in Dublin and had two days to find a coworking space. I ran around Dublin visiting as many as possible. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m looking to rent a hotdesk, which means I don’t have any storage space at the office and I don’t have a particular desk. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are my impressions of eight businesses offering either hot desks or dedicated desks, ranked in order of preference. It’s subjective. The going rate in Dublin seems to be €200 — €300 per month for a hot desk. Hours range from 9am - 7pm Monday - Friday, to 24/7. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;First place: &lt;a href="http://dogpatchlabs.com/"&gt;Dogpatch Labs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dogpatch offer a coworking space and access to a community of tech startups. They run regular networking and mentoring events and occupy 3 floors of a warehouse next to an old dock. The offices have a range of interiors styles. The middle level is fairly standard but pleasant open plan offices, the top floor is a flexible working space with event areas. The lower level is a series of vaults that each contain meeting rooms of various sizes. There’s a lot going on and there’s a good buzz in the air. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The range of interior spaces is a big plus for me and I’m looking forward to being able to switch up my working environment through the day. There’s a couple of kitchen areas, and a table football and table-tennis table on the top level. Access is 6am - midnight, and a hot desk is €200 per month. A dedicated desk is €400. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dogpatch occupy less than a quarter of the warehouse building, the remainder of the space is used as a shopping mall and a museum. In my opinion Dogpatch is by far the best value and if you’re working in tech it’ll probably be your go-to solution. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Second place: &lt;a href="http://studio9.ie/?page_id=223"&gt;Studio9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These guys are great. The space is a lot smaller that Dogpatch, comprising only ~12 desks. It’s a basement, but don’t let that put you off — its open plan and has large windows at either end. The space is well designed and uses a lot of light colours and textures, including wood on the walls and floors. There are also plenty of pot plants. These combine to give a bright and airy atmosphere that feels very natural and bright.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are alcoves down one side of the main room which serve as meeting rooms, and a garden and basic kitchen at the back. The owners want the space to foster a community, and I expect that this is achieved. There are no dedicated offices and no teams using multiple desks, everyone is an independent worker. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The desks are large, and each has its own little wall to provide some privacy. €200 per month ongoing, or €250 for just one month. They offer a trial day for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Third place: &lt;a href="http://www.officesuites.ie/locations/20-harcourt-street/"&gt;OfficeSuites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The building looks well run and appears clean and fresh with adequate resources. The building is an old Georgian tenement with high ceilings, cornicing and lots of natural light. The furnishings and decor lean towards corporate rather than something more interesting, but this works well to add a professional feel to the homely architecture. Access is 24/7. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s only two rooms for hotdesking, and most of the building is given to private offices. There’s a garden with bike storage, meeting rooms and a quiet room for calls. Lockers are extra. They also offer a free day as a trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;€249 p/m for desk access 9am-7pm Monday - Friday&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Fourth place: &lt;a href="https://www.element78.co/"&gt;Element78&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friendly and well resourced, but very corporate. The architecture is corporate glass and steel. They’re situated on the ground floor in a posh business district with large financials for neighbours. It’s too corporate for me, but if you wanted an impressive place to meet clients and a nice address, this could be it. There were about 15 hot-desks for rent, plus plenty of dedicated desks. Clients seemed to include mostly young tech companies and tech freelancers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m hoping to find somewhere with more of a community, more inspiring architecture, and more character. I was offered a free day as a trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;€200 for the first month then €350 p/m&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Fifth place: &lt;a href="https://glandore.co/flexible-workspace.aspx#Hot-Desk"&gt;Glandore&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Glandore offer a relatively luxurious package with a corporate feel. They have a few buildings in Dublin and only the flagship has hotdesking space. There’s a super looking restaurant and a large club room to relax in, but these are features that I don’t need, and the rates aren’t competitive if all you need is a desk and somewhere to take calls. It’s set up for teams and for impressing clients, and independent tech workers are probably better off elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;€295 p/m &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sixth place: &lt;a href="https://www.regus.ie/office-space/ireland/dublin/dublin-4-ballsbridge"&gt;Regus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regus offer a polished on boarding experience and the friendly staff were quick to respond and generally helpful, but the office space was bland, grey and generic. The rooms I visited didn’t have external windows and it reminded me of the rooms banks often put auditors in. If grey walls and tube lights are your thing then this is for you.  24/7 access, and meeting rooms equipped with A/V.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;€299.70 p/m.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Seventh place: &lt;a href="http://www.cocreate.ie/"&gt;CoCreate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I visited the southern branch and thought the building was a bit shabby and needed a new layer of paint. I recognised the desks as some of the cheapest available from &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IKEA&lt;/span&gt;. The rooms were small and needed cleaning, and there was weird art on the wall. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thought of paying €200 a month to sit at a small wobbly desk put me off. The place was also almost deserted. Maybe their other branch is better, but this is not for me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;€220 p/m. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Last place: &lt;a href="http://tcubedublin.com/tcube/index.html"&gt;tCube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last and least, tCube seems to be putting in zero effort. When I visited I saw two rooms that needed painting, disorganised furniture and abandoned bits of computers lying around. The kitchen isn’t high spec and the meeting room isn’t big enough. I was also given a speech about how great the wifi was - a prerequisite that was taken for granted everywhere else. At €300 p/m for a dedicated desk its easy to find better value elsewhere. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Social"/><category term="Freelance"/><category term="Coworking"/><category term="Dublin"/><category term="Element78"/><category term="Regus"/><category term="OfficeSuites"/><category term="CoCreate"/><category term="Studio9"/><category term="Glandore"/><category term="tCube"/></entry><entry><title>Corporate London</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/corporate.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-07-10T21:37:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-07-10T21:37:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-07-10:/corporate.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Reflections on 3 years living and working in&amp;nbsp;London&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="2014-2017"&gt;2014 - 2017&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having made arrangements to leave London, it seems like a reasonable time to
reflect on my time here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;London is a tough city to live in — it’s big enough that a sub 1-hour commute
is considered good, and it’s super expensive. My stay in London has been
defined by my quest to complete my graduate scheme and qualify as an accountant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first arrived I had no idea what London or working in a corporate would
be like. I was coming from academia, and my motivation for moving to finance
could be summed up in two points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand more about the 2008 financial crisis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get paid more for using mostly the same skills (math) as in engineering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t think there’s anything wrong with these motivations, but I should have
been making a long term career plan instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started my job I was surprised at the 6 weeks of induction and
hot-desking. Life as an auditor felt nomadic, as everyone would spend large
amounts of time at client’s offices, and no-one has their own desk in our
office. The only thing you really own is your knowledge and your network of relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2014, I arrived with a high opinion of my employer and the view that I would
be staying for several years. Having escaped the financial insecurity of
short-term research grants, I’d moved back to my home country to contribute to
the system that educated me. I was happy to have a regular job with a decent,
predictable salary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A phrase that kept coming to mind back then was “accountant factory”. Our
training materials were scripted and everything was a standardised process. We
were being processed. Graduates in, corporate accountants out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company is huge and so are the efficiencies and barriers to competition
that come with this. When I arrived I was impressed there were free biscuits,
and it felt presumptuous to put a meeting in someones diary. Now I ignore any
communications addressed to a mailing list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="accountant"&gt;Accountant&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The toughest experiences were related to the accountancy qualification. Naïvely
I had believed that the qualification wouldn’t be a big deal and I didn’t give
any thought to it when I applied — I just wanted to find out how banks worked.
If there were some exams to be done then it would be fine, I’d already achieved
a PhD and I would handle it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That turned out to be a mistake. A huge mistake. The alarm bells should have
rung louder when I realised most of my graduate colleagues had only applied so
that they could get the qualification (and were already intending to leave asap
afterwards). Doing the pre-course work before college wasn’t trivial. College -
I was being sent to a classroom again. We were being taken out of the office,
away from clients, and put in a classroom to prepare for these exams…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting a job that required becoming a chartered accountant, without
considering the effort and time involved to qualify was dumb. It’s an oversight
I find hard to believe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disappointment and sadness at having to study again was profound. The
teaching and assessment style was several steps behind what I’d become used to.
Compared to the depth, autonomy and research-focus of a doctorate, writing
cookie-cutter essays in time-pressured exams felt stupid. The exams were hard
and I failed several of them, probably because of my low morale whilst
revising. Retaking them required more weekends and annual leave being spent
away from my family, camped-out in libraries and offices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This required much patience and generosity from Ritsya, who having not seen me
for long periods during my doctorate expected us to have a more normal
lifestyle when we came to London. I found it miserable to pause my social life
and other interests whilst studying, and then I would try to rush back to them
when I had the time, knowing that soon I’d have to pause them again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I hadn’t already studied in Vienna, this process of working and studying in
London would have been exciting and felt valuable or special. I’d passed enough
exams though to know that they’re never as important as they’re made out to be,
and whatever it was that was missing from my life wasn’t going to be found in
another qualification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the upside though, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACA&lt;/span&gt; is the most practical qualification I’ve gained
and has taught me many useful aspects of business and finance. I’m glad to
finally see business not as some mysterious system but something attainable and understandable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="neighbourhood"&gt;Neighbourhood&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Living in London has also required a lot of time on trains — my door to desk
commute is about an hour each way, and I’ve never lived somewhere in London
that hasn’t felt transient. We’ve needed to live near a station and didn’t want
to commute more than an hour and that’s put us in neighbourhoods with other
young professionals who also don’t have long term plans (or financial ability)
to stay in the city. We’re all looking to move on and move up as fast as
possible.  I want to leave London partly because there are so many people with
the same attitudes and priorities as my own…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="corporate-culture"&gt;Corporate Culture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in the office I spent the first few months figuring out how people were
organised, how teams operated and how decisions were made. I think it took me
about a year to feel like I understood how things really worked, and 1.5 years
to feel like I could do all aspects of my job with certainty. There is a
difference between how things are spoken about, and how things actually happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My experience has been that performance is all that matters and behaviour is
defined by self-interest. I don’t think this is different from previous
environments I’ve worked in — academia isn’t any different&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and the
construction industry certainly isn’t. I wonder if the only way people can
endure it is if they’ve not experienced anything else, or think it normal, or
necessary. I find myself wishing we could be kinder to each other, and that we
could create structures that incentivise mutual support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corporate finance usually appears clean and well presented. Its people appear
dependable and capable. The culture is sanitised and there’s a lot of pressure
to conform - you can see it in the clothes and accessories we wear and the
jokes we tell each other in the canteen. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came to see my office as a glass and steel cathedral. I read about the Middle
East, and migrants arriving in Europe, and tower blocks burning, and felt
really disconnected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the high regard with which we hold ourselves, we don’t ask each other
how we can help. Maybe we are too busy, or feel powerless to help. Apparently
we do not know how to help, despite our wealth, talents, education and connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember watching a man leave the office one day and thought that if he gave
his whole career and left his firm after decades of service, there would be
nothing left to identify him after a few weeks. The work will always get done.
Market forces will dictate how the business adapts and grows. The City rolls on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Publications trump almost all other metrics, and the incentives to
  publish quantity over quality are such that risky or slow research is
  inexcusable. The metrics used to standardise success and allocate resources
  can be subverted just as well in academia as in any other industry. What
  management measures, the team prioritises. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="Career"/><category term="Corporate"/><category term="London"/></entry><entry><title>Move</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/move.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-07-08T12:26:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-07-08T12:26:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-07-08:/move.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Training&amp;rsquo;s&amp;nbsp;over&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="ambition"&gt;Ambition&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I was 15, one of my ambitions has been to be an entrepreneur. I used to joke with my dad about buying him a nice boat one day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life so far has been predominantly about education, and that stage is over now. I’m walking away from what I’ve come to see as a lifestyle and career that has too many contradictions, it doesn’t make sense to live like this. Ultimately I want to develop multiple sources of passive income. I want to create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="summer-2017"&gt;Summer 2017&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last few months have been intense, with some weeks leaving me feeling ambitious and energetic, and others feeling anxious and overwhelmed. I need to get better at defining a goal, taking the quickest path there, and ignoring interesting distractions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ritsya is brave enough and imaginative enough to force me to think big and consider how to live a better life. My biggest fear is that I screw it up, shooting myself in the foot and Ritsya and my daughter also. We were headed safely to an unremarkable existence and it would be terrible to swap that for something worse. That won’t happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that I make better decisions and produce my best work under pressure, I thrive when I’m perceived as an underdog. I need to accept this without using it as a reason to be foolish. Whilst I don’t have a clear plan, or direction, or goal, (I have many of them) I’ve got skills and I want to see what I can make. I’ll never do my best work, using my most productive combination of skills and experiences, if I’m a cog in someone else’s machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s safer being an employee than self-employed. I guess the price of removing self-employment risks is the difference between the value you generate for your employer and what you’re paid. I think those risks are overpriced, and most people are more capable than they realise. Sometimes you have to walk into a situation to find out how to make the most of it. And sometimes you have to leave a place in order to gain perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="autumn-2016"&gt;Autumn 2016&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year my boss gave me some advice that was supposed to be encouraging. I’d requested to reduce my involvement with some stuff that was unrelated to my job so that I could contribute more to my team and still maintain some semblance of a work/life balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My boss was pretty clear that reducing my involvement in the extra stuff would not be possible. During our conversation he advised me not to worry about how much I contributed to the team because “the work will get done anyway”. This was meant to be encouraging, but instead removed any conviction that the work I did was important.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="Lifestyle"/></entry><entry><title>Flee</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/flee.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-07-04T08:42:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-07-04T08:42:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-07-04:/flee.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Summer children 
squeal and shriek, &lt;br/&gt;
Watch wars. &lt;br/&gt;
Excitement mounts. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How exotic. 
Unexpectedly, &lt;br/&gt;
Death arrives. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grow-up&lt;br/&gt;
Grow old&lt;br/&gt;
Face death &lt;br/&gt;
Evade evil.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t tire. 
World is fragile.&lt;br/&gt;
Towers burn,&lt;br/&gt;
Bridges bludgeon,&lt;br/&gt;
Markets stab. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Got to get out.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="Poetry"/></entry><entry><title>Understanding VC Investment</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/investment.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-06-09T23:03:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-06-09T23:03:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-06-09:/investment.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;How to pitch to a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VC&lt;/span&gt;: Market, Management, Model,&amp;nbsp;Momentum&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I attended the &lt;a href="http://www.lis-summit.com/"&gt;Lisbon Investment Summit&lt;/a&gt; in June and wrote about my experiences &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/lis17.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. One of the best sessions was with &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Boris_Golden"&gt;Boris Golden&lt;/a&gt; called “Understand Investment”. These are my notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;VC&lt;/span&gt;’s are seeking to identify high-potential startups, and then support and fund them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are looking for something that is innovative and unproven.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A startup is not a company but an organisation searching for a business model,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whilst executing and discovering a scalable way to grow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Startups need money for ambitious but credible growth plans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A typical stake for a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VC&lt;/span&gt; could be roughly 20%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;VC&lt;/span&gt;’s want an exit price of at least 100m, otherwise their business models don’t work out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$10m can seem a lot for a founder with a 30% stake, but it’s not enough to attract VCs, so aim higher.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-to-pitch"&gt;How to pitch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify specific people with real needs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Size of market&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why now?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is your clear competitive advantage - why can no-one else do this?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Market&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find a large and attractive market…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Management&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build a smart, skilled and cohesive team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With a strong ability to deliver quickly and to learn quickly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That is ready to go big whatever it takes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With a unique vision and project-fit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Model&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Valuable and differentiated products&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Efficient go-to-market and growth channels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Profitable monetisation strategy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scalability and defensibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Momentum&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show traction and that you’ve cracked the important problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show ambitous and credible growth plans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With a capital-efficient growth model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And a clear strategy to scale and win&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Entrepreneurship"/><category term="LIS"/><category term="FinTech"/><category term="Startup"/><category term="Founder"/></entry><entry><title>How to be an ambitious founder in Europe</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/ambitious.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-06-09T21:55:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-06-09T21:55:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-06-09:/ambitious.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Creating something that matters is hard. Learn to leverage your time, you can never get it back. Being a successful founder is not impossible, it is always&amp;nbsp;exciting.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Whilst at the &lt;a href="http://www.lis-summit.com/"&gt;Lisbon Investment Summit&lt;/a&gt; I went to a session called “What it means to be ambitious for founders in Europe” by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/daedalium?lang=en"&gt;Oussama Ammar&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve written generally about the summit &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/lis17.html"&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oussama spoke with passion and humour. It’s clear that he cares about encouraging would-be founders and confronting some of the cultural hurdles that exist in Europe. These are my notes from the session:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are serious about building something that matters then you have a great and exciting future ahead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can never predict who will be successful and who will fail. There are a lot of dumb successful people and clever founders can fail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s really important to learn how to leverage your time effectively. You can lose anything else and get it back but you can never recover the time you’ve already spent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The only way to succeed is to try hard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s hard to do something that matters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Europe you need to be more ambitious than average (measured against other countries) because the environment makes it harder to be an entrepreneur. (Attitudes to risk, comfort, security, expectations of failure.. are all unhelpful for founders.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s not impossible, just harder. So be more ambitious.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everyone is replaceable, no-one is unique.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can always lose money and replace it. There is so much money in the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take a look at Crunchbase and see the failure rate for companies that raised $1m - $10m, it is the same rate for those that raised $10m+.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you lose money on a project you will learn things from that experience and you can leverage that learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;… But you will never get back the time you spent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zombies are companies that make enough money to survive but not enough to provide joy to the people in the company - aim high and…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starting a company is a big deal, like starting a marriage. Think hard about what you will be doing, what problem you are trying to solve, who you will be working with. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Europe there is not enough money to go around and this makes pitching hard. Silicon Valley doesn’t have this problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On average a startup in Europe will raise less than a startup in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USA&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Europe is irrationally concerned about risk. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USA&lt;/span&gt; is less concerned with risk and this is very helpful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So be pragmatic about risk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Incorporate in London where the laws are good, even if you don’t want to operate in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt;. It has a better designed system of corporate law. Estonia is also good. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="best-european-city-for-founders"&gt;Best European city for founders&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;London, Paris, Berlin..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There isn’t a best city because none are holistic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;London has the money&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paris has engineering and product development (and no-one outside Paris knows the products exist)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Berlin has automation and execution, execution and scaling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…You need to draw on all 3 of these cities, which when taken together can surpass Silicon Valley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="anecdotes"&gt;Anecdotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The founder of Slack lives in Vancouver with his wife and kids. He spends 1 day each week in California and everyone thinks Slack is Californian due to good marketing. Forget national pride, be pragmatic. Leverage the internet. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The founders of Airbnb would fly from New York to California for 1 day each week. They were originally in California where AirBnB started, but decided that if they could make it work in New York then AirBnB would be a success, so they moved to New York and flew back for meetings , etc. If you ask Europeans to come to a meeting in London (which is not as far as California is from New York) people start complaining and deciding they can’t be bothered. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Entrepreneurship"/><category term="LIS"/><category term="Startup"/><category term="FinTech"/><category term="Europe"/></entry><entry><title>The Lisbon Investment Summit</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/lis17.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-06-09T17:53:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-06-09T17:53:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-06-09:/lis17.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Lisbon investment Summit was full of Investors as well as Founders. The sessions were good enough but the real value was in the&amp;nbsp;conversations.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I attended the &lt;a href="http://www.lis-summit.com/"&gt;Lisbon Investment Summit&lt;/a&gt; on June 6 and 7 as part of the &lt;a href="http://www.oula.la"&gt;Oula.la&lt;/a&gt; InsurTech startup team with &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jd_sullivan?lang=en-gb"&gt;John Sullivan&lt;/a&gt;. It was the first startup conference I’d been to and I arrived hoping to have some useful conversations and understand more about the Fintech and startup spaces in Europe. As usual I wanted to focus on tech, finance and blockchains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="who-was-there"&gt;Who was there&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As well as some outstanding sessions there was a high ratio of investors to startups. This made talking to VCs, bankers and M&amp;amp;A lawyers really easy. I was happy to meet a London-based and Fintech-focussed &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VC&lt;/span&gt; when I sat down to have lunch, and thanks to interrupting a session to ask blockchain related questions on Day 1, a banker struck up a conversation with me over breakfast the next day. I met a lot of people across many relevant roles, and once I’ve worked through my notes and my new collection of business cards I hope to have some great follow-up meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="useful-sessions"&gt;Useful Sessions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most useful sessions for me were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/ambitious.html"&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;What it means to be ambitious for founders in Europe”&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/daedalium?lang=en"&gt;Oussama Ammar&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="https://www.thefamily.co"&gt;TheFamily&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/investment.html"&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Understanding Investment”&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Boris_Golden"&gt;Boris Golden&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="https://www.partechventures.com"&gt;Partech Ventures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Building successful businesses on blockchain technologies” a panel discussion moderated by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/kloaec?lang=en"&gt;Kevin Loaec&lt;/a&gt;, founder of the &lt;a href="http://chainsmiths.com/"&gt;Chainsmiths&lt;/a&gt; blockchain consultancy, and including &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mir_btc"&gt;Mir Serena Liponi&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="http://www.blockchainlab.it/"&gt;Blockchain Lab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blockchain session was valuable because it’s unusual to meet people who have been working in the blockchain space for several years. I’m always wary of being distracted by the hype and noise around developments in the blockchain space so I appreciated hearing some informed and level-headed opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="political-support"&gt;Political Support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opening session included a speech from the Mayor of Lisbon and the next day opened with a speech from the Secretary of Industry. Both speeches conveyed an open and progressive attitude to international cooperation aimed at promoting and supporting founders and startups in Portugal. The warm words were supported by practical measures including tax incentives and a state-backed scheme to match amounts contributed by private investors. It was really refreshing to hear a politician extol the virtues of multinational cooperation and bringing different cultures into Portugal. I wish Britain could do this too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the topic of Brexit, which inevitably arose due to London’s present role as a centre of finance and innovation, it seems Europe is still expecting the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; to come to its senses, and cannot understand why it’s destroying its goodwill and reputation so thoroughly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="overall"&gt;Overall&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two days in Lisbon were full of useful and energetic conversations and it was a great experience pitching &lt;a href="http://www.oula.la"&gt;Oula.la&lt;/a&gt; multiple times and talking about what we’re trying to do and how blockchains are a part of that. The opportunities to meet founders and investors are invaluable for making informed decisions. Lisbon is a beautiful city which I found easy to get around and always felt safe in. It’s also refreshingly &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/london.html"&gt;affordable!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Panoramic street" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/lis4.JPG"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="Google talks" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/lis3.JPG"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="Statue" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/lis1.JPG"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Entrepreneurship"/><category term="FinTech"/><category term="Startup"/><category term="Europe"/><category term="LIS"/></entry><entry><title>London Rent vs. London Salaries</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/london.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-05-12T22:55:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-05-12T22:55:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-05-12:/london.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Living in London is only financially possible if you are either single or household income is more than&amp;nbsp;£60k/year.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Living in London is expensive, everyone in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; knows this. Everyone knows that this is mostly due to the price of property, which we all enjoy talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve lived here for 3 years now, and when my wife and I were both working we lived comfortably. Two incomes under one roof is just fine. Not as fine as in many other cities, but reasonable. Just over a year ago my first child was born, and now that my wife’s maternity pay has ended we are a single income household. This is not fine. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though I earn almost £50k/year, and any salary increase will be taxed at 40%, I cannot cover essential day-to-day costs. I’m in the 40% tax bracket, and my basic monthly outgoings exceed my monthly take home pay by £400. If my employer wanted to pay me enough to cover essential costs, it would cost them approximately double the shortfall due to tax. None of this makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salaries and living expenses have become really disconnected. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most people the most obvious way to increase wealth is to buy property. Mortgage repayments are cheaper than rent, and the value of the property increases over time. Double win. But there is a big hurdle to overcome before this is possible - saving money for a deposit on a house is often impossible without external help (i.e. the “Bank of Mum and Dad”), because so much of the money earnt must be spent on rent first. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a trap. Repayments on a mortgage are cheaper than paying rent, but you cannot save enough for a deposit because;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;so much of your salary goes to paying rent&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the average cost of a &lt;em&gt;flat&lt;/em&gt; in London is 500k&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, which means a 5% deposit is £25k — which is a higher deposit than you would need anywhere else in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt;, despite being the place you are least able to accumulate it. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if my partner went back to work and we put our baby in childcare? Childcare is not cheap, and working would need to bring in more than the cost of childcare. This requires a higher than average salary from a graduate job, (which is the life stage when people might reasonably start having children), so unless both parents are unusually high earners that option isnt viable either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Living in London is only financially possible if you are either single or household income is more than £60k/year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’d be lucky to find a 1 bedroom flat for less than £1000/month &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href="http://www.rightmove.co.uk/house-prices/London.html"&gt;Rightmove&lt;/a&gt;, an estate agent with some useful price statistics. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="London"/><category term="Rent"/></entry><entry><title>Spare time</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/spare-time.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2016-08-13T21:15:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-08-13T21:15:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2016-08-13:/spare-time.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a list of interests I want to consider pursuing. I wrote it when I began to study for my last set of exams and my mind filled with things I’d rather be doing instead. Some of these interests are just me reacting to having no spare time for a few months, but others are decent goals and projects. Temporarily losing my spare time made me value it more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="free-time" src="/images/spare_time.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote this post so that I could compare what I thought was important when I was busy to when I wasn’t. Writing the list allowed me to move on without forgetting. Here’s a break down of each item:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Run 10k in 50 minutes” - This is easier than I imagined. When I wrote the
     list I could barely run 2k without stopping, but intended to go for a
     weekly run whilst studying. I’ve struggled to stay energetic and healthy
     during previous exam phases, so now I have a rule that I must do some mild
     exercise even if I think I can’t spare the time. I find running really
     lowers my stress levels, and increasing my heart rate and working up a
     sweat lets me sleep better and concentrate for longer. After a few weeks of
     minimal running, I could run 5k easily. If I kept at it, 10k in 50 mins
     would be easy. But point 2…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Be Insanity strong” - As in, do the Insanity workout programme. Again. I thought about it and decided to do P90x instead. Week 1 is going great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Read the bible habitually” - When I was 17 I found out about Jesus and
    became a Christian. In the months and years after that I’d regularly read my
    bible almost every day and pray a lot. I wanted to understand, so I set a
    goal of 5 chapters each day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read through the new testament repeatedly and read most of the old
testament during this time. I knew the scriptures well enough that a lot of
sermons became boring and obvious - I’d already studied the bible passage
being used. During this time I remember being aware that the way I thought
was different to how it would have been otherwise. My perspectives were
long-term and less me focused. I thought about what I was reading instead
of the days’ headlines or social chatter. I remember enjoying the benefits
and thinking that I should keep this habit. The reasons why I think
Christianity is so wonderful are well summarised in &lt;a href="http://messages.destinyedinburgh.com/sermon/the-gospel-we-preach-a-message-for-leaders"&gt;this
sermon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s now 10 years later, and whilst my convictions are strong, my knowledge
of the bible is sadly pretty fuzzy. My thinking is clouded by the
perspectives contained in the media I consume and the conversations I’m
part of. I strongly suspect I would be acting and thinking differently if I
read my bible more, but I don’t know what those differences would be.
Trouble is, it’s often not obvious what the immediate benefits of
reading the bible are, you have to work for it a bit. Praying for help is
effective. The books in the bible were written to last through the ages and
across all cultures, so it’s not surprising that they’re not as easy to
read as something written for an English speaker in a hurry. I should stop
being in a hurry, and stop prioritising only quantifiable goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Think more” - On a similar note to 3, but less supernatural. If I spent
    less time consuming content and a little more looking around me or walking,
    I reckon I’d be more self-aware and make better decisions. This would
    probably lead to a happier, more satisfying life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Pray more” - I don’t know why, but the creator of the universe wants me to
    talk and share my life with him. He cares about me. This makes no sense to
    me, at all. If I was God, I would not go out of my way to consider the views
    and concerns of a very flawed human. But when I pray, my prayers are very
    often answered. I should ask him about this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Amazon seller?” - Amazon have this “Fulfilled by Amazon” service,
     which means you don’t even need to hold the stock you want to sell.
     If I choose the right products, import them cheaply from China and
     reselling  them on Amazon at a profit, I end up quids in for minimal
     effort and manageable risk. Sounds intriguing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Blog about interesting data” - Here I am, blogging. I should stick
    to the main topic and get technical. I was inspired by this
    &lt;a href="http://www.curiousgnu.com/"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Finish Coursera” - The data science specialization is great! It’s in R, and I want to focus on Python, but I’d still like to do it. I need to consider the opportunity cost of the time committed, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Read for fun, history, fiction” - When I started my job, in April 2014, I
    was half way through &lt;a href="https://read.amazon.co.uk/kp/embed?asin=B00796LLLK&amp;amp;asin=B00796LLLK&amp;amp;preview=newtab&amp;amp;linkCode=kpe&amp;amp;ref_=cm_sw_r_kb_dp_GP2Rxb3Q8MYC4"&gt;Savage
    Continent&lt;/a&gt;,
    which is an eye-opening and eye-watering history of Europe in the years
    after World War 2. I see Europe through different eyes because of it.
    However I only got half way though, and since April ‘14 I never felt I had
    the free time or energy to pick it back up. This should change. When I was a
    researcher, and when I was a student, I had so much more opportunity to
    develop my own pursuits. Since entering the corporate world, I find myself
    fighting a war of attrition to exert my personality onto my lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read for fiction… I’m unconvinced. What do you have at the end of
it? What can you do with it? Maybe I’ve just been reading the wrong authors,
but I’m going to leave this for now. Sure, you could gain an appreciation of
a different time or place, but that appreciation comes via the fictional
characters and events, its secondary. What about abstract constructs,
perspectives, morals… things that history books are ill-suited for? Great
fiction would be essential for exploring these. But for now, I’ll prioritise
point 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" class="my-5" frameborder="0" height="550" src="https://read.amazon.co.uk/kp/card?asin=B00796LLLK&amp;amp;asin=B00796LLLK&amp;amp;preview=inline&amp;amp;linkCode=kpe&amp;amp;ref_=cm_sw_r_kb_dp_GP2Rxb3Q8MYC4" style="max-width: 100%; float:middle" width="336"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Do a photography project” - This I would love to do, but probably won’t.
     It would be a luxury, and the opportunity cost would be too great right
     now. I’d like to shoot a series of black and white portraits, and turn them
     into large prints. I think good portrait photography is uniquely impactful
     and moving, choosing B&amp;amp;W removes distractions and leaves a subjects
     humanity more exposed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Have a list of business/product ideas” - There’s no excuse for this
     one, anyone can have several good ideas. It’s turning them into
     reality that takes skill. Need to have the ideas first, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Do a law &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MOOC&lt;/span&gt;” - i.e Study particular areas of law, in my own time
     and at my own pace. I studied a tiny bit of law during the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACA&lt;/span&gt;, and
     realised employment law or contract law could be really useful.
     (Same for the tax system - another surprise). We only had a brief
     introduction though, so if I could find the time I’d like to know more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Do an InfoSec or Network Security &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MOOC&lt;/span&gt;” - Its super interesting,
     but not likely to be a good use of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Learn to fight - Krav Maga / &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MMA&lt;/span&gt;” - Ever since watching The Bourne
     Identity I’ve wanted to learn Krav Maga, and &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/LybrzdG96_8"&gt;Georges
     St-Pierre&lt;/a&gt; made me want to train
     for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MMA&lt;/span&gt;. For now though, I’ll do P90x. I can reconsider in 90 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class="relative" style="padding-top: 56.25%"&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen="" class="absolute inset-0 w-full h-full" frameborder="0" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/u0_8dzaNxhg"&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Get out of London” - My contract ends in April 2017, next summer
     will be a crossroads. I hate the commute, I hate being constantly
     rushed. Living in other cities has been a lot more pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/><category term="Habits"/><category term="Advice"/><category term="Reflection"/></entry><entry><title>How to wake up early</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/how-to-wake-up-early.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2016-08-06T22:04:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-08-06T22:04:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2016-08-06:/how-to-wake-up-early.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For years I’ve wished that I could wake up early and use the quiet
pre-breakfast hours for distraction-free productivity. And for years I
have spectacularly failed at this. I love the quiet, distraction-free
hours at the end of the day too, as well as waking up slowly.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many famous leaders and politicians are known to start their days early,
and I would like to be able to do this too. After years of trying and
failing, I have had a break-through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The secret of waking up early is this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Become a parent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the first couple of months with a new-born:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will be well-practiced at quickly waking up at previously
    unthinkable times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will be used to operating on less sleep than you ever thought possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your beautiful child will become a reliable alarm clock, waking you
    up at the crack of dawn with cute smiles and increasingly insistent
    demands that you get up, play and make breakfast.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have the freedom to begin sleeping and working when you want, I still believe this is a great option. I bashed out a PhD in 3.5 years during which I usually woke up late and began to work around lunch time! - Glorious autonomy! &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="Productivity"/><category term="Sleep"/></entry></feed>