<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>blog - positioning</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="feeds/positioning.tag.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2020-12-03T15:46:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Obviously Awesome</title><link href="obviously-awesome.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-03T15:46:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-03T15:46:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-12-03:obviously-awesome.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My notes on &amp;#8220;Obviously Awesome&amp;#8221; by April&amp;nbsp;Dunford&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Intro&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In order to do better marketing, understand your value and differentiators&amp;nbsp;better&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand what makes a best-fit&amp;nbsp;customer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positioning is a fundamental input to every business tactic you&amp;nbsp;use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you fail at positioning, you fail at marketing and&amp;nbsp;sales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positioning is &amp;#8220;conext setting&amp;#8221; for&amp;nbsp;products&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customers need to be able to easily understand&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What your product&amp;nbsp;does&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why it is&amp;nbsp;special&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why it matters to&amp;nbsp;them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your prospects can&amp;#8217;t figure out what your product does quickly, they will invent a position for you. It might hide your key strengths or misunderstand your&amp;nbsp;value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find people to demo your product to, then ask them to describe it back to you. Do the same with existing customers. If they&amp;#8217;re not saying the same thing then you have a positioning&amp;nbsp;problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Products with strong positioning:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find the best kind of&amp;nbsp;customer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the value&amp;nbsp;obvious&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sell&amp;nbsp;quickly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Part&amp;nbsp;1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Positioning as&amp;nbsp;context&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Without positioning to guide us, we don&amp;#8217;t know how to understnad a&amp;nbsp;product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positioning lets us make assumptions about&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who a product is&amp;nbsp;for&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what its main features&amp;nbsp;are&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how much it&amp;nbsp;costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Without it we would be paralyzed by choice, and we wouldnt be able to make sense of all the products around&amp;nbsp;us. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The context and purpose of a product from the founders/engineers perspective are often different to those of the&amp;nbsp;prospect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prodcuts can be positioned in multiple ways, and often the best positioning is not the default&amp;nbsp;positioning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bad positioning makes it harder for prospects to figure out if your product is worth thinking&amp;nbsp;about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positioning requires considering:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customers point of view - what problem/pain does it&amp;nbsp;solve&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ways your product is uniquely&amp;nbsp;different&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The characteristics of a potential&amp;nbsp;customer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The best market context to make your value uniquely&amp;nbsp;obvious&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Five (plus one) components of effective&amp;nbsp;positioning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Competitive Alternatives - if you didnt exist, what would your customers use instead?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Its what your prospects would use to do the task if your product didnt exist. It could be excel, or pen and paper. It could be nothing, (in which case maybe you product doesnt solve a real pain&amp;nbsp;point.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You probably know a lot more about your market, and problem, and alternative solutions, than your prospects do. (&amp;#8220;Doing nothing&amp;#8221; could be an opportunity, not a red&amp;nbsp;flag.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Its important to understand what customers will compare your product with, because this is how they will define &amp;#8220;better&amp;#8221;. Is it &amp;#8220;easier&amp;#8221; than a pen and&amp;nbsp;paper?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customers might never have purchased a solution like yours&amp;nbsp;before.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unique Attributes - What do you have that alternative do not?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Could be:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivery Model (online vs offline, installed on-site vs&amp;nbsp;not)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Business model (rental vs&amp;nbsp;purchase)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specific expertise (data scientist with financial and back-end web dev&amp;nbsp;expertise)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Value (and quantifiable objective proof) - What value do the attributes enable for customers?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If unique attributes are your secret sauce, the value is why someone might care about your secret&amp;nbsp;sauce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fact based, provable, demonstrable, quantifiable, objective. 3rd party oppinions are&amp;nbsp;relevant. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Target market characterists - Who cares a lot about that value?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on customers who are most likely to purchase quickly, wont ask for discounts, will tell their friends about&amp;nbsp;you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should clearly identify who these are&amp;nbsp;and &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identidy what sets them apart from other groups of customers. why are they uniquely likely to buy from you when others wouldnt or would take longer to consider and make a&amp;nbsp;purchase&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Market Category - What context makes your value obvious to the ideal customer?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Declaring that your product exists in a certain market triggers a powerful set of&amp;nbsp;assumptions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make these assumptions help you, not hinder&amp;nbsp;you. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When presented with your product, customers will try to use what they already know to figure out what your product is all about and why its special. You want them to be able to do this really quickly and&amp;nbsp;easily. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make these assumptions work for you, not against you. You won&amp;#8217;t have to list every feature, because most of them will be assumed by the context of the market&amp;nbsp;category. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get it right, and sales efforts (copy) wont be wasted battling those assumptions, but can instead build off of them to show secret sauce and value more&amp;nbsp;obviously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Bonus) Relevant Trends - what trends make your product relevant right now?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Used carefully, trends can show prospoects why they should pay attention to your product right now. Increases&amp;nbsp;urgency.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can increase urgency, excitement, coolness,&amp;nbsp;credibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;but the trend must be directly relevant, practically and objectively&amp;nbsp;applicable. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blockchains, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AI&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ML&lt;/span&gt; are trends - they are relevant to multiple&amp;nbsp;markets. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of these components is relevant to the&amp;nbsp;others&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Startups"></category><category term="marketing"></category><category term="positioning"></category><category term="startups"></category><category term="book"></category></entry></feed>