<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>blog - Vim</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="feeds/vim.tag.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2016-12-01T22:32:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Vim!</title><link href="vim.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-01T22:32:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-12-01T22:32:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-12-01:vim.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Vim is a text editor renowned for its efficiency and its use of keyboard shortcuts. It&amp;#8217;s based on the Vi text editor from the 1970&amp;#8217;s. It was first released in 1991 and is still being developed today. It comes pre-installed on Unix systems (including MacOS) and can be …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Vim is a text editor renowned for its efficiency and its use of keyboard shortcuts. It&amp;#8217;s based on the Vi text editor from the 1970&amp;#8217;s. It was first released in 1991 and is still being developed today. It comes pre-installed on Unix systems (including MacOS) and can be run from the&amp;nbsp;terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vim is famous in another way too - for being difficult to learn. I found some good and remarkably creative tools to begin learning its concepts and controls. This was necessary because there is no &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GUI&lt;/span&gt;. There is a &lt;em&gt;game&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="http://vim-adventures.com/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and there is &lt;a href="http://www.openvim.com/"&gt;this interactive tutorial&lt;/a&gt;. There&amp;#8217;s also a built-in vim tutorial - just type &amp;#8216;vimtutor&amp;#8217; into&amp;nbsp;Terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vim is designed so that you don&amp;#8217;t need to take your hands off your keyboard and use a mouse. It has the &amp;#8216;insert&amp;#8217; mode where you enter text as usual, and the &amp;#8216;command&amp;#8217; mode where you can make use of a comprehensive and flexible shortcut language to move around, edit and search the text. With no &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GUI&lt;/span&gt; or toolbar, it&amp;#8217;s a very different approach to text editing than I&amp;#8217;m used&amp;nbsp;to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can run Vim from the terminal, but there are also versions that run as apps. MacVim on MacOS has the option to show a tool bar of simple commands like a normal program, and lets the arrow keys move the cursor in addition to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VIM&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8216;hjkl&amp;#8217; functionality. This makes getting started a little&amp;nbsp;simpler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also a lot of plugins to extend Vim&amp;#8217;s functionality and turn it from a text editor into an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IDE&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;a href="https://realpython.com/blog/python/vim-and-python-a-match-made-in-heaven/"&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt; walks you through setting up Vim as a Python &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IDE&lt;/span&gt; and explains how to manage various&amp;nbsp;add-ons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recommend Daniel Mieslers &lt;a href="https://danielmiessler.com/study/vim/"&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; for a quick overview of how to use&amp;nbsp;Vim.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Tools"></category><category term="Vim"></category></entry></feed>