<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>JohnMathews.eu - Non-technical/Entrepreneurship</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/feeds/non-technical/entrepreneurship.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://johnmathews.eu/</id><updated>2020-10-28T13:37:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Pippip.Email</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/pippip.email.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-28T13:37:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-10-28T13:37:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-10-28:/pippip.email.html</id><summary type="html"></summary><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="pippip"&gt;&lt;a href="https://pippip.email"&gt;PipPip&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6 weeks ago I had an idea for a product whilst reading a news&amp;nbsp;article. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be great if the writing and sending of important messages could be
separated, so that I could write something long before I needed to send it, and
know that then sending would happen at the right time without having to think
about it. This could be useful for sending my daughter a message on her 15th
birthday, or to my wife on our 10th anniversary. I also designed a check-in
mechanism, so that messages could be sent if I disappeared or pass&amp;nbsp;away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://PipPip.email"&gt;PipPip&lt;/a&gt; is the result - event-driven and scheduled email delivery, from days to&amp;nbsp;decades&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re working on validating the idea and finding the right niche&amp;nbsp;audience. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Entrepreneurship"></category><category term="PipPip"></category></entry><entry><title>Bakke-Rij</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/bakkerij.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-06-11T13:09:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-06-11T13:09:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2018-06-11:/bakkerij.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a great example of a creative and innovative coworking&amp;nbsp;space.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently began working in a new coworking space, sharing an office unit with another entrepreneur. What makes this coworking space unique is it&amp;rsquo;s conversion from an industrial bakery to a coworking space. Where the machinery once stood, converted shipping containers with glass walls have become offices for startups and&amp;nbsp;freelancers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The skylights, glass walls and bright colors create a light and airy atmosphere, and the space seems popular with designers and founders working in creative industries. It&amp;rsquo;s an energetic space with a creative feel to&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bakke-Rij" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/bakkerij1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bakke-Rij" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/bakkerij2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Entrepreneurship"></category><category term="coworking"></category><category term="Netherlands"></category><category term="Haarlem"></category></entry><entry><title>Understanding VC Investment</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/investment.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-09T23:03:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-06-09T23:03:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-06-09:/investment.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;How to pitch to a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VC&lt;/span&gt;: Market, Management, Model,&amp;nbsp;Momentum&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I attended the &lt;a href="http://www.lis-summit.com/"&gt;Lisbon Investment Summit&lt;/a&gt; in June and wrote about my experiences &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/lis17.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. One of the best sessions was with &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Boris_Golden"&gt;Boris Golden&lt;/a&gt; called &amp;ldquo;Understand Investment&amp;rdquo;. These are my&amp;nbsp;notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;VC&lt;/span&gt;&amp;rsquo;s are seeking to identify high-potential startups, and then support and fund&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are looking for something that is innovative and&amp;nbsp;unproven.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A startup is not a company but an organisation searching for a business&amp;nbsp;model,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whilst executing and discovering a scalable way to&amp;nbsp;grow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Startups need money for ambitious but credible growth&amp;nbsp;plans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A typical stake for a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VC&lt;/span&gt; could be roughly&amp;nbsp;20%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;VC&lt;/span&gt;&amp;rsquo;s want an exit price of at least 100m, otherwise their business models don&amp;rsquo;t work&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$10m can seem a lot for a founder with a 30% stake, but it&amp;rsquo;s not enough to attract VCs, so aim&amp;nbsp;higher.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-to-pitch"&gt;How to&amp;nbsp;pitch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify specific people with real&amp;nbsp;needs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Size of&amp;nbsp;market&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why&amp;nbsp;now?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is your clear competitive advantage - why can no-one else do&amp;nbsp;this?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="market"&gt;Market&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find a large and attractive&amp;nbsp;market…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="management"&gt;Management&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build a smart, skilled and cohesive&amp;nbsp;team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With a strong ability to deliver quickly and to learn&amp;nbsp;quickly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That is ready to go big whatever it&amp;nbsp;takes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With a unique vision and&amp;nbsp;project-fit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="model"&gt;Model&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Valuable and differentiated&amp;nbsp;products&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Efficient go-to-market and growth&amp;nbsp;channels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Profitable monetisation&amp;nbsp;strategy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scalability and&amp;nbsp;defensibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="momentum"&gt;Momentum&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show traction and that you&amp;rsquo;ve cracked the important&amp;nbsp;problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show ambitous and credible growth&amp;nbsp;plans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With a capital-efficient growth&amp;nbsp;model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And a clear strategy to scale and&amp;nbsp;win&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Entrepreneurship"></category><category term="LIS"></category><category term="FinTech"></category><category term="Startup"></category><category term="Founder"></category></entry><entry><title>How to be an ambitious founder in Europe</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/ambitious.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-09T21:55:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-06-09T21:55:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-06-09:/ambitious.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Creating something that matters is hard. Learn to leverage your time, you can never get it back. Being a successful founder is not impossible, it is always&amp;nbsp;exciting.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Whilst at the &lt;a href="http://www.lis-summit.com/"&gt;Lisbon Investment Summit&lt;/a&gt; I went to a session called &amp;ldquo;What it means to be ambitious for founders in Europe&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/daedalium?lang=en"&gt;Oussama Ammar&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve written generally about the summit &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/lis17.html"&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oussama spoke with passion and humour. It&amp;rsquo;s clear that he cares about encouraging would-be founders and confronting some of the cultural hurdles that exist in Europe. These are my notes from the&amp;nbsp;session:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are serious about building something that matters then you have a great and exciting future&amp;nbsp;ahead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can never predict who will be successful and who will fail. There are a lot of dumb successful people and clever founders can&amp;nbsp;fail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s really important to learn how to leverage your time effectively. You can lose anything else and get it back but you can never recover the time you&amp;rsquo;ve already&amp;nbsp;spent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The only way to succeed is to try&amp;nbsp;hard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s hard to do something that&amp;nbsp;matters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Europe you need to be more ambitious than average (measured against other countries) because the environment makes it harder to be an entrepreneur. (Attitudes to risk, comfort, security, expectations of failure.. are all unhelpful for&amp;nbsp;founders.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not impossible, just harder. So be more&amp;nbsp;ambitious.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everyone is replaceable, no-one is&amp;nbsp;unique.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can always lose money and replace it. There is so much money in the&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take a look at Crunchbase and see the failure rate for companies that raised $1m - $10m, it is the same rate for those that raised&amp;nbsp;$10m+.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you lose money on a project you will learn things from that experience and you can leverage that&amp;nbsp;learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;… But you will never get back the time you&amp;nbsp;spent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zombies are companies that make enough money to survive but not enough to provide joy to the people in the company - aim high&amp;nbsp;and…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starting a company is a big deal, like starting a marriage. Think hard about what you will be doing, what problem you are trying to solve, who you will be working&amp;nbsp;with. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Europe there is not enough money to go around and this makes pitching hard. Silicon Valley doesn&amp;rsquo;t have this&amp;nbsp;problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On average a startup in Europe will raise less than a startup in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USA&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Europe is irrationally concerned about risk. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USA&lt;/span&gt; is less concerned with risk and this is very&amp;nbsp;helpful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So be pragmatic about&amp;nbsp;risk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Incorporate in London where the laws are good, even if you don&amp;rsquo;t want to operate in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt;. It has a better designed system of corporate law. Estonia is also&amp;nbsp;good. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="best-european-city-for-founders"&gt;Best European city for&amp;nbsp;founders&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;London, Paris,&amp;nbsp;Berlin..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There isn&amp;rsquo;t a best city because none are&amp;nbsp;holistic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;London has the&amp;nbsp;money&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paris has engineering and product development (and no-one outside Paris knows the products&amp;nbsp;exist)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Berlin has automation and execution, execution and&amp;nbsp;scaling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…You need to draw on all 3 of these cities, which when taken together can surpass Silicon&amp;nbsp;Valley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="anecdotes"&gt;Anecdotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The founder of Slack lives in Vancouver with his wife and kids. He spends 1 day each week in California and everyone thinks Slack is Californian due to good marketing. Forget national pride, be pragmatic. Leverage the&amp;nbsp;internet. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The founders of Airbnb would fly from New York to California for 1 day each week. They were originally in California where AirBnB started, but decided that if they could make it work in New York then AirBnB would be a success, so they moved to New York and flew back for meetings , etc. If you ask Europeans to come to a meeting in London (which is not as far as California is from New York) people start complaining and deciding they can&amp;rsquo;t be&amp;nbsp;bothered. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Entrepreneurship"></category><category term="LIS"></category><category term="Startup"></category><category term="FinTech"></category><category term="Europe"></category></entry><entry><title>The Lisbon Investment Summit</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/lis17.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-09T17:53:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-06-09T17:53:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-06-09:/lis17.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Lisbon investment Summit was full of Investors as well as Founders. The sessions were good enough but the real value was in the&amp;nbsp;conversations.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I attended the &lt;a href="http://www.lis-summit.com/"&gt;Lisbon Investment Summit&lt;/a&gt; on June 6 and 7 as part of the &lt;a href="http://www.oula.la"&gt;Oula.la&lt;/a&gt; InsurTech startup team with &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jd_sullivan?lang=en-gb"&gt;John Sullivan&lt;/a&gt;. It was the first startup conference I&amp;rsquo;d been to and I arrived hoping to have some useful conversations and understand more about the Fintech and startup spaces in Europe. As usual I wanted to focus on tech, finance and&amp;nbsp;blockchains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="who-was-there"&gt;Who was&amp;nbsp;there&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As well as some outstanding sessions there was a high ratio of investors to startups. This made talking to VCs, bankers and M&amp;amp;A lawyers really easy. I was happy to meet a London-based and Fintech-focussed &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VC&lt;/span&gt; when I sat down to have lunch, and thanks to interrupting a session to ask blockchain related questions on Day 1, a banker struck up a conversation with me over breakfast the next day. I met a lot of people across many relevant roles, and once I&amp;rsquo;ve worked through my notes and my new collection of business cards I hope to have some great follow-up&amp;nbsp;meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="useful-sessions"&gt;Useful&amp;nbsp;Sessions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most useful sessions for me&amp;nbsp;were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/ambitious.html"&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/span&gt;What it means to be ambitious for founders in Europe&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/daedalium?lang=en"&gt;Oussama Ammar&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="https://www.thefamily.co"&gt;TheFamily&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/investment.html"&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/span&gt;Understanding Investment&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Boris_Golden"&gt;Boris Golden&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="https://www.partechventures.com"&gt;Partech&amp;nbsp;Ventures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/span&gt;Building successful businesses on blockchain technologies&amp;rdquo; a panel discussion moderated by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/kloaec?lang=en"&gt;Kevin Loaec&lt;/a&gt;, founder of the &lt;a href="http://chainsmiths.com/"&gt;Chainsmiths&lt;/a&gt; blockchain consultancy, and including &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mir_btc"&gt;Mir Serena Liponi&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="http://www.blockchainlab.it/"&gt;Blockchain&amp;nbsp;Lab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blockchain session was valuable because it&amp;rsquo;s unusual to meet people who have been working in the blockchain space for several years. I&amp;rsquo;m always wary of being distracted by the hype and noise around developments in the blockchain space so I appreciated hearing some informed and level-headed&amp;nbsp;opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="political-support"&gt;Political&amp;nbsp;Support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opening session included a speech from the Mayor of Lisbon and the next day opened with a speech from the Secretary of Industry. Both speeches conveyed an open and progressive attitude to international cooperation aimed at promoting and supporting founders and startups in Portugal. The warm words were supported by practical measures including tax incentives and a state-backed scheme to match amounts contributed by private investors. It was really refreshing to hear a politician extol the virtues of multinational cooperation and bringing different cultures into Portugal. I wish Britain could do this&amp;nbsp;too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the topic of Brexit, which inevitably arose due to London&amp;rsquo;s present role as a centre of finance and innovation, it seems Europe is still expecting the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; to come to its senses, and cannot understand why it&amp;rsquo;s destroying its goodwill and reputation so&amp;nbsp;thoroughly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="overall"&gt;Overall&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two days in Lisbon were full of useful and energetic conversations and it was a great experience pitching &lt;a href="http://www.oula.la"&gt;Oula.la&lt;/a&gt; multiple times and talking about what we&amp;rsquo;re trying to do and how blockchains are a part of that. The opportunities to meet founders and investors are invaluable for making informed decisions. Lisbon is a beautiful city which I found easy to get around and always felt safe in. It&amp;rsquo;s also refreshingly &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/london.html"&gt;affordable!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Panoramic street" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/lis4.JPG"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Google talks" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/lis3.JPG"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Statue" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/lis1.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Entrepreneurship"></category><category term="FinTech"></category><category term="Startup"></category><category term="Europe"></category><category term="LIS"></category></entry></feed>