<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>John Mathews Blog - JohnMathews.eu - Non-technical/Family</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/feeds/non-technical/family.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://johnmathews.eu/</id><updated>2021-04-05T11:54:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Over-Engineering this blog</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/over-engineering-this-blog.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-04-05T11:54:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-04-05T11:54:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-04-05:/over-engineering-this-blog.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the last few weeks I’ve spent an unreasonable amount of time and energy
making unnecessary improvements to this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of these improvements are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding keyboard shortcuts (type &lt;code&gt;?&lt;/code&gt; to find out which)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/Adding-search.html"&gt;Implementing&lt;/a&gt;, then
   &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/fuse-search.html"&gt;reimplementing&lt;/a&gt;, and then optimizing client side fuzzy search&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using &lt;code&gt;src-set&lt;/code&gt;s to serve responsive images
   (&lt;a href="https://github.com/pelican-plugins/image-process"&gt;Image-Process&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lazy loading images to make this site load faster.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compressing page files using &lt;code&gt;brotli&lt;/code&gt; and also &lt;code&gt;gzip&lt;/code&gt;.
   (&lt;a href="https://github.com/kurtmckee/pelican_precompress"&gt;Precompress&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trying (and ultimately failing) to avoid a “white flash” when dark mode is
   chosen and a new page loads.
   (&lt;a href="https://github.com/tailwindlabs/tailwindcss/discussions/3904"&gt;Github discussion&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not really sure why I did it. It makes almost no difference to anyone but
me. It felt a bit compulsive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like tinkering, and it’s nice to build something that will continue to work
with no maintenance. I tell myself that over the next few years I will gain the
benefits of these features even when I’ve forgotten I implemented them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s taught me a lot of JavaScript, which is a great language to be familiar
with - it’s everywhere. I would warmly encourage someone younger than myself to
pursue interests for the sake of curiosity and fun. And there is a very high chance that even if no-one uses
the shortcuts except me, my new javascript skills will come in useful somewhere else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even if they do I’m not sure its a good enough reason - things should be
built when they solve a present problem, not over-engineered for what-ifs and
maybes. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/You_aren%27t_gonna_need_it"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;YAGNI&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I wouldn’t let myself do this in a professional capacity. There
is a tension between being curious and being focussed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not really sure that I need to justify myself. Its a hobby, I wanted to do it, I
enjoy tinkering with web technologies and learning new things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But also, I lost sleep over this - I stayed up too late, and let it put
pressure on other things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that being curious, and making room to play with interesting
things, has been one of the most useful approaches to personal development
and up-skilling myself. But there must be a limit..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a tension between wasting my time and taking a risk, and it will take a few
years before I know for sure if these efforts were worthwhile, or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it’s not fun, don’t do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Successful business owners seem to be very good at leaving things alone once
they’re “good enough”, and not being perfectionists. In fact, I think that
being a perfectionist is antithetical to being an entrepreneur. I am not a
perfectionist, I’m just really curious and have a big appetite for learning. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this “appetite for learning” stops me from focussing. I let myself
become distracted by adding new features to this blog, when instead I should
zoom out a bit and think about working towards a more substantial and
meaningful goal, to the exclusion of more minor goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that good entrepreneurs are very focussed, to a fault. I am not
that focussed. I am too distracted by life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a balancing act, there is a tension between being emotionally and
physically present with my family and friends, and ignoring as many things as
possible so that I can focus on doing something meaningful that is necessarily hard.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Technical/Web"/><category term="blog"/><category term="javascript"/><category term="self-reflection"/></entry><entry><title>Regrets Of The Dying</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/regrets-of-the-dying.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-02-01T22:52:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-02-01T22:52:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-02-01:/regrets-of-the-dying.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wish that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’d had the courage to live a life true to myself, not the life others expected of me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I hadn’t worked so hard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’d had the courage to express my feelings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I had stayed in touch with my friends.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’d let myself be happier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…the five most common regrets of terminally ill patients, as described by a
palliative care nurse&lt;sup id="sf-regrets-of-the-dying-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-regrets-of-the-dying-1" title="Source"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-regrets-of-the-dying-1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://bronnieware.com/blog/regrets-of-the-dying/"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-regrets-of-the-dying-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"/></entry><entry><title>A List Of Unconnected Thoughts And Aphorisms</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-02-01T22:27:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-02-01T22:27:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-02-01:/a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do the people you care about love you back? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It does not matter how slowly you go as long as you do not stop. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assume that nobody is going to help you, and nobody is going to stop you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Money is (just) fuel. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets talk about the end. My current self, existing now, is to be seen in
    the context of my end, and my beginning. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you want money, ask for advice. When you want advice, ask for money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You follow the rules of war for you, not your enemy. You fight by rules to
   keep your
   humanity.&lt;sup id="sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-1" title="source"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to be a top performer in any field you must become abnormal.
   Normal is average, which by definition, is far below the top! “We can always
   be average and do what’s normal. I’m not in this to do what’s normal.”
   –Kobe Bryant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Becoming Abnormally Good&lt;sup id="sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-2-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-2" title="source"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; at something:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No reasonable excuses - don’t make (reasonable) excuses that let you off the hook. You need the negative emotions that leads to inspired decision making.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not Worrying About What You Can’t Control &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know it’s best to be genuinely friendly no matter who you’re trying to
    get information out of, thanks in part to the work of Hanns Scharff and a
    slew of studies on interrogation
    techniques&lt;sup id="sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-3-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-3" title="source"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.globalo.com/history-wwii-charlie-brown-franz-stigler-incident/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-2"&gt;&lt;a href="https://capitalandgrowth.org/answers/Article/3217401/Become-Abnormal"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-2-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-3"&gt;&lt;a href="https://psmag.com/social-justice/nazi-interrogator-revealed-value-kindness-84747"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-3-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"/></entry><entry><title>Questions For Interesting Conversations</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/questions.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-02-01T22:05:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-02-01T22:05:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-02-01:/questions.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s the &lt;strong&gt;best piece of advice&lt;/strong&gt; you ever received?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What would you say to your &lt;strong&gt;18-year-old self&lt;/strong&gt; if you had a chat with them today?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever &lt;strong&gt;lost or rejected a friend&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tell me about &lt;strong&gt;a time when you changed your mind&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What have you been &lt;strong&gt;thinking about lately&lt;/strong&gt;? What’s on your mind?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you work in a language that’s not your mother tongue? &lt;strong&gt;What’s it like to live in translation&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is a &lt;strong&gt;choice between remembering and forgetting&lt;/strong&gt;, do you lean towards the side of forgetting?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Were you raised for &lt;strong&gt;autonomy or loyalty&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was there ever a moment where you thought, &lt;strong&gt;‘I’m giving up’&lt;/strong&gt; — what did you do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Was your identity given to you or chosen by you&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"/></entry><entry><title>Mental Models I Used To Use</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/mental-models-i-used-to-use.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-20T16:48:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T16:48:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-20:/mental-models-i-used-to-use.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The rules&lt;sup id="sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-1" title="or policies"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and mental models that helped me
succeed in one season or phase of life may not be the best for the next phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a list of a few mental models I remember being concious of in previous
years. Probably I’ve already forgotten some.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Always ask “why…”&lt;/em&gt;. Be obsessive about this. It’s going to make things
    harder for a while before things get easier. You’ll find difficult answers
    that you otherwise wouldn’t. If you’re only concerned with the present then
    its true that ignorance is bliss, but otherwise it’s a liability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;What if…”&lt;/em&gt; is another good question to ask a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adapt&lt;/em&gt; to the situation, don’t make it adapt to you if you have any
    choice. Be kind of like water, going around things and through the gaps.
    Look for the edges and the gaps, the parts that aren’t well known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Let people talk&lt;/em&gt; as much as they want to. Shut up and listen. If they
    mean you harm or don’t respect you then it’ll become more obvious the more
    they keep talking. If they mean you well or they’re saying something
    useful, you will benefit more from letting them talk more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inversion&lt;/em&gt; - it can be hard to know if you should do something, but how
    would you feel if you didn’t do it, or if it didn’t happen?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Regrets are inevitable&lt;/em&gt;, everyone has them. Same as making mistakes. Let
    your regrets be for things that you did do, and not what you didn’t do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are willing to try something, fail at it, and still be glad that you
    tried, then you should almost definitely do it. Commit to it and enjoy the
    experience! Don’t be scared, or at least, be scared &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; optimistic and
    happy&lt;sup id="sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-2-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-2" title="Courage isn’t the absence of fear. It’s being scared and doing     the right thing anyway."&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is beauty and luxury in being in such a bad spot that you are backed
    into a corner with seemingly no way out. Things become black and white,
    instead of shades of gray, and that will make priorities and options much
    clearer. You are likely to work very efficiently and effectively in this
    scenario, and you will learn important things about yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I’m older and I have responsibilities, I can’t ever let things
become so bad that a situation becomes black and white. I have to
navigate a world of grays. If they do become black and white, I’ll
already have a long list of failings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was younger, things were more fragile. My resources were smaller and
things could quickly flip from good to bad. Enjoy the few benefits that a
situation like that gives, because (hopefully) once its gone its gone for good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to solve a problem is to prevent it from occurring in the first
    place. Succeeding at this will bring its own challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take responsibility for things you are not responsible for, kind of. Do it
    deliberately and for your own benefit, but don’t forget that you are only
    pretending that it’s your responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do this, you will force yourself to understand a situation more
deeply and from other peoples perspectives. This will let you learn faster
and help you in future. Keep this at arms length though - it’s make-believe
and you need to be able to switch it on and off. It’s a toy for you to play
with. This seems to be what “extreme responsibility” is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think its important to have mental models that you’re comfortable with,
because it lets you make decisions quickly and consistently. But understand
that &lt;a href="https://fs.blog/2015/11/map-and-territory/"&gt;the map is not the
territory&lt;/a&gt;, and these are just
tools in a toolbox.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-1"&gt;or policies &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-2"&gt;Courage isn’t the absence of fear. It’s being scared and doing
    the right thing anyway. &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-2-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"/></entry><entry><title>What I’m reading</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/reading.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2018-06-04T15:52:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-06-04T15:52:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2018-06-04:/reading.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A list of interesting things. June&amp;nbsp;2018&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="articles"&gt;Articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fs.blog/mental-models/"&gt;Mental models&lt;/a&gt; A comprehensive list organised around different disciplines. It a long read but probably one of the most easy to apply and tangibly useful articles I’ve read recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/vb.html"&gt;Life is short&lt;/a&gt; - Is life actually short, or would we always want more time, no matter how much we could have?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.eugenewei.com/blog/2018/5/21/invisible-asymptotes"&gt;Invisible asymptotes&lt;/a&gt; - A well written and long look at various facets of business strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://osam.com/Commentary/factors-from-scratch"&gt;Factors from scratch&lt;/a&gt; - Investing: A unified framework to explain how factors work. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://kottke.org/18/06/a-sad-update-about-a-scissors-maker-that-went-viral"&gt;This is tragic&lt;/a&gt; - “…But I do think this highlights the potential disconnects between mental health &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; business, publicity &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; success, and success &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; happiness. The internet can seem so intimate but ultimately it’s a thin view of an individual’s or company’s reality.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://statico.github.io/vim3.html"&gt;Vim&lt;/a&gt; after 15 years&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2018/03/27/a-complete-guide-to-cyprocurrency-regulations-around-the-world.html?__source=sharebar%7Clinkedin&amp;amp;par=sharebar"&gt;Cryptocurrency regulations around the world&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.lrb.co.uk/v40/n13/john-lanchester/after-the-fall"&gt;On the 2008 financial crisis&lt;/a&gt; - “I’m not sure if it’s philosophically possible for an action to be both necessary and a disaster, but that in essence is what the bailouts were.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="podcasts"&gt;Podcasts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/whatbitcoindid"&gt;Jill Carlson&lt;/a&gt; on the “What Bitcoin Did” podcast. “For the first time there is no longer a monopoly on the creation of value or monetary systems, that is really What Bitcoin Did.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/deVoaRTfVqs"&gt;Georges St-Pierre&lt;/a&gt; on the Joe Rogan podcast. A long and candid conversation from one of the world’s best athletes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/KqhRZfKRriU"&gt;Ricardo Spagni&lt;/a&gt; a.k.a Fluffypony on Monero vs Bitcoin, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EOS&lt;/span&gt;, the current bear market, Tari, and ASICs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="resources"&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lots of &lt;a href="https://vincentarelbundock.github.io/Rdatasets/datasets.html"&gt;data sets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"/><category term="Reading"/></entry><entry><title>Neighbours</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/neighbours.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2018-05-31T22:30:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-05-31T22:30:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2018-05-31:/neighbours.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Humans deserve respect, simply because they are human. This truth is in the process of going from self evident, to assumed, to&amp;nbsp;denied.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A useful model I’ve come across states that it takes three generations for a society to deny something previously considered true. The first generation studies or experiences something which leads to a particular value or belief. The second generation inherits the belief and assumes it to be true, but doesn’t arrive at the belief through their own critical thought. The third generation then questions the assumption, realises that most holders of the belief do not have a good basis for their belief, and disregards it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The belief that people have a responsibility to look after each other and treat each other with a minimum level of respect seems to be following this route.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That humans inherently deserve a degree of respect and dignity simply because they are human is self-evident. In times of comfort and excess it could be ignored, but in times of calamity and in the aftermath of disasters it becomes undeniable and obvious. This is partly because disasters reveal our instinct for justice and our frailty in the face of misfortune.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life is experienced through the lens of the mind, and its perception is mostly governed by fundamental circumstances or desires. The trappings of a prosperous society allows this reality to be covered by a veneer of soft arguments, or rejected in favor of a viewpoint that says we have superseded these supposedly basic origins. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good leaders should know better. They should study history and be self-aware. In the past they have forgotten this reality and have been forced to relearn it at great cost. Are we about to forget, again, and let our children live with those consequences?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My grandfathers generation saw the damage that sectarian systems bring, and were forced to answer questions around how much respect people deserve only because they are people. As the consequences of different views and systems became evident, my fathers generation assumed the answers to be self-evident, because the consequences of the previous “forgetting” were still clear. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who is clearly articulating this now? This year? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we discuss taxation, social mobility, migration, military intervention, why do we not start with the assumed self-evident truth that people are inherently valuable and important? Humans are more than metrics, and cannot be entirely evaluated using only quantitative methods. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Horton, the title character in “Horton Hears a Who” by Dr. Zeus, understood this. He went to great lengths to protect the tiny and weak people in who-ville. We teach this truth to our children, but do not demonstrate it as adults. Jesus also understood it. He said that we should love our neighbours, and explained that our neighbours are people we come across who need our help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wonder if forgetting that humans are inherently worthy of respect is a prerequisite for declining;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;standards of governance&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;social mobility&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;peace&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;economic growth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which makes me think it is a self defeating deception. When we choose to disregard a group of humans because it is inconvenient to help them, we are elevating our needs above theirs. This seems to create chains of events where everybody suffers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"/><category term="Politics"/><category term="Equality"/></entry><entry><title>Live near the ocean</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/ocean.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-11-23T18:48:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-11-23T18:48:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-11-23:/ocean.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Being near water is&amp;nbsp;better.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3 id="california"&gt;California&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="California" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/california3.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/california3.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/california3.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/california3.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/california3.jpg 1600w"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="California" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/california7.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/california7.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/california7.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/california7.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/california7.jpg 1600w"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="California" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/california9.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/california9.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/california9.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/california9.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/california9.jpg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="dorset"&gt;Dorset&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Dorset" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/dorset.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/dorset.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/dorset.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/dorset.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/dorset.jpg 1600w"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="Dorset" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/beach.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/beach.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/beach.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/beach.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/beach.jpg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="acapulco"&gt;Acapulco&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Acapulco" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/mex1.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/mex1.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/mex1.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/mex1.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/mex1.jpg 1600w"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="Acapulco" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/mex2.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/mex2.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/mex2.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/mex2.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/mex2.jpg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="dublin"&gt;Dublin&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Dublin" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/dublin.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/dublin.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/dublin.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/dublin.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/dublin.jpg 1600w"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="Dublin" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/dublin1.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/dublin1.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/dublin1.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/dublin1.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/dublin1.jpg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-netherlands"&gt;The Netherlands&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Hague" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/hague.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/hague.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/hague.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/hague.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/hague.jpg 1600w"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="Hague" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/amsterdam3.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/amsterdam3.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/amsterdam3.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/amsterdam3.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/amsterdam3.jpg 1600w"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="Hague" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/amsterdam1.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/amsterdam1.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/amsterdam1.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/amsterdam1.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/amsterdam1.jpg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"/><category term="water"/></entry><entry><title>Corporate London</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/corporate.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-07-10T21:37:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-07-10T21:37:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-07-10:/corporate.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Reflections on 3 years living and working in&amp;nbsp;London&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="2014-2017"&gt;2014 - 2017&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having made arrangements to leave London, it seems like a reasonable time to reflect on my time here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;London is a tough city to live in — it’s big enough that a sub 1-hour commute is considered good, and it’s super expensive. My stay in London has been defined by my quest to complete my graduate scheme and qualify as an accountant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first arrived I had no idea what London or working in a corporate would be like. I was coming from academia, and my motivation for moving to finance could be summed up in two points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand more about the 2008 financial crisis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get paid more for using mostly the same skills (math) as in engineering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t think there’s anything wrong with these motivations, but I should have been making a long term career plan instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started my job I was surprised at the 6 weeks of induction and hot-desking. Life as an auditor felt nomadic, as everyone would spend large amounts of time at client’s offices, and no-one has their own desk in our office. The only thing you really own is your knowledge and your network of relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2014, I arrived with a high opinion of my employer and the view that I would be staying for several years. Having escaped the financial insecurity of short-term research grants, I’d moved back to my home country to contribute to the system that educated me. I was happy to have a regular job with a decent, predictable salary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A phrase that kept coming to mind back then was “accountant factory”. Our training materials were scripted and everything was a standardised process. We were being processed. Graduates in, corporate accountants out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company is huge and so are the efficiencies and barriers to competition that come with this. When I arrived I was impressed there were free biscuits, and it felt presumptuous to put a meeting in someones diary. Now I ignore any communications addressed to a mailing list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="accountant"&gt;Accountant&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The toughest experiences were related to the accountancy qualification. Naïvely I had believed that the qualification wouldn’t be a big deal and I didn’t give any thought to it when I applied — I just wanted to find out how banks worked. If there were some exams to be done then it would be fine, I’d already achieved a PhD and I would handle it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That turned out to be a mistake. A huge mistake. The alarm bells should have rung louder when I realised most of my graduate colleagues had only applied so that they could get the qualification (and were already intending to leave asap afterwards). Doing the pre-course work before college wasn’t trivial. College - I was being sent to a classroom again. We were being taken out of the office, away from clients, and put in a classroom to prepare for these exams…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting a job that required becoming a chartered accountant, without considering the effort and time involved to qualify was dumb. It’s an oversight I find hard to believe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disappointment and sadness at having to study again was profound. The teaching and assessment style was several steps behind what I’d become used to. Compared to the depth, autonomy and research-focus of a doctorate, writing cookie-cutter essays in time-pressured exams felt stupid. The exams were hard and I failed several of them, probably because of my low morale whilst revising. Retaking them required more weekends and annual leave being spent away from my family, camped-out in libraries and offices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This required much patience and generosity from Ritsya, who having not seen me for long periods during my doctorate expected us to have a more normal lifestyle when we came to London. I found it miserable to pause my social life and other interests whilst studying, and then I would try to rush back to them when I had the time, knowing that soon I’d have to pause them again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I hadn’t already studied in Vienna, this process of working and studying in London would have been exciting and felt valuable or special. I’d passed enough exams though to know that they’re never as important as they’re made out to be, and whatever it was that was missing from my life wasn’t going to be found in another qualification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the upside though, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACA&lt;/span&gt; is the most practical qualification I’ve gained and has taught me many useful aspects of business and finance. I’m glad to finally see business not as some mysterious system but something attainable and understandable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="neighbourhood"&gt;Neighbourhood&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Living in London has also required a lot of time on trains — my door to desk commute is about an hour each way, and I’ve never lived somewhere in London that hasn’t felt transient. We’ve needed to live near a station and didn’t want to commute more than an hour and that’s put us in neighbourhoods with other young professionals who also don’t have long term plans (or financial ability) to stay in the city. We’re all looking to move on and move up as fast as possible.  I want to leave London partly because there are so many people with the same attitudes and priorities as my own…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="corporate-culture"&gt;Corporate Culture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in the office I spent the first few months figuring out how people were organised, how teams operated and how decisions were made. I think it took me about a year to feel like I understood how things really worked, and 1.5 years to feel like I could do all aspects of my job with certainty. There is a difference between how things are spoken about, and how things actually happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My experience has been that performance is all that matters and behaviour is defined by self-interest. I don’t think this is different from previous environments I’ve worked in — academia isn’t any different&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and the construction industry certainly isn’t. I wonder if the only way people can endure it is if they’ve not experienced anything else, or think it normal, or necessary. I find myself wishing we could be kinder to each other, and that we could create structures that incentivise mutual support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corporate finance usually appears clean and well presented. Its people appear dependable and capable. The culture is sanitised and there’s a lot of pressure to conform - you can see it in the clothes and accessories we wear and the jokes we tell each other in the canteen. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came to see my office as a glass and steel cathedral. I read about the Middle East, and migrants arriving in Europe, and tower blocks burning, and felt really disconnected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the high regard with which we hold ourselves, we don’t ask each other how we can help. Maybe we are too busy, or feel powerless to help. Apparently we do not know how to help, despite our wealth, talents, education and connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember watching a man leave the office one day and thought that if he gave his whole career and left his firm after decades of service, there would be nothing left to identify him after a few weeks. The work will always get done. Market forces will dictate how the business adapts and grows. The City rolls on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Publications trump almost all other metrics, and the incentives to publish quantity over quality are such that risky or slow research is inexcusable. The metrics used to standardise success and allocate resources can be subverted just as well in academia as in any other industry. What management measures, the team prioritises. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"/><category term="Career"/><category term="Corporate"/><category term="London"/></entry><entry><title>Move</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/move.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-07-08T12:26:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-07-08T12:26:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-07-08:/move.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Training&amp;rsquo;s&amp;nbsp;over&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="ambition"&gt;Ambition&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I was 15, one of my ambitions has been to be an entrepreneur. I used to joke with my dad about buying him a nice boat one day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life so far has been predominantly about education, and that stage is over now. I’m walking away from what I’ve come to see as a lifestyle and career that has too many contradictions, it doesn’t make sense to live like this. Ultimately I want to develop multiple sources of passive income. I want to create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="summer-2017"&gt;Summer 2017&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last few months have been intense, with some weeks leaving me feeling ambitious and energetic, and others feeling anxious and overwhelmed. I need to get better at defining a goal, taking the quickest path there, and ignoring interesting distractions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ritsya is brave enough and imaginative enough to force me to think big and consider how to live a better life. My biggest fear is that I screw it up, shooting myself in the foot and Ritsya and my daughter also. We were headed safely to an unremarkable existence and it would be terrible to swap that for something worse. That won’t happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that I make better decisions and produce my best work under pressure, I thrive when I’m perceived as an underdog. I need to accept this without using it as a reason to be foolish. Whilst I don’t have a clear plan, or direction, or goal, (I have many of them) I’ve got skills and I want to see what I can make. I’ll never do my best work, using my most productive combination of skills and experiences, if I’m a cog in someone else’s machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s safer being an employee than self-employed. I guess the price of removing self-employment risks is the difference between the value you generate for your employer and what you’re paid. I think those risks are overpriced, and most people are more capable than they realise. Sometimes you have to walk into a situation to find out how to make the most of it. And sometimes you have to leave a place in order to gain perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="autumn-2016"&gt;Autumn 2016&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year my boss gave me some advice that was supposed to be encouraging. I’d requested to reduce my involvement with some stuff that was unrelated to my job so that I could contribute more to my team and still maintain some semblance of a work/life balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My boss was pretty clear that reducing my involvement in the extra stuff would not be possible. During our conversation he advised me not to worry about how much I contributed to the team because “the work will get done anyway”. This was meant to be encouraging, but instead removed any conviction that the work I did was important.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"/><category term="Lifestyle"/></entry><entry><title>Flee</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/flee.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-07-04T08:42:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-07-04T08:42:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-07-04:/flee.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Summer children 
squeal and shriek, &lt;br/&gt;
Watch wars. &lt;br/&gt;
Excitement mounts. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How exotic. 
Unexpectedly, &lt;br/&gt;
Death arrives. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grow-up&lt;br/&gt;
Grow old&lt;br/&gt;
Face death &lt;br/&gt;
Evade evil.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t tire. 
World is fragile.&lt;br/&gt;
Towers burn,&lt;br/&gt;
Bridges bludgeon,&lt;br/&gt;
Markets stab. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Got to get out.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"/><category term="Poetry"/></entry><entry><title>London Rent vs. London Salaries</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/london.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-05-12T22:55:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-05-12T22:55:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-05-12:/london.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Living in London is only financially possible if you are either single or household income is more than&amp;nbsp;£60k/year.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Living in London is expensive, everyone in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; knows this. Everyone knows that this is mostly due to the price of property, which we all enjoy talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve lived here for 3 years now, and when my wife and I were both working we lived comfortably. Two incomes under one roof is just fine. Not as fine as in many other cities, but reasonable. Just over a year ago my first child was born, and now that my wife’s maternity pay has ended we are a single income household. This is not fine. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though I earn almost £50k/year, and any salary increase will be taxed at 40%, I cannot cover essential day-to-day costs. I’m in the 40% tax bracket, and my basic monthly outgoings exceed my monthly take home pay by £400. If my employer wanted to pay me enough to cover essential costs, it would cost them approximately double the shortfall due to tax. None of this makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salaries and living expenses have become really disconnected. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most people the most obvious way to increase wealth is to buy property. Mortgage repayments are cheaper than rent, and the value of the property increases over time. Double win. But there is a big hurdle to overcome before this is possible - saving money for a deposit on a house is often impossible without external help (i.e. the “Bank of Mum and Dad”), because so much of the money earnt must be spent on rent first. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a trap. Repayments on a mortgage are cheaper than paying rent, but you cannot save enough for a deposit because;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;so much of your salary goes to paying rent&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the average cost of a &lt;em&gt;flat&lt;/em&gt; in London is 500k&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, which means a 5% deposit is £25k — which is a higher deposit than you would need anywhere else in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt;, despite being the place you are least able to accumulate it. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if my partner went back to work and we put our baby in childcare? Childcare is not cheap, and working would need to bring in more than the cost of childcare. This requires a higher than average salary from a graduate job, (which is the life stage when people might reasonably start having children), so unless both parents are unusually high earners that option isnt viable either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Living in London is only financially possible if you are either single or household income is more than £60k/year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’d be lucky to find a 1 bedroom flat for less than £1000/month &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href="http://www.rightmove.co.uk/house-prices/London.html"&gt;Rightmove&lt;/a&gt;, an estate agent with some useful price statistics. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"/><category term="London"/><category term="Rent"/></entry><entry><title>Spare time</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/spare-time.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2016-08-13T21:15:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-08-13T21:15:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2016-08-13:/spare-time.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a list of interests I want to consider pursuing. I wrote it when I began to study for my last set of exams and my mind filled with things I’d rather be doing instead. Some of these interests are just me reacting to having no spare time for a few months, but others are decent goals and projects. Temporarily losing my spare time made me value it more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="free-time" src="/images/spare_time.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote this post so that I could compare what I thought was important when I was busy to when I wasn’t. Writing the list allowed me to move on without forgetting. Here’s a break down of each item:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Run 10k in 50 minutes” - This is easier than I imagined. When I wrote the
     list I could barely run 2k without stopping, but intended to go for a
     weekly run whilst studying. I’ve struggled to stay energetic and healthy
     during previous exam phases, so now I have a rule that I must do some mild
     exercise even if I think I can’t spare the time. I find running really
     lowers my stress levels, and increasing my heart rate and working up a
     sweat lets me sleep better and concentrate for longer. After a few weeks of
     minimal running, I could run 5k easily. If I kept at it, 10k in 50 mins
     would be easy. But point 2…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Be Insanity strong” - As in, do the Insanity workout programme. Again. I thought about it and decided to do P90x instead. Week 1 is going great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Read the bible habitually” - When I was 17 I found out about Jesus and
    became a Christian. In the months and years after that I’d regularly read my
    bible almost every day and pray a lot. I wanted to understand, so I set a
    goal of 5 chapters each day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read through the new testament repeatedly and read most of the old
testament during this time. I knew the scriptures well enough that a lot of
sermons became boring and obvious - I’d already studied the bible passage
being used. During this time I remember being aware that the way I thought
was different to how it would have been otherwise. My perspectives were
long-term and less me focused. I thought about what I was reading instead
of the days’ headlines or social chatter. I remember enjoying the benefits
and thinking that I should keep this habit. The reasons why I think
Christianity is so wonderful are well summarised in &lt;a href="http://messages.destinyedinburgh.com/sermon/the-gospel-we-preach-a-message-for-leaders"&gt;this
sermon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s now 10 years later, and whilst my convictions are strong, my knowledge
of the bible is sadly pretty fuzzy. My thinking is clouded by the
perspectives contained in the media I consume and the conversations I’m
part of. I strongly suspect I would be acting and thinking differently if I
read my bible more, but I don’t know what those differences would be.
Trouble is, it’s often not obvious what the immediate benefits of
reading the bible are, you have to work for it a bit. Praying for help is
effective. The books in the bible were written to last through the ages and
across all cultures, so it’s not surprising that they’re not as easy to
read as something written for an English speaker in a hurry. I should stop
being in a hurry, and stop prioritising only quantifiable goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Think more” - On a similar note to 3, but less supernatural. If I spent
    less time consuming content and a little more looking around me or walking,
    I reckon I’d be more self-aware and make better decisions. This would
    probably lead to a happier, more satisfying life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Pray more” - I don’t know why, but the creator of the universe wants me to
    talk and share my life with him. He cares about me. This makes no sense to
    me, at all. If I was God, I would not go out of my way to consider the views
    and concerns of a very flawed human. But when I pray, my prayers are very
    often answered. I should ask him about this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Amazon seller?” - Amazon have this “Fulfilled by Amazon” service,
     which means you don’t even need to hold the stock you want to sell.
     If I choose the right products, import them cheaply from China and
     reselling  them on Amazon at a profit, I end up quids in for minimal
     effort and manageable risk. Sounds intriguing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Blog about interesting data” - Here I am, blogging. I should stick
    to the main topic and get technical. I was inspired by this
    &lt;a href="http://www.curiousgnu.com/"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Finish Coursera” - The data science specialization is great! It’s in R, and I want to focus on Python, but I’d still like to do it. I need to consider the opportunity cost of the time committed, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Read for fun, history, fiction” - When I started my job, in April 2014, I
    was half way through &lt;a href="https://read.amazon.co.uk/kp/embed?asin=B00796LLLK&amp;amp;asin=B00796LLLK&amp;amp;preview=newtab&amp;amp;linkCode=kpe&amp;amp;ref_=cm_sw_r_kb_dp_GP2Rxb3Q8MYC4"&gt;Savage
    Continent&lt;/a&gt;,
    which is an eye-opening and eye-watering history of Europe in the years
    after World War 2. I see Europe through different eyes because of it.
    However I only got half way though, and since April ‘14 I never felt I had
    the free time or energy to pick it back up. This should change. When I was a
    researcher, and when I was a student, I had so much more opportunity to
    develop my own pursuits. Since entering the corporate world, I find myself
    fighting a war of attrition to exert my personality onto my lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read for fiction… I’m unconvinced. What do you have at the end of
it? What can you do with it? Maybe I’ve just been reading the wrong authors,
but I’m going to leave this for now. Sure, you could gain an appreciation of
a different time or place, but that appreciation comes via the fictional
characters and events, its secondary. What about abstract constructs,
perspectives, morals… things that history books are ill-suited for? Great
fiction would be essential for exploring these. But for now, I’ll prioritise
point 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" class="my-5" frameborder="0" height="550" src="https://read.amazon.co.uk/kp/card?asin=B00796LLLK&amp;amp;asin=B00796LLLK&amp;amp;preview=inline&amp;amp;linkCode=kpe&amp;amp;ref_=cm_sw_r_kb_dp_GP2Rxb3Q8MYC4" style="max-width: 100%; float:middle" width="336"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Do a photography project” - This I would love to do, but probably won’t.
     It would be a luxury, and the opportunity cost would be too great right
     now. I’d like to shoot a series of black and white portraits, and turn them
     into large prints. I think good portrait photography is uniquely impactful
     and moving, choosing B&amp;amp;W removes distractions and leaves a subjects
     humanity more exposed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Have a list of business/product ideas” - There’s no excuse for this
     one, anyone can have several good ideas. It’s turning them into
     reality that takes skill. Need to have the ideas first, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Do a law &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MOOC&lt;/span&gt;” - i.e Study particular areas of law, in my own time
     and at my own pace. I studied a tiny bit of law during the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACA&lt;/span&gt;, and
     realised employment law or contract law could be really useful.
     (Same for the tax system - another surprise). We only had a brief
     introduction though, so if I could find the time I’d like to know more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Do an InfoSec or Network Security &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MOOC&lt;/span&gt;” - Its super interesting,
     but not likely to be a good use of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Learn to fight - Krav Maga / &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MMA&lt;/span&gt;” - Ever since watching The Bourne
     Identity I’ve wanted to learn Krav Maga, and &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/LybrzdG96_8"&gt;Georges
     St-Pierre&lt;/a&gt; made me want to train
     for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MMA&lt;/span&gt;. For now though, I’ll do P90x. I can reconsider in 90 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class="relative" style="padding-top: 56.25%"&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen="" class="absolute inset-0 w-full h-full" frameborder="0" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/u0_8dzaNxhg"&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Get out of London” - My contract ends in April 2017, next summer
     will be a crossroads. I hate the commute, I hate being constantly
     rushed. Living in other cities has been a lot more pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"/><category term="Habits"/><category term="Advice"/><category term="Reflection"/></entry><entry><title>How to wake up early</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/how-to-wake-up-early.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2016-08-06T22:04:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-08-06T22:04:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2016-08-06:/how-to-wake-up-early.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For years I’ve wished that I could wake up early and use the quiet
pre-breakfast hours for distraction-free productivity. And for years I
have spectacularly failed at this. I love the quiet, distraction-free
hours at the end of the day too, as well as waking up slowly.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many famous leaders and politicians are known to start their days early,
and I would like to be able to do this too. After years of trying and
failing, I have had a break-through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The secret of waking up early is this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Become a parent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the first couple of months with a new-born:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will be well-practiced at quickly waking up at previously
    unthinkable times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will be used to operating on less sleep than you ever thought possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your beautiful child will become a reliable alarm clock, waking you
    up at the crack of dawn with cute smiles and increasingly insistent
    demands that you get up, play and make breakfast.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have the freedom to begin sleeping and working when you want, I still believe this is a great option. I bashed out a PhD in 3.5 years during which I usually woke up late and began to work around lunch time! - Glorious autonomy! &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Family"/><category term="Productivity"/><category term="Sleep"/></entry></feed>