<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>John Mathews - Non-technical/Journal</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://johnmathews.is/feeds/non-technical/journal.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://johnmathews.is/</id><updated>2021-09-10T13:52:22+02:00</updated><entry><title>1 Peter 1 vs 10</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/1-peter-1-vs-10.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-09-10T13:52:22+02:00</published><updated>2021-09-10T13:52:22+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2021-09-10:/1-peter-1-vs-10.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Concerning this salvation, the prophets who prophesied about the grace
that was to be yours searched and inquired carefully, inquiring what person or
time the Spirit of Christ in them was indicating when he predicted the
sufferings of Christ and the subsequent glories. It was revealed to them that
they were serving not themselves but you, in the things that have now been
announced to you through those who preached the good news to you by the Holy
Spirit sent from heaven, things into which angels long to look.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The salvation that Peter is referring to is described
&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.is/1-peter-1-vs-3.html"&gt;previously&lt;/a&gt;. He was encouraging us that
even though our salvation is mysterious it is very valuable, and that the
inexpressible joy that we feel is not unusual or a cause for concern. Don’t be
uncomfortable. Grace and peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To encourage us even more, Peter tells us that even the prophets (he implicitly
assumes his readers are familiar with the prophets, so I guess they’re
definitely Jewish, as guessed in the first post in this series) searched
for understanding about our salvation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They wanted to know who the Christ would be and when he would arrive. I guess
they initially thought they were doing this to satisfy their own curiosity
because it had to be revealed to them that this was in fact a service to the
saints that would come after them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, it says that it was the Spirit who predicted Christ’s sufferings
and the following glories. I would not have expected that the Spirit of God
needed to do any predicting about Christ’s sufferings or glories. Are you even
able to predict something if you’re omnipotent?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to the text, Peters says that things have been announced to us via those
who preached the good news to us by the Hold Spirit, who was sent from heaven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preaching by the power or enabling of the Holy Spirit has revealed things to us
that angels long&lt;sup id="sf-1-peter-1-vs-10-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-1-peter-1-vs-10-1" title="Long, or longed? I would have expected it to be “longed to know”, but its not. Does chronology get messed up from our perspective if the other party is outside of time?"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to know. We don’t know everything, and we
still have questions, but some of our questions are answered, some of them
inexpressibly, and some of the things we find mysterious or uncomfortable are
supposed to be so until our salvation is complete. Grace and peace. Hang in
there, you’re doing ok.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-1-peter-1-vs-10-1"&gt;Long, or longed? I would have expected it to be “longed to
know”, but its not. Does chronology get messed up from our perspective if the
other party is outside of time? &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-1-peter-1-vs-10-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="bible"/></entry><entry><title>1 Peter 1 vs 3</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/1-peter-1-vs-3.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-08-27T15:09:08+02:00</published><updated>2021-08-27T15:09:08+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2021-08-27:/1-peter-1-vs-3.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;May grace and peace be multiplied to you.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 1:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;mark&gt;Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ! According to his
great mercy, he has caused us to be born again to a living hope through the
resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead, to an inheritance that is
imperishable, undefiled, and unfading, kept in heaven for you, who by God’s
power are being guarded through faith for a salvation ready to be revealed in
the last time.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 2:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;mark&gt;In this you rejoice, through now for a little while, if necessary, you
have been grieved by various trials, so that the tested genuineness of your
faith - more precious that gold that perishes though it is tested by fire - may
be found to result in praise and glory and honor at the revelation of Jesus
Christ.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 3:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;mark&gt; Though you have not seen him, you love him. Though you do not now see
him, you believe in him and rejoice with joy that is inexpressible and filled
with glory, obtaining the outcome of your faith, the salvation of your
souls.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought that writing about 1 paragraph per post would be easy, maybe even too
short, but this is so dense that I’m not sure. The last three highlighted
paragraphs are all one paragraph originally&lt;sup id="sf-1-peter-1-vs-3-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-1-peter-1-vs-3-1" title="Originally in my English bible. Does the original text even have paragraphs?"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; , I’ve just split them up to
make it easier to write about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="part-1"&gt;Part 1&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Peter’s greeting (&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.is/1-peter-1-1.html"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;), he
starts his letter by praising Father God - the Lord of Lords and King of Kings.
Peter says that it is by God’s mercy that we have been born again, and that we
are able to enjoy a living hope. As soon as Peter says this he begins to explain
how, and he uses a chain or reasoning again like he did in his greeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m going to try and paraphrase in order to make the text less dense and make
its meaning more obvious:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because of God’s mercy, we have a hope that is alive and so significant it
    is as if we have been reborn. Our life is new, reset, fundamentally different.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is a direct result of Jesus dying and resurrecting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The living hope seems to be hoping (or trusting) in the inheritance which is
    promised but not yet received. The inheritance is described as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imperishable - cannot be destroyed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Undefiled - cannot be made dirty, less pure, less valuable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unfading - doesn’t get old or less good as time passes. It doesn’t diminish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kept in heaven for you - deliberately reserved in heaven for you, in particular.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By God’s power, you are being guarded until your salvation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This protection is received via your faith. Protection comes through your
    faith. Not because of it, or from it, but through it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The purpose of the protection is to keep you safe until your salvation,
    which will only be revealed to you in the last time. Your salvation is
    mysterious, because it hasn’t been revealed yet. This last point is
    itself mysterious.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1 id="part-2"&gt;Part 2&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The tested genuineness of your faith is more precious than gold.&lt;/em&gt; Not just the
genuineness, integrity, or sincerity of your faith, but the tested sincerity of your faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tested sincerity is more precious than gold. Your faith is contrasted with gold that will
eventually decompose - even really high quality gold that is ultra refined. But
your tested and sincere faith is more resilient and more valuable than gold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process that creates a tested and genuine faith in Jesus is therefore to be
appreciated, because of the end result. If you have a living hope of an
inheritance through Jesus resurrection, then rejoicing would be a good
response even if it is causing you grief and many trials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trials and grief will ultimately result in praise and glory and honor during the
revelation (revealing?) of Jesus Christ. I’m not sure if this is glory and honor
for Jesus, or for the person who has a tested and genuine faith. Maybe both?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="part-3"&gt;Part 3&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t know if this passage is instructional or reassuring, or both. I guess
it’s both at the same time - you should love him, even though you’ve never seen
him. And also, don’t feel uneasy about having never seen him. It’s unusual to
love someone you’ve never seen, but in this situation it’s normal. Don’t worry.
Grace and peace. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same goes for inexpressible joy - you’re hope in Jesus, his resurrection,
and your coming resurrection makes you happy in ways that you didn’t expect and
can’t really articulate or explain - this is ok! It is more than ok - it is
evidence of the sincerity and truthiness of your faith and is expected.
Believing in someone you’ve never seen, and loving someone you’ve never seen is
going to result in you obtaining salvation. It’s unusual, and different, but
don’t worry. Grace and peace.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-1-peter-1-vs-3-1"&gt;Originally in my English bible.
Does the original text even have paragraphs? &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-1-peter-1-vs-3-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="bible"/></entry><entry><title>1 Peter 1 vs 1</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/1-peter-1-1.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-08-25T15:26:07+02:00</published><updated>2021-08-25T15:26:07+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2021-08-25:/1-peter-1-1.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;People usually say that the bible is a collection of books, but some of the
books are actually letters. Two of the letters were written by Peter, who was
one of Jesus’ disciples. “1 Peter” is the first letter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other numbers are the chapters and verses. They’re used to divide the text
so that specific parts can be referred to easily. They’re not part of the
original text - chapters were introduced around the 13&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{th}\)&lt;/span&gt; century, and
verses in the 16&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{th}\)&lt;/span&gt; century, apparently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{1}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;To those who are elect exiles of the Dispersion in Pontus, Galatia,
Cappadocia, Asia, and Bithynia, according to the foreknowledge of God the
Father, in the sanctification of the Spirit, for obedience to Jesus Christ and
for sprinkling with his blood:&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;May grace and peace be multiplied to you.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the start of a letter to a specific group of people. It’s intended to be
encouraging and dense from the very beginning. It is intended that the letter is
remembered and paid attention to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sentence structure is awkward when its translated into modern English
because its a translation. Presumably in the original language you could create
long statements with many clauses in them and people would be comfortable with
that. I’m unaware of the letter writing customs of the day, so maybe Peter is
using a very normal type of introduction, or maybe he is deliberately imitating
the style of a specific type of letter, or person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first sentence implies that exiles of the Dispersion (what dispersion? I
don’t know.) are not exiles by accident. Even though I bet becoming exiled felt like an
unplanned interruption to their life. The first sentence says that God chose
them, and that there is a purpose. There is a chain of reasoning that involves
God the Father, God the Son and God the Holy Spirit - the trinity. One God in
three persons… I don’t get it, I can’t explain it, but I’m going to try and
work with this understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;According to the foreknowledge of God the Father →&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in the sanctification of the Spirit →&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for obedience to Jesus Christ and
    for sprinkling with his blood&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s like 1 and 2 and requirements for 3, because “for” means “the reason
why something was done”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should find out what “sprinkling with his blood” means, instead of guessing.
Clearly its a weird and gross idea…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It means… being marked by Jesus’ blood. It seems clear enough that this is the
blood that was spilt when he was sacrificially murdered, and it seems that the benefit or the
reason why this would be desirable is already obvious to the readers. Having
Jesus’ blood on you is to associate yourself with the benefits of that sacrifice
as well as to count the cost of the sacrifice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s probably a line of reasoning that would be intuitive to believers with a
Jewish background if they’ve previously sacrificed animals in temples during
various festivals. Is this letter written to a group of believers with a Jewish
(rather than gentile) background?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to the chain of reasoning: the foreknowledge of the Father and the
sanctification of the Spirit is necessary for being associated with Jesus
sacrifice and for being obedient to Jesus. That’s a big conclusion from only the
first sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;May grace and peace be multiplied to you.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like that exhortation so much I could get it as a tattoo. Grace and Peace,
better than fine dining and a comfortable bed. Also, chewing over the
implications of the previous sentence is enough to cause confusion and angst -
so the exhortation is well timed. Chill - even though you’ve been exiled, you
weren’t planning on being a migrant, and God planned this for you, and this is
part of your necessary sanctification in order to be associated with Jesus’
sacrifice - you can be full of peace, and there is lots of grace (which is
forgiveness, and patience, and maybe gentleness) available to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next sentence…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.3/latest.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';

    var configscript = document.createElement('script');
    configscript.type = 'text/x-mathjax-config';
    configscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'none' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        availableFonts: ['STIX', 'TeX']," +
        "        preferredFont: 'STIX'," +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";

    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(configscript);
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="bible"/></entry><entry><title>Daddy-Daughter To-Do List</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/daddy-daughter-to-do-list.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-08-22T21:07:12+02:00</published><updated>2021-08-22T21:07:12+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2021-08-22:/daddy-daughter-to-do-list.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Things we want to do together:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="checklist"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"/&gt; Make some furniture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"/&gt; Run to the beach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"/&gt; Parkour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"/&gt; Go on bike rides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"/&gt; Go to work together (when she is older)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"/&gt; Go on long train journeys together (Paris and Salzburg)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"/&gt; Go to restaurants and have long conversations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"/&gt; Take interesting people to lunch and ask them questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="daughter"/><category term="family"/></entry><entry><title>Can an explanation of an historical event ever be completely true?</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/historical-truths.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-07-06T16:53:56+02:00</published><updated>2021-07-06T16:53:56+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2021-07-06:/historical-truths.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We use historical events as examples to learn from, but is it possible to
acquire a true understanding of a historical event?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is important because we use that understanding to learn by example,
and identify patterns of cause and effect. Is it possible for a normal person to
do this, or does it require training, lots of time, or special skills? Is it
impossible for everyone?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started thinking about this when I had the following thought:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When we think we understand why something historical happened, all we’ve
probably done is accept a story that seems plausible.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="limitations-and-reliability"&gt;Limitations and Reliability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An account of an event must necessarily be a simplification - not
all details can be recorded or learned. This is ok because most details are not
pertinent and have no meaningful consequences. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how do we choose which details are included, and how do we verify that the
details were chosen correctly?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can we be sure that a lesson or conclusion based on historical events is reliable?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="hypothetical-model"&gt;Hypothetical model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truthfulness of a historical story could be thought of as a value on a scale
ranging from completely false to perfectly true. I think that there are
mechanisms that push popular or resilient narratives towards the middle of this
scale and away from either extreme. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a version of a story approaches the dishonest end it will contain an
increasing number of errors or omit an increasing number of pertinent facts.
This has the effect of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increasing the likelihood and frequency of someone hearing the story and rebutting its assertions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making it harder to align the assertions and implications with existing understandings of reality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the opposite end of the scale, a story is unlikely to be comprehensively honest because:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding truth requires adding complexity. It is easier to create or capture a
   simple story than a complicated story.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a story’s detail and depth increases so do the resources required to
   communicate it. Each narrative is competing for attention and a complex story
   requires more resources to broadcast and listen to than a simple story. Those
   with the resources to do so will want the story to benefit them in some way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This creates incentives to omit inconvenient truths and distractions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="implications"&gt;Implications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that there is unfortunately no substitute for the hard work of coordinating disparate
information, because the truthiness of a conclusion is generally proportional to the
inconvenience of the effort spent forming it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are predisposed to choose convenience over inconvenience and this enables:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;History to be written by the “winning side”, who have more resources than the “losing side”. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complex events to be simplified into expedient and bite-sized narratives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As time passes, the practical benefit of holding a view that differs from a
popular narrative decreases. This reduces any incentive to challenge a popular view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This creates a feedback loop that makes it increasingly difficult for a younger
generation to discover information about historical events that challenge a
popular narrative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="an-heuristic"&gt;An heuristic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How much evidence did I collect myself, that wasn’t brought to my attention by
an algorithm or by someone else?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="awkward-questions"&gt;Awkward questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Was &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WW2&lt;/span&gt; a battle of the good against the bad, or the bad against the really bad, or something else?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why did the Allies win &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WW2&lt;/span&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Was the influence of government on social freedoms in America 100 years ago dissimilar to China today?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Racial and ethnic discrimination was normal 100 years ago - it appears to have been so universally accepted that I’m led to question the presuppositions of modern attitudes about human nature and morality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.is/images/tom-gauld-cartoon.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="cartoon by tom gauld" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1600px, (min-width: 1280px) 1300px, (min-width: 1024px) 1100px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/tom-gauld-cartoon.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/tom-gauld-cartoon.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/tom-gauld-cartoon.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/tom-gauld-cartoon.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/tom-gauld-cartoon.jpg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="history"/></entry><entry><title>Proverbs 16</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/proverbs-16.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-06-25T12:00:29+02:00</published><updated>2021-06-25T12:00:29+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2021-06-25:/proverbs-16.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The first 9 verses seem to loosely be about plans and the motivations for
various actions. The wisdom and purpose of God’s actions are contrasted with the
motivations of human plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first proverb is a bit of a riddle. &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{1}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The plans of the heart
belong to man, but the answer of the tongue is from the Lord.&lt;/mark&gt; I get the
first part, but why would a spoken answer generally be from God? Is it that even
if you are wise, and fear God, your plans are still your own but the way you
speak about them is different because you fear God?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{2}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;All the ways of a man are pure in his own eyes, but the Lord weighs
the spirit.&lt;/mark&gt; Don’t be surprised that foolish, stupid or evil people think
that their actions and decisions are upstanding and good. Understand that God
says the spirit (motivation or attitude) that produced the plan or the actions
is what should be judged. I don’t think that God would agree that “the ends
justifies the means”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{3}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Commit your work to the Lord and your plans will be
established.&lt;/mark&gt; A good proverb for fridge magnets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{4}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The Lord has made everything for its purpose, even the wicked for
the day of trouble.&lt;/mark&gt; The mysteries around moral responsibility from
free will and predestination are not unique to the New Testament. I can’t think
of anything useful to say in order to expand on this. I believe it’s true, I
don’t really know what I would do differently now that I’ve read this proverb. I
can trust God that he knows what he’s doing and that he is &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;. I’ll add it
to my list of things I know about God without taking anything else off the list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{5}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Everyone who is arrogant&lt;sup id="sf-proverbs-16-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-proverbs-16-1" title="Arrogant: Having or revealing an exaggerated sense of ones own importance or abilities."&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in heart is an
abomination to the Lord, be assured he will not go unpunished.&lt;/mark&gt; God really
doesn’t like arrogance, which seems very similar to pride. This is troubling
because society seems to have lost any appreciation for humility to the point
where we no longer know how to talk about the virtues and vices of humility and
pride. Pride is considered a virtue and is conflated with self-worth. We lack
the nuance required to reliably discern wisdom from folly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{6}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;By steadfast love and faithfulness iniquity is atoned for, and by
the fear of the Lord one turns away from evil.&lt;/mark&gt; It is refreshing and
pleasant to read about &lt;em&gt;Steadfast love and faithfulness&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t hear many people talking about these virtues - love has been reduced or
redefined as something that can be found or changed quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faithfulness isn’t celebrated or spoken about very much. Maybe because it isn’t
as dramatic as betrayal. Faithfulness and steadfast love are predicated on
humility, which is another concept society seems silent about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second half of the proverb is also profound. It tells me how I can turn away
from evil. I know that it is easier to say I will change my ways than it is to
actually change, consistently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Being good” or “turning away from evil” is not nearly as easy or simple as a
child thinks it is, and this proverb tells me how to do it. The last proverb of
the previous chapter said that the fear of the lord is instruction in wisdom,
and that humility comes before honor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{8}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Better is a little with righteousness than great revenues with
injustice.&lt;/mark&gt; In case there was any doubt, here it is. Don’t compromise
yourself in order to make more money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{9}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The heart of a man plans his way, but the Lord
establishes&lt;sup id="sf-proverbs-16-2-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-proverbs-16-2" title="Establish: Set up on a firm or permanent basis."&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  his
steps.&lt;/mark&gt; So I can make my own plans, but if my plans are to be successful,
or substantial, I need the Lord to make my plans “firm” or “permanent”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{10}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;An oracle is on the lips of a king, his mouth does not sin in
judgement.&lt;/mark&gt; I don’t know what this means. An oracle is “a priest acting as
a medium through whom advice or prophecy was sought from the gods.” Kings have
certainly sinned when making judgements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{11}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;A just balance and scales are the Lords, all the weights in the bag
are his work.&lt;/mark&gt; God loves justice, and the instruments or justice are
ultimately his, and are from him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{12}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;It is an abomination to kings to do evil, for the throne is
established by righteousness.&lt;/mark&gt; The kings in verses 12 and 10 are not like
kings I have heard about. If 12 is true then perhaps 10 can be true. At a
minimum, 12 and 13 provides some standard by which to judge kings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{16}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;How much better to get wisdom than gold! To get understanding is to
be chosen rather than silver.&lt;/mark&gt; One of the many bits of advice that could
come from this would be to prioritise jobs with training and experience over jobs with
higher salaries immediately. Especially in your twenties or when you are
starting your career. You don’t need lots of disposable income, you do need
wisdom, training, experience, perspective, time with wise or experienced people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{17}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The highway of the upright turns aside from evil, whoever guards
his way preserves his life.&lt;/mark&gt; &lt;em&gt;Guarding your way&lt;/em&gt; - this is not a concept
or expression I’ve heard of before. I guess it could mean “defend the path your
life could take”, or “think about the consequences (second order consequences).”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{18}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Pride goes before destruction, and a haughty spirit before a
fall.&lt;/mark&gt; God really doesn’t like pride, and also it leads to destruction.
This is not a coincidence. Haughty means “arrogantly superior or disdainful”
which is mostly a synonym for prideful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{19}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;It is better to be of a lowly spirit with the poor than to divide
the spoil with the proud.&lt;/mark&gt; Avoid prideful people, avoid evil people.
Proverbs seems really clear that you are supposed to socialise and spend time
with people you want to be like. A lowly spirit is “low is status, or humble”.
Better to hang out with poor people and be humble than to be rich and associate
with prideful people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{20}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Whoever gives thought to a matter will discover good, and blessed
is he who trusts in the Lord.&lt;/mark&gt; More encouragement to trust God, and to be considerate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;21 and 23 both say that it is wise to speak persuasively or encouragingly. If
the words are well intended, then make them more effective by being persuasive. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{21}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The wise of heart is called discerning, and sweetness of speech
increases persuasiveness.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{23}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The heart of the wise makes his speech judicious&lt;sup id="sf-proverbs-16-3-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-proverbs-16-3" title="Judicious: Having, showing or done with good judgement or sense."&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and adds
persuasiveness to his lips.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{24}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Gracious words are like a honeycomb, sweetness to the soul and
health to the body.&lt;/mark&gt;Our words affect our bodies, and our souls. Gracious
words are really valuable. Gracious means to be kind, courteous, or patient. Let
it go, be gentle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{25}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;There is a way that seems right to a man, but its end is the way to
death.&lt;/mark&gt; Don’t be so confident in your own wisdom and judgement. It’s not
just that your judgement is a bit less good than God’s, this proverb says its
totally opposite. Expect to be doing things that look like the opposite of what
someone might expect. Expect to do unintuitive things. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{26}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;A workers appetite works for him, his mouth urges him on.&lt;/mark&gt;
True that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{32}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Whoever is slow to anger is better than the mighty, and he who
rules his spirit than he who takes a city.&lt;/mark&gt; Wow. This is high praise for
self control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="domino meme" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1600px, (min-width: 1280px) 1300px, (min-width: 1024px) 1100px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.is/images/proverbs/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/domino-meme.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.is/images/proverbs/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/domino-meme.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.is/images/proverbs/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/domino-meme.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.is/images/proverbs/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/domino-meme.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.is/images/proverbs/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/domino-meme.jpg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.3/latest.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';

    var configscript = document.createElement('script');
    configscript.type = 'text/x-mathjax-config';
    configscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'none' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        availableFonts: ['STIX', 'TeX']," +
        "        preferredFont: 'STIX'," +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";

    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(configscript);
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-proverbs-16-1"&gt;Arrogant: Having or revealing an
exaggerated sense of ones own importance or abilities. &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-proverbs-16-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-proverbs-16-2"&gt;Establish: Set up on a firm or permanent basis. &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-proverbs-16-2-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-proverbs-16-3"&gt;Judicious:
Having, showing or done with good judgement or sense. &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-proverbs-16-3-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="books"/><category term="bible"/><category term="wisdom"/></entry><entry><title>Proverbs 15</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/proverbs-15.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-06-24T15:36:13+02:00</published><updated>2021-06-24T15:36:13+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2021-06-24:/proverbs-15.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{1}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;A soft answer turns away wrath, but a harsh word stirs up
anger.&lt;/mark&gt; A soft answer can diffuse a volatile situation, and speaking
harshly leads to anger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{2}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The tongue of the wise commends knowledge, but the mouths of fools
poor out folly.&lt;/mark&gt; Knowledge is to be commended. If someone speaks a lot of
folly, they are a fool. Folly is “foolishness or a lack of good sense” - it’ll
take discernment to judge a lack of good sense. Find someone who commends
acquiring knowledge, and learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{3}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The eyes of the Lord are in every place, keeping watch on the evil
and the good.&lt;/mark&gt; Don’t mistake God’s patience for indifference, know that
your good works and faithfulness are seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{4}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;A gentle tongue is a tree of life, but perverseness in it breaks the
spirit.&lt;/mark&gt; Yet again, this book teaches that our words are powerful and have
great consequence. A gentle tongue, a soft answer, guarded words preserver
life, good fruit, fountain of life, now a tree of life. It is unequivocal, as is
the inverse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{5}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;A fool despises his father’s instruction but whoever heeds reproof
is prudent.&lt;/mark&gt; I just had a thought that people younger than 10 would have a
difficult time heeding or despising, and are too young to be considered wise or
foolish. They are children. When proverbs refers to parents and children, I
reckon its probably referring to either adult children and maybe teenagers. I
have young kids so I’m predisposed to see parenting advice in that context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{7}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The lips of the wise spread knowledge, not so the hearts of
fools.&lt;/mark&gt; What you say is important..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{8}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The sacrifice of the wicked is an abomination to the Lord, but the
prayers of the upright are acceptable to him.&lt;/mark&gt; Integrity matters, and it
seems that God is more concerned with motivation than impact. Better to pray
quietly and honestly than to hypocritically do good works in public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{11}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Sheol and Abaddon lie open before the Lord, how much more the
hearts of the children of man!&lt;/mark&gt; I am guessing that Sheol and Abaddon are
some reference to a hellish place - if God can perceive what happens in a
completely godless place that is far from him, it is going to be trivial
to perceive the thoughts and motivations of your heart. He can read us like an
open book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{12}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;A scoffer does not like to be reproved, he will not go to the
wise.&lt;/mark&gt; Reproof is almost as strong of a theme as words. Reproof is part of
growing up and becoming wise. You &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be reproved if you are to learn and
become wise. If I do not reprove my children then I am negligent. If you want to
avoid reproof or do not accept it then you are a fool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But remember, these are proverbs - they are generally true, most of the time.
There will be situations where you parent gives bad advice and you’d be wise to
ignore it. But its the exception, not the rule. If everyone else is the problem,
then the problem is certainly you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{13}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;A glad heart makes a cheerful face, but by sorrow the spirit is
crushed.&lt;/mark&gt; This proverb connections emotions, spirit and the physical body.
It says they are linked. If you are happy then you will look happy, and vice
versa. If you carry around stress and tension then it’s going to change how you
look. Don’t be sad indefinitely, it will crush you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grieve, and grow, and move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{14}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The heart of him who has understanding seeks knowledge, but the
mouths of fools feed on folly.&lt;/mark&gt; This isn’t talking about the consequences
of your words, it says that if you have understanding then your heart will
desire knowledge. If you feed on folly, which is like consuming things that are
foolish, then you are a fool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{15}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;All the days of the afflicted are evil, but the cheerful of heart
has a continual feast.&lt;/mark&gt; A pessimist and an optimist could experience the
same event and become respectively more pessimistic and more optimistic. As much
as you are able, choose to have a cheerful heart. If you are afflicted, then don’t
give up hope. Affliction doesn’t mean you did something wrong or lack wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{16}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Better is a little with the fear of the Lord, than great treasure and
trouble with it.&lt;/mark&gt; So the fear of the Lord leads to the avoidance of
trouble.. and it is better to live peaceably than deal with trouble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{17}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Better is a dinner of herbs where love is than a fattened ox and
hatred with it.&lt;/mark&gt; Better to eat only garnishes, or bait, with people who
love you than fine dining with people who do not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{18}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;A hot-tempered man stirs up strife but he who is slow to anger
quiets contention.&lt;/mark&gt; Don’t lose your temper. Blessed are the peace-makers..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{22}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Without counsel plans fail, but with many advisers they
succeed.&lt;/mark&gt; You’re not supposed to know everything and be completely
independent. You are supposed to ask for help, weigh the advice, and
deliberately look for wise people to be friends with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{23}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;To make an apt&lt;sup id="sf-proverbs-15-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-proverbs-15-1" title="Apt: Appropriate or suitable in the circumstances."&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; answer is a joy to a man, and a word in season, how good it
is!&lt;/mark&gt; It is fun to say something apt? It is a blessing to receive a bit of
well-timed advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proverbs talks a lot about words and mouths. For most of history, books have
been rare and literacy was not widespread. Therefore most knowledge transfer
would occur by speaking. Maybe it still does today because it feels like it
requires less effort than reading. I think the same principles can be applied to
reading and writing as for hearing and speaking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{25}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The Lord tears down the house of the proud but maintains the
widow’s boundaries.&lt;/mark&gt; The boundaries are the edges of the land owned by the
widow. God really doesn’t like proud people, and is soft-hearted towards the vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{27}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;He who is greedy for unjust gain troubles his own household, but he
who hates bribes will live.&lt;/mark&gt; Don’t be a fool, don’t be bribed - directly
or indirectly. Love life, look after your family, and hate bribes. Loving one
thing means you hate other things. If you’re building a business, design for
Segregation of Duties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{28}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The heart of the righteous ponders how to answer but the mouth of
the wicked pours out evil things.&lt;/mark&gt; It is good, and Godly, to think about
your answer &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; you say it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{33}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The fear of the Lord is instruction in wisdom, and humility comes
before honor.&lt;/mark&gt; Ok great - I have a definition for what “fear of the Lord”
means. (And it’s a reliable definition too.) I still don’t understand &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; this
is what it means, but at least I know &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; it means. They &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; question is
less foundational that the &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn humility, despise pride. Seek wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.3/latest.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';

    var configscript = document.createElement('script');
    configscript.type = 'text/x-mathjax-config';
    configscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'none' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        availableFonts: ['STIX', 'TeX']," +
        "        preferredFont: 'STIX'," +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";

    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(configscript);
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-proverbs-15-1"&gt;Apt: Appropriate or suitable in the
circumstances. &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-proverbs-15-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="books"/><category term="bible"/><category term="wisdom"/></entry><entry><title>Proverbs 14</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/proverbs-14.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-06-14T15:20:40+02:00</published><updated>2021-06-14T15:20:40+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2021-06-14:/proverbs-14.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{1}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The wisest of women builds her house, but folly with her own hands
tears it down.&lt;/mark&gt; This chapter begins with a proverb about women! And not by
juxtaposing men either. It’s important that I remember that wisdom - the
desirable quality that so much of proverbs is about - is personified as a woman,
like in chapter 9:1, &lt;em&gt;Wisdom has built her house, she has hewn&lt;sup id="sf-proverbs-14-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-proverbs-14-1" title="Hewn: chop or cut with an const"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  her seven pillars.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{2}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Whoever walks in uprightness fears the Lord, but he who is devious
in his ways despises him.&lt;/mark&gt; Fear is contrasted with despising, so I don’t
think this is supposed to fear of violence or victimisation, but more like a
feeling of reverence and profound respect. The Lord loves me, and in the
previous chapter it says that parents discipline their children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{4}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Where there are no oxen, the manger is clean, but abundant crops
come by the strength of the ox.&lt;/mark&gt; This is really interesting, the point
feels modern. The rural imagery is unusual (to me) but otherwise it feels
like something you might find on Instagram. What’s the lesson? Progress is
messy, or doing work creates waste, don’t fret about the cleanliness of your
manger if you want to have a productive farm..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{5}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;A faithful witness does not lie, but a false witness breathes out
lies.&lt;/mark&gt; It’s really important - don’t lie. This is a strong recurring message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{6}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;A scoffer seeks wisdom in vain, but knowledge is easy for a man of
understanding.&lt;/mark&gt; What does he understand? That scoffing is harmful to the
scoffer, and what else?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{7}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Leave the presence of a fool, for there you do not meet words of
knowledge.&lt;/mark&gt; It would be good to have a clearer understanding of the
differences between &lt;em&gt;understanding&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt;. This proverb is very
similar to modern sayings like “You become like the 5 people you spend most time
with”. What are the marks of a fool? How do you know if you’re hanging out with
a foolish person? They talk a lot, without thinking about their words. They are
quick to become angry or emotional. They are not diligent, or consistently hard
working. They don’t plan ahead (filling their barns in summer).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{8}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The wisdom of the prudent is to discern his way, but the folly of
fools is deceiving.&lt;/mark&gt; It’s wise, and prudent, to discern a course of
action, or series of events and decisions. Discern means “recognise or find
out”, I tend to use it to “look closely for additional clues about what might happen”.
“Prudent” means to “act or demonstrate care and thought for the future”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{10}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The heart knows its own bitterness, and no stranger shares its
joy.&lt;/mark&gt; This, I think, makes total sense to an old person and seems
mysterious to young people. When I first read it I thought it said something
like “no-one shares its joy”, but it doesn’t. Only “stranger”. Family and close
friends can share joy, but they still won’t be able to know your bitterness. I’d
recommend not holding onto bitterness, and finding out how its possible to
forgive because of the work that Jesus completed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{11}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The house of the wicked will be destroyed, but the tent of the
upright will flourish.&lt;/mark&gt; Again, don’t be wicked, it will go badly for you.
If you are upright and living in a humble, fragile, vulnerable tent
you can still flourish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{12}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;There is a way that seems right to a man, but it’s end is the way
to death.&lt;/mark&gt;This book doesn’t pull any punches. It’s an alarming assertion
that someone can think they are doing things “right” but are in fact heading
towards death. Don’t rely on your own understanding, figure out what God thinks
about a thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{13}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Even in laughter the heart may ache, and the end of joy may be
grief.&lt;/mark&gt;At the moment I don’t have much experience of grief, but I
inevitably will. I know there is sorrow so profound that it becomes physical as
well as emotional, and regret that changes what it means to be alive. I guess
one of the things this proverb reveals is that its ok to laugh whilst
experiencing heart ache, and its natural to feel happy and sad (laughing and
heart-aching) at the same time. It’s part of being alive emotionally, and
shouldn’t be considered weird or broken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;14 and 15 reiterate themes I’ve noted previously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{16}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;One who is wise is cautious and turns away from evil, but a fool is
reckless and careless.&lt;/mark&gt; It is wise to not do something, even if you could.
You don’t have to do/see/visit all the things, even if you could. It’s ok to
risk erring on the side of cautious, because if you are not cautious, you are foolish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess that if you are discerning then you can perceive more clearly and what
was originally partially known and therefore risky becomes less risky because
there are fewer unknowns. Instead of “maybe its wrong” it can become “its almost
definitely wrong, or right”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{17}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;A man of quick temper acts foolishly, and a man of evil devices is
hated.&lt;/mark&gt; Don’t lose your temper quickly. Losing it slowly is often more difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{18}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The simple inherit folly, but the prudent are crowned with
knowledge.&lt;/mark&gt; You’re supposed to aspire to prudence (and more generally,
wisdom). You can’t really opt out of this, because if you’re not
wise then you’re a fool. If you’re not prudent, you are (too) simple. And bad
things happen to fools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{19}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The evil bow down before the good, the wicked at the gates of the
righteous.&lt;/mark&gt; It’s surprising to read such bold and simple confidence that
justice would prevail. No ifs or maybes or conditions, just a simple resolution
at the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{20}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The poor is disliked even by his neighbour, but the rich has many
friends.&lt;/mark&gt; Timeless pragmatism. This proverb is an observation, not a
commendation. And look at the next proverb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{21}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Whoever despises his neighbour is a sinner, but the blessed is he
who is generous to the poor.&lt;/mark&gt;. Be generous, not just theoretically or in
your thoughts, but also in your actions and your money (see 23). Don’t despise people.
Who is your neighbour?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{22}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;…Those who devise good meet steadfast love and
faithfulness.&lt;/mark&gt; Steadfast love and faithfulness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{23}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;In all toil there is profit, but mere talk leads only to
poverty.&lt;/mark&gt; It’s not enough to only talk about loving your neighbour. And
don’t be convinced that any hard work you do it totally wasted, apparently it is not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{24}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The crown of the wise is their wealth, but the folly of fools
brings folly.&lt;/mark&gt; Really? Does &lt;em&gt;wealth&lt;/em&gt; here mean something more or different
to financial wealth? (I think I asked this in a previous proverb.) Not all wise
people are rich, this is certain. And many biblical heroes were financially
impoverished. Is it just a wide generalization?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{25}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;A truthful witness saves lives..&lt;/mark&gt; Literally. Though probably
without knowing exactly which lives, and at what moment. Investors refer to this
as second order consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{26}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;In the fear of the Lord one has strong confidence, and his children
will have refuge.&lt;/mark&gt; The best that I can understand this is to read it the
same as if it said “In the Lord one has strong confidence..”. What does this
proverb mean that my shortened simplified version doesn’t?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{27}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The fear of the Lord is a fountain of life, that one may turn away
from the snares of death.&lt;/mark&gt; Turning away is like physically repenting. A fountain
of life is a source of life, and probably health and healing. It is contrasted
with death traps. It would be interesting to consider the relative importance of
feelings and actions in this book. Is it that feelings lead to actions, but
actions are what makes the difference - the judgement between wisdom and
foolishness, love and hatred, depends (only) on your actions?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{28}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;In a multitude of people is the glory of a king, but without people
a prince is ruined.&lt;/mark&gt;If a king doesn’t have any subjects, what is he king
of? If leaders are not followed by any people, they cannot claim to be leaders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{29}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Whoever is slow to anger has great understanding, but he who has a
hasty temper exalts folly.&lt;/mark&gt;If you have a quick temper then you are
responsible for it, and you are endorsing foolishness. Being slow to anger is a
sign of wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{30}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;A tranquil heart gives life to the flesh, but envy makes the bones
rot.&lt;/mark&gt; Envy is apparently really bad. Tranquility is freedom from
disturbance, or being calm. It’s good for your health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{31}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Whoever oppresses a poor man insults his maker, but he who is
generous to the needy honors him.&lt;/mark&gt; The poor mater, and have dignity, and
are worthy of respect, because we are all made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.3/latest.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';

    var configscript = document.createElement('script');
    configscript.type = 'text/x-mathjax-config';
    configscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'none' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        availableFonts: ['STIX', 'TeX']," +
        "        preferredFont: 'STIX'," +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";

    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(configscript);
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-proverbs-14-1"&gt;Hewn: chop or
cut with an const &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-proverbs-14-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="books"/><category term="bible"/><category term="wisdom"/></entry><entry><title>Proverbs 13</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/proverbs-13.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-06-08T11:30:55+02:00</published><updated>2021-06-08T11:30:55+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2021-06-08:/proverbs-13.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{1}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;A wise son hears his father’s instruction, but a scoffer does not listen
to rebuke.&lt;/mark&gt; The chapter opens the same way as the previous chapter - with a
proverb about the importance of wisdom, knowledge or instruction. As always, the
proverb starts with the good example and then contrasts against it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{2}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;From the fruit of his mouth a man eats what is good, but the desire of
the treacherous is violence.&lt;/mark&gt; Slightly weird imagery I think, my mouth
produces fruit that I can then eat.. Weird. But I can see the principle - the
fruit of my mouth is the words I speak, words are powerful for either good or
evil. Speaking well will lead to good things that do what good food does -
nourish, strengthen, sustain. Treacherous people desire violence. So are people who
want to do violent things likely to betray? Maybe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{3}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;He who guards his mouth preserves his life, he who opens wide his lips
comes to ruin.&lt;/mark&gt; Choose your words carefully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{5}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The righteous hates falsehood, but the wicked brings shame and
disgrace.&lt;/mark&gt; It’s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt; to be strongly opposed to be falsehoods -
misrepresentations, lies, manipulation, duplicity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{6}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Righteousness guards him whose way is blameless, but sin overthrows
the wicked.&lt;/mark&gt; I guess there are (at least) 2 ways of looking at this - the
only way I can be blameless is by Jesus’ imputed righteousness, which also saves
me literally from death. The alternative is that I am not righteous and am
overcome by sin. Alternatively and more prosaically, try to be blameless instead
of wicked, and instead of creating trouble for yourself you’ll find people bear
with you for longer and are nicer to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{7}\)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;mark&gt;One pretends to be rich, yet has nothing. Another pretends to be
poor, yet has great wealth.&lt;/mark&gt; (I prefer not to use semicolons) I really
like this proverb! The last 20 years have seen several degrees of financial
wealth or lack, and the reality has often been very different to what I’d
expected. I often intuit that things must get easier, or nicer, or more
fulfilling if only a certain problem was removed, or a certain something was
bought, or recognised, or achieved. The reality is a lot more complicated than
that. Wealth isn’t what I thought it was, I thought it was mostly financial.
Now, I think its freedom. Freedom to be at peace, to be unburdened of my past
and present, freedom to still have hope for the future, freedom to have some
spare time, freedom to not be crushed by life and be a good dad and husband and friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{8}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The ransom of a man’s life is his wealth, but a poor man hears no
threat.&lt;/mark&gt; oh! Incisive! This reminds me of “no one ever really owns
a fortune, it always seems to own them”. There are various troubles and burdens
you avoid by being poor, like choosing life instead of material excess. Lose
your wealth and choose a rich life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{10}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;By insolence&lt;sup id="sf-proverbs-13-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-proverbs-13-1" title="Insolence: rude and disrespectful behaviour”"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; comes nothing but strife, but with those who take advice is
wisdom.&lt;/mark&gt; Disrespect and rudeness never works, wisdom is acquired when you
make a habit of asking for advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{11}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Wealth gained hastily will dwindle, but whoever gathers little by
little will increase it.&lt;/mark&gt; I’m surprised to read this - I didn’t realise
that the rate of change of ones wealth would likely effect how it can be
sustained, and I wouldn’t have guessed that this is some general principle that
exists across millennia, cultures and geographies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{12}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Hope deferred makes the heart sick, but a desire fulfilled is a
tree of life.&lt;/mark&gt; This one I’ve heard before. I don’t really understand it,
though. I’m not sure what a sick heart definitely is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems counter-intuitive because we are told to keep on looking forward to and
hoping for Jesus to complete his work saving us and bringing history to
completion. There is a lot of “now and not yet” tensions in between the time of
Jesus’ resurrection and second coming (I know so little about it that I don’t
particularly want to mention it). So maybe a Christian’s heart would be expected
to be a little sick? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, if &lt;em&gt;a desire fulfilled is a tree of life&lt;/em&gt; then I guess I’m desiring the
wrong kind of things - most of my desires are chasing after the wind. I desire
to eat and then I get hungry again, desire to graduate and then realise the work
hasn’t even begun, etc. The image of a &lt;em&gt;Tree of life&lt;/em&gt; hasn’t been used before I
don’t think, maybe it means something specific which I’m unaware of. There was a
tree of life in the garden of Eden…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;13 - 16: Don’t ignore wisdom, don’t be an idiot, be prudent, have good sense.
Strong recurring themes. &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{16}\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Every prudent man acts with knowledge,
but a fool flaunts his folly&lt;/mark&gt; is interesting though - I think prudence is
being used in a slightly different sense to what I’m used to. This proverb is
saying that one should be informed before acting. And because a fool rushes into
action, it will be clear that the don’t know what they are doing or talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{22}\)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;mark&gt;A good man lays up an inheritance for his children’s children,
but the sinner’s wealth is laid up for the righteous.&lt;/mark&gt; I remember reading
this when I was about 18 and thinking this was quite a burden - to leave an
inheritance for grandchildren as well as children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seventeen years later it makes a lot of sense - the inheritance isn’t primarily money,
but wisdom, peace, security. The way that I parent my children will directly
effect how they parent their own children, and in this way I will either bless
or curse my grandchildren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I damage my children, they will suffer and be less able to provide for their
own children (emotionally, physically, spiritually). Our own childhoods have a
large influence on our adulthoods, and our ability to parent, so I should make
sure my children have good childhoods, which is not a trivial endeavour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;23 and 24 break the pattern of “good example, bad example.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{23}\)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;mark&gt;The fallow&lt;sup id="sf-proverbs-13-2-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-proverbs-13-2" title="Fallow: ploughed and harrowed but left for a period without being sown in order to restore its fertility or to avoid surplus production"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  ground of the poor would yield much food, but it is swept away
through injustice.&lt;/mark&gt; The missed opportunities are real. Poor people are not
incapable of productive and fruitful work. It is injustice that prevents
fruitfulness. I find this proverb subtly provocative and insightful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{24}\)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;mark&gt;Whoever spares the rod hates his son, but he who loves him is
diligent to discipline him.&lt;/mark&gt; Parents who love their children do not enjoy
causing them stress or discomfort, but if they love them and are wise then they
discipline diligently, or consistently. Apparently physical punishment is timeless?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{25}\)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;mark&gt;The righteous has enough to satisfy his appetite, but the belly of
the wicked suffers want.&lt;/mark&gt; The last proverb in the chapter finishes with
encouragement that it is better to be righteous than wicked, because it leads to
satisfaction rather than want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The previous chapter also finished with encouragement specifically about
righteousness. Even though the book doesn’t have headings it seems like it does
have structure, and the author requires you to actually read the text closely in
order to pull out meaning. Shocking. Clearly not optimised for engagement,
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SEO&lt;/span&gt; or social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.3/latest.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';

    var configscript = document.createElement('script');
    configscript.type = 'text/x-mathjax-config';
    configscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'none' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        availableFonts: ['STIX', 'TeX']," +
        "        preferredFont: 'STIX'," +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";

    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(configscript);
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-proverbs-13-1"&gt;Insolence: rude and disrespectful
behaviour” &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-proverbs-13-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-proverbs-13-2"&gt;Fallow: ploughed and harrowed but left for a period without
being sown in order to restore its fertility or to avoid surplus
production &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-proverbs-13-2-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="books"/><category term="bible"/><category term="proverbs"/><category term="wisdom"/></entry><entry><title>Proverbs 12</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/proverbs-12.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-06-02T12:24:40+02:00</published><updated>2021-06-02T12:24:40+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2021-06-02:/proverbs-12.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The chapter starts with &lt;mark&gt;“Whoever loves discipline loves knowledge, but he
who hates reproof is stupid.”&lt;/mark&gt; and ends with &lt;mark&gt;“In the path of
righteousness is life, and in its pathway there is no death.”&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opening proverb is jarring to read, maybe because unlike “wickedness” or “righteousness”,
which are concepts I don’t hear or think much about day-to-day, “discipline” and
“knowledge” are very familiar and part of contemporary conversation. So is
stupidity. So this proverb feels tangible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does it mean? If I love discipline then I am loving knowledge, and in this
case I’m confident the opposite is also true - If I avoid or dislike discipline
then I avoid or dislike knowledge. Discipline is hard, I guess I need to lean
into being disciplined, and remember why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encouragingly, the proverb is immediately followed by the reminder that &lt;mark&gt;“A good
man obtains favour from the Lord, but a man of evil devices he condemns”&lt;/mark&gt;, so
make an effort, do good things, and obtain favour. That’s a big reason to
persevere through discipline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^4\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;mark&gt;“An excellent wife is the crown of her husband, but she who brings
shame is like rottenness in his bones.”&lt;/mark&gt; If it were me I’d leave off all
the negative second parts of these proverbs, its abrasive. But also if it were
me I doubt they’d be worth studying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is the pattern of all these proverbs “good thing, bad thing” - to make the
contrast stronger? To know why to do a thing and also why not to do the
opposite? To make it more punchy? I guess if its abrasive you are more likely to
remember it, and if you’re confident that what you are saying is true then you
want it to be remembered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to the proverb, this is a great proverb - I like it. It honors wives,
though it does put them in the context of their husbands, and it also speaks to
how valuable and precious a good wife is - crowns are precious and rare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empirically, it also feels &lt;em&gt;thruthy&lt;/em&gt; - marriages are difficult and if either
spouse can be considered “excellent” then that is unusual and valuable.
Relationships can give a lot of life and health and happiness, and require a lot
of effort and work. To be an excellent spouse is certainly worth desiring and
celebrating and protecting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next few verses contrast wickedness and righteousness - don’t be wicked, be upright!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^9\)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;mark&gt;“Better to be lowly and have a servant that to play the great man and lack
bread”&lt;/mark&gt;. Don’t put appearances before substance? Don’t spend money on fancy cars
or clothes if you wont have enough for decent food? Prioritize substance
(truth?) over appearances and social pressures? Having a servant (or a domestic
helper) would certainly be helpful, and of more tangible benefit than receiving
shout-outs at networking events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{10}\)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;mark&gt;“Whoever is righteous has regard for the life of his beast, but the mercy of the
wicked is cruel.”&lt;/mark&gt; - animal welfare is important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{11}\)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;mark&gt;Whoever works his land will have plenty of bread, but he who
follows worthless pursuits lacks sense.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11 and 12 are both about enjoying the good consequences of honest work, 11
advises against worthless pursuits, and 12 says that is a wicked to covet the
profits of evildoers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verses 13 - 19 are all about speaking and listening. Each proverb contrasts good and
evil or wisdom and foolishness. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;13 - your own dishonest words will become a trap for you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;14 - you words and your works will come back to you - invest in them and dividends will be returned.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;17, 18 - these contrast each other. Your words are powerful,
  speaking the truth is honest (even when it isn’t simple, or if it makes a
  situation more complicated) and being rash (acting without careful
  consideration of the consequences) can be as violent as wielding a sword. Wise
  words bring healing, though.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{15}\)&lt;/span&gt; Fools think they are right, and because of the contrasting pattern
presumably do not listen to (or ask for) advice. This seems similar to the
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunning%E2%80%93Kruger_effect"&gt;Dunning-Kruger
Effect&lt;/a&gt; Wise people
know that they don’t know everything they need to, ask for advice, and listen to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{16}\)&lt;/span&gt; I had to look up &lt;em&gt;Vexation&lt;/em&gt; - it means “the state of being annoyed,
frustrated or worried”. Wise people can stay calm and ignore insults. If you
get all fired up when someone insults you you’re probably (generally speaking)
being foolish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{19}\)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;mark&gt;Truthful lips endure forever, but a lying tongue is but for a
moment.&lt;/mark&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truth endures, lies do not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verses 20 - 29 have two themes - the benefits of consistent hard work, and the
benefits of being truthful. As usual, each proverb is a comparison of right and
wrong or wisdom and foolishness:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{21}\)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;mark&gt;No ill befalls the righteous, but the wicked are filled with
trouble.&lt;/mark&gt; This is encouraging to read, and also highlights that proverbs
highlight truthful patterns, but are not specific guarantees.  - Obviously
righteous people will have trouble, this proverb isn’t saying that life will be
perfectly pleasant. As usual, it is a push towards doing good because of the
benefits, a pull away from doing wrong because of the damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{22}\)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;mark&gt;.. those who act faithfully are his delight.&lt;/mark&gt; It is
wonderful to read that (a good) God would delight in people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{23}\)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;mark&gt;A prudent man conceals knowledge, but the heart of a fool
proclaims knowledge.&lt;/mark&gt;  I find it surprising to read that concealing
knowledge can be a desirable trait. I guess there are certain questions that
must be answered before the answers to other questions can be understood, and I
know that for my young children I wouldn’t answer particular questions that same
as if they were adults.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{24}\)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;mark&gt;The hand of the diligent will rule, while the slothful will be
put to forced labor.&lt;/mark&gt; Its ironic, and counter-intuitive, that those who are
diligent and able and willing to labor end up in management or leadership
positions, and that those who would avoid laborious work end up doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{25}\)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;mark&gt;Anxiety in a man’s heart weighs him down, but a good word makes
him glad.&lt;/mark&gt; I find it encouraging (again) to read that being weighed down
by anxiety is normal, and I like that anxiety isn’t described as a weakness or as
foolishness. (I don’t want to conjecture too much about what isn’t written, but
there’s a long list of things that fools do and the consequences of foolishness,
and anxiety isn’t on the list.) This proverb also emphasises and
encourages the impact of good words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(^{28}\)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;mark&gt;In the path of righteousness is life, and in its pathway there is
no death.&lt;/mark&gt; How wonderful to know how to find life and avoid death. It’s
such a pleasing way to end a chapter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.3/latest.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';

    var configscript = document.createElement('script');
    configscript.type = 'text/x-mathjax-config';
    configscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'none' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        availableFonts: ['STIX', 'TeX']," +
        "        preferredFont: 'STIX'," +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";

    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(configscript);
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="bible"/><category term="proverbs"/><category term="wisdom"/></entry><entry><title>Proverbs 11</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/proverbs-chapter-11.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-06-01T10:16:41+02:00</published><updated>2021-06-01T10:16:41+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2021-06-01:/proverbs-chapter-11.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;div class="toc"&gt;&lt;span class="toctitle"&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/span&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#context"&gt;Context&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#notes"&gt;Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h1 id="context"&gt;Context&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are my notes from reading Proverbs, one of the books in the bible. Almost
the entire book is a collection of proverbs - short sayings that are generally
true. I presume there is some structure and themes in their arrangement,
taking notes should help these become clearer and hopefully also help me
remember and apply them better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is split up into chapters, which are quite short sections of the book.
It would probably take about a minute or two to read each one. The chapters are
further split up into verses. In Proverbs each verse seems to be one sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numbering the text like this is useful because it lets you refer precisely to a
part of the book. Proverbs does have a few headings, but they are too far apart
to provide enough structure on their own, I think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve read this book a couple of times before, and appreciated it even when I
could feel that I was missing most of the wisdom in it. The book is quite easy
to read - the sentences are short and the analogies seem simple enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s refreshing to read something that has existed for thousands of year, has
withstood criticisms, and feels approachable. It’s practical, despite being
old and written in a completely different cultural context. I find this comforting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="notes"&gt;Notes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each proverb contrasts justice and injustice using a variety of
phrases and images. Pride and humility, integrity and crookedness, righteousness
and wickedness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the context of these qualities, various situations are described: a false
balance, disgrace, wisdom, riches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proverbs are somewhat exaggerated, which seems reasonable given that they
are self contained single sentences tasked with defining and then resolving a
problem. The imagery is clear, it does not rely on subtlety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest themes are that honesty, integrity, righteousness are to be valued,
and their opposites are to be avoided at all costs. Each of these qualities are
in fact actions, not sentiments, and the consequences of these actions are
reliable and consistent, and inevitable. The advice to “love your neighbor like
yourself” is a good summary of many of the proverbs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its clarity and confidence is encouraging. Do good and good things will happen,
do evil and the consequences are inevitably bad for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="examples"&gt;Examples&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The fruit of the righteous is a tree of life, and whoever captures souls is
    wise&lt;/mark&gt; - &lt;em&gt;the first part sounds wonderful. Who wouldn’t want to produce life?
    The second part is surprising. What is the “capturing souls”?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The desire of the righteous ends only in good, the expectation of the wicked
    in wrath.&lt;/mark&gt; - &lt;em&gt;this is encouraging&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;One gives freely, yet grows all the richer; another withholds what he should
    give, and only suffers want.&lt;/mark&gt; - &lt;em&gt;counter-intuitive&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Like a gold ring a pig’s snout is a beautiful woman without discretion&lt;/mark&gt; - &lt;em&gt;this
    doesn’t seem to fit in with any proverbs around it. Is this the only mention
    of a woman in this section? Why is it important enough to be included? Does
    this imply that beauty is discreet? There is surely a big cultural gap
    between Amsterdam in 2021 and where ever this was first written.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;A man who is kind benefits himself, but a cruel man hurts himself.&lt;/mark&gt;  - &lt;em&gt;this is good to know&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t lie, cheat, steal or plot. Treat people like you yourself would want to be treated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make an effort to do good and increase justice, and things will go well
for you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;God delights in blameless people, and he abhors people with crooked hearts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beauty without discretion is an incongruous waste.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="books"/><category term="bible"/><category term="proverbs"/><category term="wisdom"/></entry><entry><title>My Life Expectancy</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/my-life-expectancy.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-05-12T10:59:32+02:00</published><updated>2021-05-12T10:59:32+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2021-05-12:/my-life-expectancy.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="key-points"&gt;Key points:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weight doesn’t matter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be in “excellent” health.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workout 3 or 4 times a week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drink liquor (or red wine) 3 or 4 times a week (after each workout).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try to be happy, optimistic and relaxed. What are you working so hard for
   anyway? You need something to do, someone to love, something to hope for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1 id="longevity-calculations"&gt;Longevity Calculations&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was playing with the life expectancy calculator at &lt;a href="https://www.blueprintincome.com/tools/life-expectancy-calculator-how-long-will-i-live/"&gt;blueprintincome&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id="sf-my-life-expectancy-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-my-life-expectancy-1" title="There is also a more detailed calculator at projectbiglife, its calibrated for Canadian citizens."&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and was surprised to find that their regression technique gives me
a 50% chance of living to 95! I’d expected a result closer to 80.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After printing out a &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.is/90-year-life-calendar.jpg"&gt;90 year calendar&lt;/a&gt;, my next
thought was to play with the calculator to find the maximum age I could have a 50% chance of reaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing the factors below would apparently give me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;75% chance of living to 92&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;50% change of living to 101&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;25% chance of living to 107&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="dont-workout-every-day"&gt;Don’t workout every day&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no additional benefit from working out more than 4 times a week.
Once you’re fit and working out 4 times a week it doesn’t matter if you do
more exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being in “excellent” health is better than being in “very good” health though,
so make the workouts count. I guess if it didn’t make a difference then it
wouldn’t be excellent in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="drink-more-alcohol"&gt;Drink more alcohol&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was surprised that having 3-4 drinks each week increases your life
expectancy. I thought that it was best to not drink any alcohol at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should be drinking red wine or liquor 3 or 4 times each week. Liquor increases
longevity in men, but reduces longevity for women. Red wine increases longevity in
women, but has no effect in men&lt;sup id="sf-my-life-expectancy-2-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-my-life-expectancy-2" title="Alcohol consumption in later life and reaching longevity: the Netherlands Cohort Study "&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I guess I
should drink some rum after each workout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="weight-doesnt-make-a-different"&gt;Weight doesn’t make a different&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to their regression, my expected longevity is unchanged within a
weight range of 78kg - 90kg. I guess it’s much more important that I’m in
“excellent” health, working out 4 times a week and having some wine, rum, or
whiskey after each workout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="but-its-just-statistics"&gt;But it’s just statistics&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The calculator only asks for quantifiable or physical attributes. It doesn’t
consider emotional, relational or spiritual factors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-my-life-expectancy-1"&gt;There is also a more detailed
calculator at &lt;a href="https://www.projectbiglife.ca/life-expectancy-calculator"&gt;projectbiglife&lt;/a&gt;, its calibrated for Canadian citizens. &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-my-life-expectancy-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-my-life-expectancy-2"&gt;&lt;a href="https://academic.oup.com/ageing/article/49/3/395/5730334"&gt;Alcohol consumption in later life and
reaching longevity: the Netherlands Cohort Study
&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-my-life-expectancy-2-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="regression"/><category term="statistics"/><category term="life-expectancy"/><category term="death"/></entry><entry><title>Reading - April 2021</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/reading-april-2021.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-04-21T12:55:20+02:00</published><updated>2021-04-21T12:55:20+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2021-04-21:/reading-april-2021.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;div class="toc"&gt;&lt;span class="toctitle"&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/span&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#the-architecture-behind-a-one-person-tech-startup"&gt;The Architecture Behind A One-Person Tech Startup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#boring-tech-behind-a-one-person-saas"&gt;Boring tech behind a one person SaaS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#djangos-place-in-a-web-development-world"&gt;Djangos place in a web development world&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#cache-invalidation"&gt;&lt;s&gt;Cache invalidation&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#vim-abbreviations"&gt;Vim abbreviations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#to-fix-the-social-sciences-look-to-the-dark-ages-of-medicine"&gt;&lt;s&gt;To fix the social sciences, look to the “dark ages” of medicine&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#emotional-resilience-in-leadership-report"&gt;Emotional resilience in leadership report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#3-virtues-of-a-programmer"&gt;3 virtues of a programmer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#is-webassembly-magic-performance-pixie-dust"&gt;Is WebAssembly magic performance pixie dust?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#yamauchi-no10-family-office"&gt;Yamauchi No.10 Family Office&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#improve-and-extend-your-text-objects-with-targetsvim"&gt;Improve and Extend Your Text Objects With targets.vim&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#a-vim-guide-for-adept-users"&gt;A Vim Guide for Adept Users&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#deep-dive-in-cors"&gt;Deep dive in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CORS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#the-tty-demystified"&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TTY&lt;/span&gt; demystified&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Articles and blog posts I saved to read later:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the-architecture-behind-a-one-person-tech-startup"&gt;&lt;a href="https://anthonynsimon.com/blog/one-man-saas-architecture/"&gt;The Architecture Behind A One-Person Tech Startup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An article by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/anthonynsimon"&gt;Anthony Najjar Simon&lt;/a&gt; about how he runs his one-man SaaS using Django.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low stress, one-person company, run from a flat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-funded, taking things slow - &lt;em&gt;he likes taking things slow&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grateful to be standing on the shoulders of the open source giants who went ahead and made the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OSS&lt;/span&gt; stack we all enjoy and benefit from.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your own context matters when choosing a tech stack. There is no “holy grail”. I guess this means that you should use what you’re familiar with and what is &lt;em&gt;boring&lt;/em&gt; for you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses K8s on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AWS&lt;/span&gt;. He says “dont fall into the trap of thinking you need to use it too” - expertise with these tools was learnt over several years fighting fires on the day job.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Productive because he used the tools he is most familiar with and he can focus on shipping.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Django, Celery, PostgreSQL, Python, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AWS&lt;/span&gt;, Redis. - same as MoneyBar and PipPip.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="boring-tech-behind-a-one-person-saas"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.listennotes.com/blog/the-boring-technology-behind-a-one-person-23/"&gt;Boring tech behind a one person SaaS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The tech-stack keeps evolving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Boring” means “what I’m familiar with so that I can focus on the business”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of his time is spent talking to people and thinking. He spends 15% of his time on engineering. Probably it was more when he was setting stuff up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The methods described in the post are &lt;strong&gt;definitely not the best way&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;em&gt;It’s just one way of doing engineering in a very specific type of business. It’s not the only way.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Django, Celery, PostgreSQL, Python, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AWS&lt;/span&gt;, Redis. - same as MoneyBar and PipPip.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses Ansible for provisioning machines. - &lt;span class="caps"&gt;YAML&lt;/span&gt; files. Should look into this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Good enough for now”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Doesn’t use &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CI&lt;/span&gt; tools, he uses Ansible with a shell script he wrote.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses &lt;a href="https://www.datadoghq.com/"&gt;Datadog&lt;/a&gt; for monitoring and alerting, and PagerDuty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses &lt;a href="https://rollbar.com/"&gt;Rollbar&lt;/a&gt;, which seems similar to Sentry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses Slack, not to talk with humans, but integrations with Rollbar and Datadog, and also &lt;a href="https://api.slack.com/messaging/webhooks"&gt;slack incoming webhooks&lt;/a&gt; to be notified when someone signs up or does something interesting like deletes a thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make a “ding” sound whenever someone signs up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He’s &lt;em&gt;always very careful about operational stuff&lt;/em&gt; to prevent downtime and outages. Servers are over-provisioned to protect against spikes caused by sudden media interest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoids working from home or cafe cos its more productive in an office. Productivity is important - make every minute count. He doesn’t often work more than 8 hours/day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He optimizes for spending less time and making money instead of more time and saving money.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses &lt;code&gt;Vagrant&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;virtualbox&lt;/code&gt; on an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MBP&lt;/span&gt; so that dev work is on the same systems as prod infra.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses 1 monolithic repo. Likes this approach.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;He uses contractors&lt;/em&gt;!!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Usually, the biggest obstacle to building and shipping things is overthinking. What if this, what if that. You are not important at all and no one cares. No one sees. Even if you screw up the initial product launch, no one will care because they’re not looking. Only when you’ve proved that you deserve their attention will you have any attention and visibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://hackernoon.com/think-big-start-small-act-fast-6fdab1f771ea"&gt;Think big, start small, act fast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use boring technology, or whatever tech you want. Just make sure you’re solving an actual problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ignore the &lt;a href="https://stevemcconnell.com/articles/cargo-cult-software-engineering/"&gt;cargo cult people&lt;/a&gt; and ignore the noise. Keep calm and carry on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="djangos-place-in-a-web-development-world"&gt;&lt;a href="https://thenewstack.io/djangos-place-in-a-web-development-world-ruled-by-react/"&gt;Djangos place in a web development world&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not everything needs to be an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SPA&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Django is a back-end framework, it’ll work with an front-end framework, because separation of concerns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To use django with an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SPA&lt;/span&gt;, you could use &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DRF&lt;/span&gt;, or just normal views that return &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JSON&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reading this makes me want to check out React to see what all the fuss is about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="cache-invalidation"&gt;&lt;s&gt;&lt;a href="https://yihui.org/en/2018/06/cache-invalidation/"&gt;Cache invalidation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id="vim-abbreviations"&gt;&lt;a href="https://jovica.org/posts/vim_abbreviations/"&gt;Vim abbreviations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cool and all, but not as powerful as snippets I think.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Auto correcting typos: teh -&amp;gt; the&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expanding phrases: kr -&amp;gt; kind regards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi-line text expansion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It really seems similar to what I’m using UltiSnips for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I found &lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/30266587/snippets-vs-abbreviations-in-vim"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; question on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SO&lt;/span&gt; comparing abbreviations and snippets. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TLDR&lt;/span&gt;: It’s easier to add and maintain snippets than abbreviations, and you have less boilerplate with snippets than abbreviations, especially in complex cases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="to-fix-the-social-sciences-look-to-the-dark-ages-of-medicine"&gt;&lt;s&gt;&lt;a href="https://thereader.mitpress.mit.edu/social-sciences-dark-ages/"&gt;To fix the social sciences, look to the “dark ages” of medicine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id="emotional-resilience-in-leadership-report"&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/18FfZ86PGA_uSFf425EzKXAmiFQLFBPqjqPN7iu1TZRw/preview?pru=AAABdEZGCv8*_gdPBrQH8tAPyvMfLk6Unw"&gt;Emotional resilience in leadership report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id="3-virtues-of-a-programmer"&gt;&lt;a href="http://threevirtues.com/"&gt;3 virtues of a programmer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laziness - The quality that makes you go to great effort to reduce overall energy expenditure. It makes you write labor-saving programs that other people will find useful and document what you wrote so you don’t have to answer so many questions about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Impatience - The anger you feel when the computer is being lazy. This makes you write programs that don’t just react to your needs, but actually anticipate them. Or at least pretend to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hubris - The quality that makes you write (and maintain) programs that other people won’t want to say bad things about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also, I read a quote somewhere saying the mark of a great program is having people use it in ways you didn’t expect, or something like that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="is-webassembly-magic-performance-pixie-dust"&gt;&lt;a href="https://surma.dev/things/js-to-asc/"&gt;Is WebAssembly magic performance pixie dust?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id="yamauchi-no10-family-office"&gt;&lt;a href="https://y-n10.com/"&gt;Yamauchi No.10 Family Office&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A beautifully designed website.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="improve-and-extend-your-text-objects-with-targetsvim"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.barbarianmeetscoding.com/blog/exploring-vim-plugins-improve-and-extend-your-text-objects-with-targets-vim"&gt;Improve and Extend Your Text Objects With targets.vim&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id="a-vim-guide-for-adept-users"&gt;&lt;a href="https://thevaluable.dev/vim-adept"&gt;A Vim Guide for Adept Users&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to manipulate multiple quickfix and location lists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are digraphs and how to use them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Useful keystrokes in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;INSERT&lt;/span&gt; mode.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Useful keystrokes in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VISUAL&lt;/span&gt; mode.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vim regular expressions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using shell commands in Vim.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Folding content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="deep-dive-in-cors"&gt;&lt;a href="https://ieftimov.com/post/deep-dive-cors-history-how-it-works-best-practices/"&gt;Deep dive in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CORS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the-tty-demystified"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.linusakesson.net/programming/tty/index.php"&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TTY&lt;/span&gt; demystified&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;ps 1&lt;/code&gt; - see which processes are running or sleeping. &lt;code&gt;WCHAN&lt;/code&gt; tells you which
    kernel event a waiting processing is awaiting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="reading"/></entry><entry><title>Tweets - April 2021</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/tweets-april-2021.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-04-21T10:39:48+02:00</published><updated>2021-04-21T10:39:48+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2021-04-21:/tweets-april-2021.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;div class="toc"&gt;&lt;span class="toctitle"&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/span&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#front-end"&gt;Front-End&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#entrepreneurship"&gt;Entrepreneurship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#mental-models"&gt;Mental Models&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#agency"&gt;Agency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#razors"&gt;Razors&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#crypto"&gt;Crypto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h1 id="front-end"&gt;Front-End&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt; 6 website for top landing page inspiration&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;• onepagelove .com by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/robhope?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@robhope&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt;• lapa .ninja by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/nguyendangtinh?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@nguyendangtinh&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt;• landingfolio .com by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dannypostmaa?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@dannypostmaa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;• saasframe .io by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AntoineMilkoff?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@AntoineMilkoff&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;• saaslandingpage .com by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Cruip_com?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@Cruip_com&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt;• saaspages .xyz by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Versoly?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@Versoly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Jim Raptis (@d__raptis) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/d__raptis/status/1382240459288895491?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;April 14, 2021&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="entrepreneurship"&gt;Entrepreneurship&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;anyone interested in a fun &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/microacquire?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@microacquire&lt;/a&gt; challenge?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;maybe 90 or 180 days from start to finish to build and sell a tiny company in public?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;would be really great M&amp;amp;A practice for my fellow founders&lt;/p&gt;— Jim Bisenius (@jim_bisenius) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jim_bisenius/status/1382169652403564546?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;April 14, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="mental-models"&gt;Mental Models&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;Tobi's favorite example of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FIRST&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PRINCIPLES&lt;/span&gt; is a Truck driver.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;His truck was sat still for 8 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HOURS&lt;/span&gt; on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;THANKSGIVING&lt;/span&gt; waiting for his cargo to be unloaded when he realized…&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;“Why not take the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WHOLE&lt;/span&gt; trailer off the back of my ship rather than unloading + reloading each item?”&lt;/p&gt;— George Mack (@george__mack) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/george__mack/status/1262509025515786248?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;May 18, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;LUTKE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEARNING&lt;/span&gt; 6 - &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TALENT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STACK&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LED&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BY&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CURIOSITY&lt;/span&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MBA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;He didn't have an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MBA&lt;/span&gt;. He didn't grind 100-hour workweeks. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Instead, he played video games (which led to coding) and he snowboarded (which led to an online snowboarding store). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This 'Talent Stack' led to Shopify.&lt;/p&gt;— George Mack (@george__mack) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/george__mack/status/1262509059841953801?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;May 18, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A super long thread, worth reading it all:
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;Josh Waitzkin might be the most &lt;span class="caps"&gt;INTERESTING&lt;/span&gt; person alive.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;He doesn't have Twitter. And he barely uses the internet.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;I've compiled my favorite 5 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MENTAL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MODELS&lt;/span&gt; of his below.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;THREAD&lt;/span&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;— George Mack (@george__mack) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/george__mack/status/1292206014746558471?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;August 8, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="agency"&gt;Agency&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;1/ &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HIGH&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AGENCY&lt;/span&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Once you &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SEE&lt;/span&gt; it - you can never &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UNSEE&lt;/span&gt; it. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Arguedbly the most important personality trait you can foster. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;I've thought about this concept every week for the last two years since I heard &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/EricRWeinstein?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@EricRWeinstein&lt;/a&gt; discuss it on &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/tferriss?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@tferriss&lt;/a&gt;' podcast. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;THREAD&lt;/span&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;— George Mack (@george__mack) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/george__mack/status/1068238562443841538?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;November 29, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="razors"&gt;Razors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;THREAD&lt;/span&gt;: 15 of the most useful razors and rules I've found.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Rules of thumb that simplify decisions.&lt;/p&gt;— George Mack (@george__mack) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/george__mack/status/1350513143387189248?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;January 16, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="crypto"&gt;Crypto&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt; Now let’s compare this to the stock-to-flow model. Below I added in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;S2F&lt;/span&gt; model, which is the aforementioned inflation rate regressed against price. /10 &lt;a href="https://t.co/eGRXIux6K2"&gt;pic.twitter.com/eGRXIux6K2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Jurrien Timmer (@TimmerFidelity) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/TimmerFidelity/status/1382026424014548995?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;April 13, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Bitcoin?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#Bitcoin&lt;/a&gt; is looking strong at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSI&lt;/span&gt; 92. Still not above &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSI&lt;/span&gt; 95 like 2017, 2013 and 2011 bull markets. I calculated &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BTC&lt;/span&gt; price needed for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSI&lt;/span&gt; 95 at April close: $92K. Let's see what the Coinbase &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IPO&lt;/span&gt; will do today🚀 &lt;a href="https://t.co/UTvdFWFhDK"&gt;pic.twitter.com/UTvdFWFhDK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— PlanB (@100trillionUSD) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/100trillionUSD/status/1382282077429719040?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;April 14, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="twitter"/></entry><entry><title>Over-Engineering this blog</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/over-engineering-this-blog.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-04-05T11:54:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-04-05T11:54:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2021-04-05:/over-engineering-this-blog.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the last few weeks I’ve spent an unreasonable amount of time and energy
making unnecessary improvements to this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of these improvements are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding keyboard shortcuts (type &lt;code&gt;?&lt;/code&gt; to find out which).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://johnmathews.is/adding-search.html"&gt;Implementing&lt;/a&gt;, then
   &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.is/fuse-search.html"&gt;reimplementing&lt;/a&gt;, and then optimizing client
   side fuzzy search.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using &lt;code&gt;src-set&lt;/code&gt; to serve responsive images
   (&lt;a href="https://github.com/pelican-plugins/image-process"&gt;Image-Process&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lazy loading images to make this site load faster.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compressing page files using &lt;code&gt;brotli&lt;/code&gt; and also &lt;code&gt;gzip&lt;/code&gt;
   (&lt;a href="https://github.com/kurtmckee/pelican_precompress"&gt;Precompress&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trying (and ultimately failing) to avoid a “white flash” when dark mode is
   chosen and a new page loads (&lt;a href="https://github.com/tailwindlabs/tailwindcss/discussions/3904"&gt;Github
   discussion&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not really sure why I did it. It makes almost no difference to anyone but
me. It felt a bit compulsive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like tinkering, and it’s nice to build something that will continue to work
with no maintenance. I tell myself that over the next few years I will gain the
benefits of these features even when I’ve forgotten I implemented them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s taught me a lot of JavaScript, which is a great language to be familiar
with - it’s everywhere. I would warmly encourage someone younger than myself to
pursue interests for the sake of curiosity and fun. And there is a very high
chance that even if no-one uses the shortcuts except me, my new javascript
skills will come in useful somewhere else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even if they do I’m not sure its a good enough reason - things should be
built when they solve a present problem, not over-engineered for what-ifs and
maybes. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/You_aren%27t_gonna_need_it"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;YAGNI&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I
wouldn’t let myself do this in a professional capacity. There is a tension
between being curious and being focussed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not really sure that I need to justify myself. Its a hobby, I wanted to do
it, I enjoy tinkering with web technologies and learning new things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But also, I lost sleep over this - I stayed up too late, and let it put
pressure on other things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that being curious, and making room to play with interesting things, has
been one of the most useful approaches to personal development and up-skilling
myself. But there must be a limit..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a tension between wasting my time and taking a risk, and it will take
a few years before I know for sure if these efforts were worthwhile, or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it’s not fun, don’t do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Successful business owners seem to be very good at leaving things alone once
they’re “good enough”, and not being perfectionists. In fact, I think that
being a perfectionist is antithetical to being an entrepreneur. I am not a
perfectionist, I’m just really curious and have a big appetite for learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this “appetite for learning” stops me from focussing. I let myself become
distracted by adding new features to this blog, when instead I should zoom out
a bit and think about working towards a more substantial and meaningful goal,
to the exclusion of more minor goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that good entrepreneurs are very focussed, to a fault. I am not that
focussed. I am too distracted by life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a balancing act, there is a tension between being emotionally and
physically present with my family and friends, and ignoring as many things as
possible so that I can focus on doing something meaningful that is necessarily hard.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Technical/Web"/><category term="blog"/><category term="javascript"/><category term="self-reflection"/></entry><entry><title>Regrets Of The Dying</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/regrets-of-the-dying.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-02-01T22:52:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-02-01T22:52:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2021-02-01:/regrets-of-the-dying.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wish that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’d had the courage to live a life true to myself, not the life others expected of me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I hadn’t worked so hard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’d had the courage to express my feelings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I had stayed in touch with my friends.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’d let myself be happier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…the five most common regrets of terminally ill patients, as described by a
palliative care nurse&lt;sup id="sf-regrets-of-the-dying-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-regrets-of-the-dying-1" title="Source"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-regrets-of-the-dying-1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://bronnieware.com/blog/regrets-of-the-dying/"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-regrets-of-the-dying-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/></entry><entry><title>A List Of Unconnected Thoughts And Aphorisms</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-02-01T22:27:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-02-01T22:27:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2021-02-01:/a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do the people you care about love you back?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It does not matter how slowly you go as long as you do not stop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assume that nobody is going to help you, and nobody is going to stop you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Money is (just) fuel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets talk about the end. My current self, existing now, is to be seen in
    the context of my end, and my beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you want money, ask for advice. When you want advice, ask for money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You follow the rules of war for you, not your enemy. You fight by rules to
   keep your
   humanity.&lt;sup id="sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-1" title="source"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to be a top performer in any field you must become abnormal.
   Normal is average, which by definition, is far below the top! “We can always
   be average and do what’s normal. I’m not in this to do what’s normal.”
   –Kobe Bryant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Becoming Abnormally Good&lt;sup id="sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-2-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-2" title="source"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; at something:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No reasonable excuses - don’t make (reasonable) excuses that let you off the hook. You need the negative emotions that leads to inspired decision making.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not Worrying About What You Can’t Control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know it’s best to be genuinely friendly no matter who you’re trying to
    get information out of, thanks in part to the work of Hanns Scharff and a
    slew of studies on interrogation
    techniques&lt;sup id="sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-3-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-3" title="source"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.globalo.com/history-wwii-charlie-brown-franz-stigler-incident/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-2"&gt;&lt;a href="https://capitalandgrowth.org/answers/Article/3217401/Become-Abnormal"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-2-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-3"&gt;&lt;a href="https://psmag.com/social-justice/nazi-interrogator-revealed-value-kindness-84747"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-a-list-of-unconnected-thoughts-and-aphorisms-3-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/></entry><entry><title>Questions For Interesting Conversations</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/questions.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-02-01T22:05:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-02-01T22:05:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2021-02-01:/questions.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s the &lt;strong&gt;best piece of advice&lt;/strong&gt; you ever received?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What would you say to your &lt;strong&gt;18-year-old self&lt;/strong&gt; if you had a chat with them today?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever &lt;strong&gt;lost or rejected a friend&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tell me about &lt;strong&gt;a time when you changed your mind&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What have you been &lt;strong&gt;thinking about lately&lt;/strong&gt;? What’s on your mind?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you work in a language that’s not your mother tongue? &lt;strong&gt;What’s it like to live in translation&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is a &lt;strong&gt;choice between remembering and forgetting&lt;/strong&gt;, do you lean towards the side of forgetting?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Were you raised for &lt;strong&gt;autonomy or loyalty&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was there ever a moment where you thought, &lt;strong&gt;‘I’m giving up’&lt;/strong&gt; — what did you do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Was your identity given to you or chosen by you&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/></entry><entry><title>Live near the ocean</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/ocean.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-11-23T18:48:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-11-23T18:48:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2017-11-23:/ocean.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Being near water is&amp;nbsp;better.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;California&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="California" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1600px, (min-width: 1280px) 1300px, (min-width: 1024px) 1100px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/california3.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/california3.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/california3.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/california3.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/california3.jpg 1600w"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="California" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1600px, (min-width: 1280px) 1300px, (min-width: 1024px) 1100px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/california7.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/california7.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/california7.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/california7.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/california7.jpg 1600w"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="California" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1600px, (min-width: 1280px) 1300px, (min-width: 1024px) 1100px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/california9.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/california9.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/california9.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/california9.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/california9.jpg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Dorset&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Dorset" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1600px, (min-width: 1280px) 1300px, (min-width: 1024px) 1100px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/dorset.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/dorset.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/dorset.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/dorset.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/dorset.jpg 1600w"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="Dorset" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1600px, (min-width: 1280px) 1300px, (min-width: 1024px) 1100px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/beach.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/beach.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/beach.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/beach.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/beach.jpg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Acapulco&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Acapulco" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1600px, (min-width: 1280px) 1300px, (min-width: 1024px) 1100px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/mex1.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/mex1.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/mex1.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/mex1.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/mex1.jpg 1600w"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="Acapulco" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1600px, (min-width: 1280px) 1300px, (min-width: 1024px) 1100px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/mex2.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/mex2.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/mex2.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/mex2.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/mex2.jpg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Dublin&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Dublin" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1600px, (min-width: 1280px) 1300px, (min-width: 1024px) 1100px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/dublin.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/dublin.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/dublin.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/dublin.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/dublin.jpg 1600w"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="Dublin" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1600px, (min-width: 1280px) 1300px, (min-width: 1024px) 1100px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/dublin1.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/dublin1.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/dublin1.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/dublin1.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/dublin1.jpg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Netherlands&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Hague" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1600px, (min-width: 1280px) 1300px, (min-width: 1024px) 1100px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/hague.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/hague.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/hague.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/hague.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/hague.jpg 1600w"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="Hague" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1600px, (min-width: 1280px) 1300px, (min-width: 1024px) 1100px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/amsterdam3.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/amsterdam3.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/amsterdam3.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/amsterdam3.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/amsterdam3.jpg 1600w"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="Hague" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1600px, (min-width: 1280px) 1300px, (min-width: 1024px) 1100px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/amsterdam1.jpg" srcset="https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/amsterdam1.jpg 300w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/amsterdam1.jpg 600w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/amsterdam1.jpg 800w, https://johnmathews.is/images/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/amsterdam1.jpg 1600w"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="water"/></entry><entry><title>Corporate London</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/corporate.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-07-10T21:37:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-07-10T21:37:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2017-07-10:/corporate.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Reflections on 3 years living and working in&amp;nbsp;London&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="2014-2017"&gt;2014 - 2017&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having made arrangements to leave London, it seems like a reasonable time to
reflect on my time here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;London is a tough city to live in — it’s big enough that a sub 1-hour commute
is considered good, and it’s super expensive. My stay in London has been
defined by my quest to complete my graduate scheme and qualify as an accountant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first arrived I had no idea what London or working in a corporate would
be like. I was coming from academia, and my motivation for moving to finance
could be summed up in two points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand more about the 2008 financial crisis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get paid more for using mostly the same skills (math) as in engineering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t think there’s anything wrong with these motivations, but I should have
been making a long term career plan instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started my job I was surprised at the 6 weeks of induction and
hot-desking. Life as an auditor felt nomadic, as everyone would spend large
amounts of time at client’s offices, and no-one has their own desk in our
office. The only thing you really own is your knowledge and your network of relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2014, I arrived with a high opinion of my employer and the view that I would
be staying for several years. Having escaped the financial insecurity of
short-term research grants, I’d moved back to my home country to contribute to
the system that educated me. I was happy to have a regular job with a decent,
predictable salary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A phrase that kept coming to mind back then was “accountant factory”. Our
training materials were scripted and everything was a standardised process. We
were being processed. Graduates in, corporate accountants out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company is huge and so are the efficiencies and barriers to competition
that come with this. When I arrived I was impressed there were free biscuits,
and it felt presumptuous to put a meeting in someones diary. Now I ignore any
communications addressed to a mailing list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="accountant"&gt;Accountant&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The toughest experiences were related to the accountancy qualification. Naïvely
I had believed that the qualification wouldn’t be a big deal and I didn’t give
any thought to it when I applied — I just wanted to find out how banks worked.
If there were some exams to be done then it would be fine, I’d already achieved
a PhD and I would handle it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That turned out to be a mistake. A huge mistake. The alarm bells should have
rung louder when I realised most of my graduate colleagues had only applied so
that they could get the qualification (and were already intending to leave asap
afterwards). Doing the pre-course work before college wasn’t trivial. College -
I was being sent to a classroom again. We were being taken out of the office,
away from clients, and put in a classroom to prepare for these exams…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting a job that required becoming a chartered accountant, without
considering the effort and time involved to qualify was dumb. It’s an oversight
I find hard to believe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disappointment and sadness at having to study again was profound. The
teaching and assessment style was several steps behind what I’d become used to.
Compared to the depth, autonomy and research-focus of a doctorate, writing
cookie-cutter essays in time-pressured exams felt stupid. The exams were hard
and I failed several of them, probably because of my low morale whilst
revising. Retaking them required more weekends and annual leave being spent
away from my family, camped-out in libraries and offices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This required much patience and generosity from Ritsya, who having not seen me
for long periods during my doctorate expected us to have a more normal
lifestyle when we came to London. I found it miserable to pause my social life
and other interests whilst studying, and then I would try to rush back to them
when I had the time, knowing that soon I’d have to pause them again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I hadn’t already studied in Vienna, this process of working and studying in
London would have been exciting and felt valuable or special. I’d passed enough
exams though to know that they’re never as important as they’re made out to be,
and whatever it was that was missing from my life wasn’t going to be found in
another qualification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the upside though, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACA&lt;/span&gt; is the most practical qualification I’ve gained
and has taught me many useful aspects of business and finance. I’m glad to
finally see business not as some mysterious system but something attainable and understandable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="neighbourhood"&gt;Neighbourhood&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Living in London has also required a lot of time on trains — my door to desk
commute is about an hour each way, and I’ve never lived somewhere in London
that hasn’t felt transient. We’ve needed to live near a station and didn’t want
to commute more than an hour and that’s put us in neighbourhoods with other
young professionals who also don’t have long term plans (or financial ability)
to stay in the city. We’re all looking to move on and move up as fast as
possible.  I want to leave London partly because there are so many people with
the same attitudes and priorities as my own…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="corporate-culture"&gt;Corporate Culture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in the office I spent the first few months figuring out how people were
organised, how teams operated and how decisions were made. I think it took me
about a year to feel like I understood how things really worked, and 1.5 years
to feel like I could do all aspects of my job with certainty. There is a
difference between how things are spoken about, and how things actually happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My experience has been that performance is all that matters and behaviour is
defined by self-interest. I don’t think this is different from previous
environments I’ve worked in — academia isn’t any different&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and the
construction industry certainly isn’t. I wonder if the only way people can
endure it is if they’ve not experienced anything else, or think it normal, or
necessary. I find myself wishing we could be kinder to each other, and that we
could create structures that incentivise mutual support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corporate finance usually appears clean and well presented. Its people appear
dependable and capable. The culture is sanitised and there’s a lot of pressure
to conform - you can see it in the clothes and accessories we wear and the
jokes we tell each other in the canteen. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came to see my office as a glass and steel cathedral. I read about the Middle
East, and migrants arriving in Europe, and tower blocks burning, and felt
really disconnected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the high regard with which we hold ourselves, we don’t ask each other
how we can help. Maybe we are too busy, or feel powerless to help. Apparently
we do not know how to help, despite our wealth, talents, education and connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember watching a man leave the office one day and thought that if he gave
his whole career and left his firm after decades of service, there would be
nothing left to identify him after a few weeks. The work will always get done.
Market forces will dictate how the business adapts and grows. The City rolls on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Publications trump almost all other metrics, and the incentives to
  publish quantity over quality are such that risky or slow research is
  inexcusable. The metrics used to standardise success and allocate resources
  can be subverted just as well in academia as in any other industry. What
  management measures, the team prioritises. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="Career"/><category term="Corporate"/><category term="London"/></entry><entry><title>Move</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/move.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-07-08T12:26:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-07-08T12:26:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2017-07-08:/move.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Training&amp;rsquo;s&amp;nbsp;over&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="ambition"&gt;Ambition&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I was 15, one of my ambitions has been to be an entrepreneur. I used to joke with my dad about buying him a nice boat one day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life so far has been predominantly about education, and that stage is over now. I’m walking away from what I’ve come to see as a lifestyle and career that has too many contradictions, it doesn’t make sense to live like this. Ultimately I want to develop multiple sources of passive income. I want to create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="summer-2017"&gt;Summer 2017&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last few months have been intense, with some weeks leaving me feeling ambitious and energetic, and others feeling anxious and overwhelmed. I need to get better at defining a goal, taking the quickest path there, and ignoring interesting distractions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ritsya is brave enough and imaginative enough to force me to think big and consider how to live a better life. My biggest fear is that I screw it up, shooting myself in the foot and Ritsya and my daughter also. We were headed safely to an unremarkable existence and it would be terrible to swap that for something worse. That won’t happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that I make better decisions and produce my best work under pressure, I thrive when I’m perceived as an underdog. I need to accept this without using it as a reason to be foolish. Whilst I don’t have a clear plan, or direction, or goal, (I have many of them) I’ve got skills and I want to see what I can make. I’ll never do my best work, using my most productive combination of skills and experiences, if I’m a cog in someone else’s machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s safer being an employee than self-employed. I guess the price of removing self-employment risks is the difference between the value you generate for your employer and what you’re paid. I think those risks are overpriced, and most people are more capable than they realise. Sometimes you have to walk into a situation to find out how to make the most of it. And sometimes you have to leave a place in order to gain perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="autumn-2016"&gt;Autumn 2016&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year my boss gave me some advice that was supposed to be encouraging. I’d requested to reduce my involvement with some stuff that was unrelated to my job so that I could contribute more to my team and still maintain some semblance of a work/life balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My boss was pretty clear that reducing my involvement in the extra stuff would not be possible. During our conversation he advised me not to worry about how much I contributed to the team because “the work will get done anyway”. This was meant to be encouraging, but instead removed any conviction that the work I did was important.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="Lifestyle"/></entry><entry><title>Flee</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/flee.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-07-04T08:42:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-07-04T08:42:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2017-07-04:/flee.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Summer children 
squeal and shriek, &lt;br/&gt;
Watch wars. &lt;br/&gt;
Excitement mounts. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How exotic. 
Unexpectedly, &lt;br/&gt;
Death arrives. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grow-up&lt;br/&gt;
Grow old&lt;br/&gt;
Face death &lt;br/&gt;
Evade evil.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t tire. 
World is fragile.&lt;br/&gt;
Towers burn,&lt;br/&gt;
Bridges bludgeon,&lt;br/&gt;
Markets stab. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Got to get out.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="Poetry"/></entry><entry><title>London Rent vs. London Salaries</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/london.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-05-12T22:55:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-05-12T22:55:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2017-05-12:/london.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Living in London is only financially possible if you are either single or household income is more than&amp;nbsp;£60k/year.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Living in London is expensive, everyone in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; knows this. Everyone knows that this is mostly due to the price of property, which we all enjoy talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve lived here for 3 years now, and when my wife and I were both working we lived comfortably. Two incomes under one roof is just fine. Not as fine as in many other cities, but reasonable. Just over a year ago my first child was born, and now that my wife’s maternity pay has ended we are a single income household. This is not fine. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though I earn almost £50k/year, and any salary increase will be taxed at 40%, I cannot cover essential day-to-day costs. I’m in the 40% tax bracket, and my basic monthly outgoings exceed my monthly take home pay by £400. If my employer wanted to pay me enough to cover essential costs, it would cost them approximately double the shortfall due to tax. None of this makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salaries and living expenses have become really disconnected. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most people the most obvious way to increase wealth is to buy property. Mortgage repayments are cheaper than rent, and the value of the property increases over time. Double win. But there is a big hurdle to overcome before this is possible - saving money for a deposit on a house is often impossible without external help (i.e. the “Bank of Mum and Dad”), because so much of the money earnt must be spent on rent first. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a trap. Repayments on a mortgage are cheaper than paying rent, but you cannot save enough for a deposit because;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;so much of your salary goes to paying rent&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the average cost of a &lt;em&gt;flat&lt;/em&gt; in London is 500k&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, which means a 5% deposit is £25k — which is a higher deposit than you would need anywhere else in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt;, despite being the place you are least able to accumulate it. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if my partner went back to work and we put our baby in childcare? Childcare is not cheap, and working would need to bring in more than the cost of childcare. This requires a higher than average salary from a graduate job, (which is the life stage when people might reasonably start having children), so unless both parents are unusually high earners that option isnt viable either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Living in London is only financially possible if you are either single or household income is more than £60k/year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’d be lucky to find a 1 bedroom flat for less than £1000/month &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href="http://www.rightmove.co.uk/house-prices/London.html"&gt;Rightmove&lt;/a&gt;, an estate agent with some useful price statistics. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="London"/><category term="Rent"/></entry><entry><title>How to wake up early</title><link href="https://johnmathews.is/how-to-wake-up-early.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2016-08-06T22:04:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-08-06T22:04:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.is,2016-08-06:/how-to-wake-up-early.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For years I’ve wished that I could wake up early and use the quiet
pre-breakfast hours for distraction-free productivity. And for years I
have spectacularly failed at this. I love the quiet, distraction-free
hours at the end of the day too, as well as waking up slowly.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many famous leaders and politicians are known to start their days early,
and I would like to be able to do this too. After years of trying and
failing, I have had a break-through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The secret of waking up early is this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Become a parent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the first couple of months with a new-born:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will be well-practiced at quickly waking up at previously
    unthinkable times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will be used to operating on less sleep than you ever thought possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your beautiful child will become a reliable alarm clock, waking you
    up at the crack of dawn with cute smiles and increasingly insistent
    demands that you get up, play and make breakfast.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have the freedom to begin sleeping and working when you want, I still believe this is a great option. I bashed out a PhD in 3.5 years during which I usually woke up late and began to work around lunch time! - Glorious autonomy! &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Journal"/><category term="Productivity"/><category term="Sleep"/></entry></feed>