<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>John Mathews Blog - JohnMathews.eu - Non-technical/Learning</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/feeds/non-technical/learning.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://johnmathews.eu/</id><updated>2021-01-18T11:51:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Why I Want To Write Regularly</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/why-i-want-to-write-regularly.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-18T11:51:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-18T11:51:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-18:/why-i-want-to-write-regularly.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As you can see, I’ve recently started writing more frequently. I want to do
this because I often have thoughts which I’d like to explore and develop
further, but rarely do. I find writing hard because it forces me to organise my
thoughts and look at how substantial they really are, or aren’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is truth in the saying that “to know a thing you need to be able to teach
it &lt;sup id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1" title="wikipedia article, and some extenal validation"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
“, and writing well has several similarities to teaching. Can I really copy a
collection of thoughts from my head to yours?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember watching Inception and hearing that the most resilient parasite is
an idea. I think that’s mostly true, and the older I get the more I believe
that ideas matter&lt;sup id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2" title="and also, that asking the right question is more important than finding the right answer. I guess asking the right question is always necessary, but finding the right answer is only sometimes sufficient. Sometimes you can get the answer a bit wrong if you asked the right question, and still get enough benefits to avoid the problem."&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. They have so many
subtle consequences. They are the first
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domino_effect"&gt;dominos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t expect writing regularly to become a permanent habit - it doesn’t need
to be. But I do want to focus on it for a while so that I become significantly
better. It’s a skill that has too many benefits to be ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realised that the blogs I remembered most were focussed and unapologetic
about their priorities. Most of them have a lot of text and do not focus on
design. They make it easy to read text, and don’t spend time or attention on
header images or styling. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I redesigned this blog I had default settings that asked me to supply an
image for each post, and for a summary, and a suggested tweet. None of it was
necessary, and whilst they all tried to make the blog better they ended up
making it worse because they added complexity and distracted from the main thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These features are still there if I want to use them, but they are not set up
to be used by default anymore. They’ve been moved to the background, and if I
forget they exist then that is &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt; - it just shows they weren’t as important in
practice as I thought they’d be when I was &lt;a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/yak_shaving"&gt;Yak
Shaving&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/You_aren%27t_gonna_need_it"&gt;You Ain’t Gonna Need
It&lt;/a&gt;, mate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1"&gt;wikipedia
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Learning_by_teaching"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;, and some
&lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20210118112910/https://digest.bps.org.uk/2018/05/04/learning-by-teaching-others-is-extremely-effective-a-new-study-tested-a-key-reason-why/"&gt;extenal
validation&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2"&gt;and also, that asking the right question is more
important than finding the right answer. I guess asking the right question is
always necessary, but finding the right answer is only sometimes &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Necessity_and_sufficiency"&gt;sufficient&lt;/a&gt;.
Sometimes you can get the answer a bit wrong if you asked the right question,
and still get enough benefits to avoid the problem. &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/></entry><entry><title>Using RSS</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/using-rss.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-14T16:52:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-14T16:52:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-14:/using-rss.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;h3 id="updated-10-feb-2021"&gt;Updated: 10 Feb 2021&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found a &lt;a href="https://brandur.org/fragments/rss-abandon"&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; which is
surprisingly similar to my thoughts on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; feeds, but better presented and
thought through. The post mentions the idea that “&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; is about capturing the
long tail of blogs that don’t post frequently”
&lt;sup id="sf-using-rss-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-using-rss-1" title="https://marco.org/2013/03/26/power-of-rss"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This idea crystalised why I was so glad I’d started using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; feeds
again. If readers use &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt;, then authors don’t need to concern themselves with
attention. This removes pressure on the author to post
frequently and lets them focus on quality over quantity. News feeds and ad
supported platforms have fundamentally different mechanics and incentives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; I can let good quality content come to me, on its own schedule. I
don’t need to remember to look for it, and the authors don’t need to remind me
that they exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="google-reader"&gt;Google Reader&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; is a very effective way of having good quality information
come to you. Back in 2008, I used to use Google Reader to subscribe to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt;
feeds. I was an aspiring photographer back then and I remember being subscribed
to around 80 blogs. Each day I’d read articles from whoever had posted
something new, without needing to visit their websites or remember who they are
or that I’d subscribed to their blog. The authors didn’t need to optimize their
output according to an opaque and changing algorithm either - they didn’t need
to optimize article length, tags, post frequency, image inclusion or linked
content. They could write how they wanted to, which I suspect leads to higher
quality content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="social-media"&gt;Social Media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years later Google Reader was closed down, presumably because using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt;
didn’t fit with Googles advertising model. I was unaware of it at the time but
I imagine it sent shockwaves through blogging communities and probably upended
many businesses. I mostly stopped reading blogs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook was growing fast, Instagram felt new and exciting, and content was
moving onto ‘platforms’, or into walled gardens. And as they kept on growing
the average quality of the content decreased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter is like this now I think. There are some real diamonds to be found from
time to time, but there’s a lot of mud too. Mostly its just mud, but the
occasional diamond can have outsized benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; isn’t like this. I choose the contents of my ‘news feed’, and
each article can be much longer than a Tweet, or a caption to a photo, or a
status update. It’s hard to write well and to create an interesting or useful blog
post, and that makes it harder to dilute quality with entertaining
distractions. I have complete control about what content I see, and I can
change it whenever I want. The process is designed around me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="reeder5"&gt;Reeder5&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used &lt;code&gt;netNewsWire&lt;/code&gt; for a few weeks, but it couldn’t sync between my laptop
and phone, so I bought &lt;code&gt;Reeder 5&lt;/code&gt;. It’s got a few unusual design patterns, but
 it works well and has all the features I want. I’ve been unsubscribing from
 email newsletters and subscribing to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; feed instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It keeps my inbox quieter, and it feels good to have a ‘separation of
 concerns’. It makes it easier to read interesting content without being distracted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-using-rss-1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://marco.org/2013/03/26/power-of-rss"&gt;https://marco.org/2013/03/26/power-of-rss&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-using-rss-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/></entry><entry><title>How I learnt to code</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/How-I-learnt-to-code.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-12-01T13:51:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-01T13:51:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-12-01:/How-I-learnt-to-code.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;4 years ago I started learning how to code, and it was &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; difficult! It’s
still difficult, but I now have a collection of tools and perspectives that
make it less daunting (more on that below). Leveling up requires one more
abstraction to wrap my head around, or one more &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; to understand. I can do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I don’t think it needed to be so difficult, so now I’m building &lt;a href="https://codeschoolmeta.com"&gt;Code
School Meta&lt;/a&gt; to make it easier to learn how to code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning to code has been fun, ultimately successful, and life changing (hello
job security!) but at the beginning it was sooo slow, and super tricky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember feeling like an imposter, and thinking that I was definitely not a
real developer - I hadn’t taken any classes in computer science. I felt like I
knew almost nothing about anything. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process began with Pandas, a (&lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt;) Python analytics library. Spreadsheets
were slowing me down at work, and I was bored. I found this &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/5JnMutdy6Fw"&gt;great
tutorial&lt;/a&gt; by Brandon Rhodes. From there I found
out about Jupyter Notebooks, and then I found about Github pages and how to
make a blog using &lt;a href="https://blog.getpelican.com/"&gt;pelican&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That led to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; (and also JavaScript, which I tried very hard to avoid
for as long as possible). I felt like a monkey bashing a keyboard as I tried to
make &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; elements do what I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Git was next, but I found this &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/rys-git-tutorial.html"&gt;amazing tutorial&lt;/a&gt;
to help me learn. It made Git seem &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt;, and also helped &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; make more
sense too. Bonus!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suddenly realized that great learning materials are crucial if I was going to
keep momentum and keep on enjoying the thrill of seeing the computer do
something I hadn’t made it do before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now I’m now working on &lt;a href="https://codeschoolmeta.com"&gt;Code School: Meta&lt;/a&gt;. It’s
an online community to make it easier to teach yourself how to code - less
confusion about how to get started or what to learn next, more encouragement,
and lots of high quality resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’d like to know more, please &lt;a href="https://codeschoolmeta.com"&gt;check it out&lt;/a&gt;
and sign up for updates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/></entry></feed>