<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>John Mathews - Non-technical/Learning</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/feeds/non-technical/learning.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://johnmathews.eu/</id><updated>2021-05-17T13:15:07+02:00</updated><entry><title>Building A Story Brand</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/building-a-story-brand.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-05-17T13:15:07+02:00</published><updated>2021-05-17T13:15:07+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-05-17:/building-a-story-brand.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;div class="toc"&gt;&lt;span class="toctitle"&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/span&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#premise"&gt;Premise&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#stories"&gt;Stories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#hero"&gt;Hero&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#problem"&gt;Problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#guide"&gt;Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#recap"&gt;Recap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#plan"&gt;Plan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#a-call-to-action"&gt;A Call To Action&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#what-is-at-stake"&gt;What is at stake?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#avoid-failure"&gt;Avoid Failure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#end-with-success"&gt;End with Success&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#people-want-your-brand-to-participate-in-their-transformation"&gt;People want your brand to participate in their transformation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#implementation"&gt;Implementation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#websites"&gt;Websites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#corporations"&gt;Corporations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#marketing-roadmap"&gt;Marketing Roadmap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h1 id="premise"&gt;Premise&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People want to &lt;mark&gt;survive and thrive&lt;/mark&gt;. They are the main character
   in the movie of their own life and they have problems. Life is busy and hard
   and complicated and they don’t want to waste energy figuring out if you can
   help them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good marketing shows that the product has an &lt;mark&gt;obvious benefit&lt;/mark&gt; for
   the customer. How does your product improve someones ability to “survive and thrive”?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cut through noisy and challenging world by having a super &lt;mark&gt;quick and
   easy to understand message&lt;/mark&gt;. Don’t be clever, be clear. Don’t make the
   customer spend calories trying to figure out how they will benefit from your product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stories are intuitive and leverage many psychological features. They organise
   information in an intuitive way and are a great way to combat noise and gain
   attention. &lt;mark&gt;People are compelled to pay attention until all the “story gaps”
   have been closed&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could a caveman look at your website and answer these questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do you &lt;strong&gt;offer&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will it &lt;strong&gt;improve&lt;/strong&gt; my life?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the &lt;strong&gt;next steps&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Story Gaps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A gap between a character and what they want. Will they find their way to success, overcome their challenges, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cadence and momentum are defined by the creation and fulfillment of story gaps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you fail to define something that the customer wants, you fail to open a story gap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This makes the story uninteresting because there isn’t a question that requires an answer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Story gaps work because we want things to resolve. It’s like singing Twinkle
Twinkle Little Star but stopping before the “are” on the last line. You need to
hear the last note of the melody for the tune to feel complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pare down the customers desire to a single focus. Make your brand known for
single specific desire and helping people get it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t clutter the story by diluting the hero’s desire with other desires. You
can eventually develop subplots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Apple&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Apple released the Lisa computer in 1983, Jobs bought a 9 page ad in the
New York times listing the computers features. When Jobs returned to Apple
after being fired, (and after partly founding Pixar, which tells stories) Apple
became a customer centric company, and their marketing was about the customers.
9 pages became 2 words - “Think Different”. A message about their customers, and
their customers need to survive and thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple isn’t the hero in the “Think Different” brand, the customer is. It’s the
same with Nike - the athletes are the heros, and you can become a (hero) athlete
with Nike’s help. Apple plays a role more like Q in James Bond, giving the hero
what they need to win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="stories"&gt;Stories&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;Hero&lt;/strong&gt; → has a &lt;strong&gt;Problem&lt;/strong&gt; → and meets a &lt;strong&gt;Guide&lt;/strong&gt; → who gives them a &lt;strong&gt;Plan&lt;/strong&gt; → and calls them to &lt;strong&gt;Action&lt;/strong&gt; → that ends in &lt;strong&gt;Success&lt;/strong&gt; → and helps them avoid &lt;strong&gt;Failure&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="story stages" class="image-process-article-inline-image" loading="lazy" sizes="(min-width: 1536x) 1020px, (min-width: 1280px) 850px, (min-width: 1024px) 800px, (min-width: 768px) 800px, (min-width: 640px) 800px, 100vw" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/building-a-story-brand/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/7storystages.png" srcset="https://johnmathews.eu/images/building-a-story-brand/derivatives/article-inline-image/300w/7storystages.png 300w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/building-a-story-brand/derivatives/article-inline-image/600w/7storystages.png 600w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/building-a-story-brand/derivatives/article-inline-image/800w/7storystages.png 800w, https://johnmathews.eu/images/building-a-story-brand/derivatives/article-inline-image/1600w/7storystages.png 1600w" style="margin-left: 0;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="hero"&gt;Hero&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The customer, not you. You are the guide. The customer is the main character in
their life and is battling internal and external adversity it order to survive
and thrive. Heroes have weaknesses, the guide is usually the strongest character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A story &lt;mark&gt;starts with a character who wants to overcome &lt;em&gt;external&lt;/em&gt; challenges&lt;/mark&gt; that
pose &lt;em&gt;internal&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;philosophical&lt;/em&gt; problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your first task is to create a story gap that implicitly asks “Will the hero get
what they need?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to define the character’s ambition at the beginning, so that the
audience knows what’s at stake and what kind of a story it is. This messaging
implicitly tells them how they could benefit and why they should spend attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="problem"&gt;Problem&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customers are more motivated to solve internal problems than external.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you &lt;mark&gt;identify a customer’s problem then you show that you understand&lt;/mark&gt; them. This
is a great hook because they will then relate to your narrative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The more we talk about the problems our customers are experiencing, the more
interest they will have in our brand.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every story needs a villain, which is the personified problem. The germs are
personified, envy is personified, etc. The diminished social status is
personified by someone with more status being villainized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;villain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;should be &lt;strong&gt;relatable&lt;/strong&gt; - readers should recognize that the villain should be disdained.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;should be a &lt;strong&gt;root source&lt;/strong&gt; - frustration is what the villain makes us feel. High taxes are the cause, and are therefore the villain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;should be &lt;strong&gt;singular&lt;/strong&gt; - just one villain, keep it simple to cut through the noise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;should be &lt;strong&gt;real&lt;/strong&gt; - don’t be a fear monger. Fight a real problem on behalf of your customers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three types of &lt;strong&gt;problem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;External&lt;/strong&gt; - A barrier to stability that must be removed - My business isn’t growing fast enough, profits are too small.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Internal&lt;/strong&gt; - I have self-doubt. Do I have what it takes to succeed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Philosophical&lt;/strong&gt; - I deserve to be successful, my hard work should be rewarded. Failure would be unjust.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt; The &lt;strong&gt;villain&lt;/strong&gt; initiates an &lt;strong&gt;external&lt;/strong&gt; problem that causes the
&lt;strong&gt;hero&lt;/strong&gt; to encounter an &lt;strong&gt;internal&lt;/strong&gt; problem that is &lt;strong&gt;philosophically wrong&lt;/strong&gt;
or unjust. &lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the external problem is to manifest the internal problem.
Customers should recognise and relate to both types of problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put your product in the context of a type of survival they they want. Otherwise
there isn’t a story gap. Translate the &lt;strong&gt;external problem&lt;/strong&gt; into several
survival categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resources&lt;/strong&gt; - Conserving or accumulating money or time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social&lt;/strong&gt; - Gaining status or a social network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generosity&lt;/strong&gt; - Most people are not as Darwinian as we’ve been led to believe, they want to be empathetic and caring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose&lt;/strong&gt; - Give customers an opportunity to be generous and participate in something greater than themselves - “the chief desire of man is not pleasure, but meaning”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The only reason that customers buy is because the external problem that your product would solve
is causing an &lt;strong&gt;internal frustration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you &lt;mark&gt;identify and articulate that frustration&lt;/mark&gt;, and then &lt;mark&gt;clearly, confidently and
repeatedly offer to solve it along with the original external problem&lt;/mark&gt; then you bond with
your customer. You’ll have positioned yourself more deeply into their internal
narrative and substantially differentiated your brand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Philosophical problems&lt;/strong&gt; are important because people want to be involved in
something larger than themselves. It adds depth and meaning. Representing (and
solving) a philosophical problem gives customers a way of expressing themselves
that they wouldn’t otherwise have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can &lt;strong&gt;resolve all three problems in the same transaction&lt;/strong&gt;, then
customers will experiences a wave of relief and pleasure, and love your brand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Anakin Skywalker blows up the Deathstar by aiming the perfect shot, he
defeats the external problem (the enemy army), his internal problem (self doubt)
and the philosophical problem (injustice).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Your &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CTA&lt;/span&gt; is the action that must be taken to close the final story
gap&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Checklist:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is there a &lt;strong&gt;single villain&lt;/strong&gt; that your brand stands against?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What &lt;strong&gt;external problem&lt;/strong&gt; is that villain causing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The internal problem is probably found by considering how the external problem makes your customer feel?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is unjust or wrong about the  suffering caused by that villain?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt; Our hero is being challenged - will they be able to solve their problem?
The only way to find out is to engage with the brand. &lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="guide"&gt;Guide&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customers aren’t looking for another hero, they are the hero in their life. They
are the main character which the movie of their life revolves around. They’re
looking for a guide because they need help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A persons life is made up of many acts - “doorways of no return”. Each life is
unique but we all have commonalities. We are all on transformational journeys
with common elements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Story chapters are book-ended by events. These events are always instigated by external
actors or events beyond their control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heroes need a guide who is &lt;strong&gt;trustworthy&lt;/strong&gt; and earns &lt;strong&gt;respect&lt;/strong&gt;. If they didn’t
need a guide their wouldn’t be narrative, or a problem. Everyone is looking for a guide to help
them solve their problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;&lt;em&gt;We wake up each morning self-identifying as a hero.
We are troubled by internal, external and philosophical issues. We know
that we can’t solve our issues on our own.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This insight has consequences and raises questions, it means our story isn’t
about us but about others. We can aspire to be someone else’s guide, but not
their hero. It shows why the search for meaning is innate, but can only be
resolved by becoming a servant or guide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stop losing sleep over the success of your company and start losing sleep over
the success of your customers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In stories, heroes are not the strongest characters, they have self-doubt and are
often ill-equipped. They are often reluctant, and are thrown into the story by
external events. They are “chosen by destiny.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the guide has already “been there and done that.” They have already
conquered the hero’s internal and philosophical challenges in their own backstory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The guide is the one with authority which the authority instinctively recognises
and accepts. The guide has much more authority than the hero but the main
character is still the hero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Those who realize that the epic story of life is not about them end up winning
in the end. This is paradoxical. Those who think they are a hero and win usually
end up being remembered as a villain.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Characteristics of a guide&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empathy and Authority are a precise one-two punch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;1. Empathy → Understanding → Trust&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we empathise with customers we show that we understand them, and
understanding produces trust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People want to be &lt;em&gt;seen, heard and understood&lt;/em&gt;. This is the essence of empathy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key phrases in your marketing copy could be:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;we understand how it feels to …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;em&gt;no-one should have to experience …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;em&gt;like you, we are frustrated by …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expressing empathy isn’t difficult. Once you’ve identified your customers
internal problem, let them know that you understand and would like to help them
find a resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brains like to conserve calories, energy, effort, time, so when a customer
realises they have a lot in common with a brand, they fill in any gaps with
trust. A customer will “batch” their thoughts, which means they are thinking in
chunks rather than in details. Commonality, whether in music taste or values, is
a powerful marketing tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;2. Authority&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt; No one likes a know-it-all and no one wants to be preached at… But
people &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; want you to establish &lt;strong&gt;competence&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When looking for a guide, a hero trusts someone who has &lt;em&gt;demonstrable
competence&lt;/em&gt;. The guide should have some serious experience helping other heroes
win their day, but doesn’t need to be perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;strong&gt;four ways to add authority (competence) to your marketing&lt;/strong&gt; without
being arrogant:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Testimonials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logos&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Statistics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Awards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meeting a brand is like meeting a person,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can you help them live a &lt;strong&gt;better life&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can they &lt;strong&gt;associate their identity&lt;/strong&gt; with your brand?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can I &lt;strong&gt;respect&lt;/strong&gt; this brand?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can I &lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; this brand?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1 id="recap"&gt;Recap&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We started the narrative by identifying something that the hero wants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then we created intrigue and tension by defining the hero’s problem. The audience wants to know if we can help them overcome the problem!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then we introduced ourselves as the guide and established authority, empathy and trust.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What next? Making a purchase always involves a small risk of wasting money. This
risky element makes a purchase somewhat similar to starting a relationship.
There is a potential downside, the customer might end up feeling foolish and
regret their decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine a customer trying to cross a river to get to their purchase. They can
hear the sound of a waterfall downstream. If they try to cross it by making a
purchase then there is a chance that something bad could happen. Put stones in the
river so they know how to safely walk across, step by step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stones are the plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="plan"&gt;Plan&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a movie, the guide gives the hero a plan. The plan tightens the focus of
the movie and creates a “path of hope” for the hero that might, possibly, lead
to the resolution of the hero’s problems. It creates a story gap and implicitly
creates questions that the audience want to be answered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt; A good plan &lt;strong&gt;removes risk&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;explains what to do&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/mark&gt; If we
don’t guide customers, they experience a little bit of confusion and use that
confusion as an excuse to not purchase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though the setup or purchase or after-purchase steps are obvious to us,
they are not obvious to customers. Give them a plan and they will feel more
confident about purchasing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heroes trust a guide who has a plan. People are looking for a philosophy then
can embody, or a series of steps they can take to solve their problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customers want to know where you can take them. Unless you can take them
somewhere they want to go, why would they listen? The marketing goal is that
every potential customer knows where we want to take them. Define a desire for
your customer, and your marketing story will have a powerful hook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There are two kinds of plan. Both work by earning trust and offering the
customer a clear path to stability.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agreement Plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Process Plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Process Plan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The minimal (3 - 6) steps required to buy &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; get benefit from the
product after purchase, or a mixture of both. E.g.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make an appointment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allow us to create a customized plan.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let’s execute the plan together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A process plan removes confusion from the customers journey. When they see the
plan they think “oh that’s not difficult, I can do that” and then they purchase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A post-purchase process plan would alleviate confusion about how the customer
would &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt; the product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Agreement Plan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agreement plans are about &lt;mark&gt;alleviating fears&lt;/mark&gt;. It’s a list of agreements you make
with the customer that are designed to alleviate their fears of doing business
with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An agreement plan can also work to &lt;mark&gt;highlight shared values&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Give the agreement plan a good name and it can increase the perceived value of
your product. “the easy-installation plan”, “your best nights sleep ever”, etc.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agreement plans can work in the background, they don’t have to be on the landing
page, though they could be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make an agreement plan by creating a list of all the things a customer could be
fearful about when doing business with you (haggling for price, interacting with
a pushy salesman, buying a defective product) and then create an promise
that would nullify that fear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="a-call-to-action"&gt;A Call To Action&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, we’ve defined a &lt;strong&gt;desire&lt;/strong&gt;, identified their &lt;strong&gt;challenges&lt;/strong&gt;,
&lt;strong&gt;empathized&lt;/strong&gt; with them, established our &lt;strong&gt;competency&lt;/strong&gt; and given them a
&lt;strong&gt;plan&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Characters only take action when challenged by an outside force.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In stories, characters never take action on their own, there is always an
outside force that challenges them to make a change. We are the outside force
that guides them to success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heroes need to be challenged by external forces. Calls to action should be
clear, and should be repeated over and over. Above the fold, in the center of
the page. Also in the navbar. And also repeatedly as they scroll down the page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customers are bombarded with adverts and calls-to-action all day every day. They
are ignoring things and filtering out noise all the time. So don’t be shy or
subtle. Be very clear. Make it very simple. If you have confidence in your
product, make confident calls to action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Direct Calls&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Buy Now&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Schedule an Appointment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Order Now&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Call Today&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Register Today&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repeat the same (singular, simple) call to action again and again down the page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Transitional Calls&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download our free &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; guide to growing your business&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free information - advice, guides, whitepapers, reports&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Giving something away for free&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Testimonials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Samples&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free-trials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good transitional &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CTA&lt;/span&gt; does three things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Establish expertise and authority, and positions you as a leader&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create reciprocity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positions you as a guide&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use both kinds in your messaging, and customers will understand (without burning
calories) what you (the guide) want them to do (the plan) to solve their problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heroes don’t take action by themselves, they &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be challenged. It’s just not
interesting if the hero can solve their own problems without an externality,
this is just how stories (and humans) work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="what-is-at-stake"&gt;What is at stake?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stories live and die by a single question; “What is at stake?” If nothing can be
gained or lost then nobody cares. If there is nothing at stake in the story then
there is no story, it’s just not interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is no benefit to buying the product, then why buy it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have to show the customer the cost of &lt;em&gt;not buying&lt;/em&gt; the product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="avoid-failure"&gt;Avoid Failure&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story remains intersting as long as the hero is teeting on the edge between
success and failure. A hero in a story only ever has 2 motivations - to escape
pain or experience something good. Life is like that too, our desire to avoid
pain motivates us to make a change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There needs to be meaninful consequential stakes in the story, otherwise it isnt
interesting. Each scene needs to move the hero either closer to or further from
their tragic external threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A brand needs to answer the “what if I don’t buy” question because otherwise the
customer can ask “so what?” - the stakes need to be clearly, simply, concisely
communicated. Probably stake, not stakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can do it humorously. and only lights - it is salt to add flavor, not a
main-serving of fear. Compare the fear to the peace and stability that could be
achieved. If you show the pain “before” and contrast it to peace and stability
“after” then you’ve also opened and closed a story loop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blog titles, email subjects, headlines, can all contain elements of potential
failure to convey a sense of urgency. Bring up the negative stakes a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People fear losing \&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(100 more than they desire gaining \\)&lt;/span&gt;100 - loss and pain is
more motivating than reward and peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let the reader know they are vulnerable to a threat. “X% of Y get W”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let the reader know that since they &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; vulnerable, they should take action
   to reduce their vulnerability. “Make sure this doesnt happen and protect yourself”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give the customer a clear, concise simple plan to reduce their
   vulnerability. “We offer the thing you need”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Challenge people to take the next step right now. the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CTA&lt;/span&gt;. “Call us today to
   arrange an appointment”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agitate a bit of fear, and then return the reader to peace and prosperity, all
within 1 or 2 paragraphs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What are you helping your customers avoid?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s only a little salt to add flavor. If its too little, customers wont know
why your product is important. If its too strong it’ll be off-putting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="end-with-success"&gt;End with Success&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans are looking for resolution to their external, internal and philosophical
problems. They can achieve this though (among other things) status,
self-realization, self-acceptance, and transcendence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you product or service can help people achieve this then it should be a
central part of your brand promise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People want to change their lives and be taken into a new reality. Tell them how
their lives are going to improve - peace, status, confidence, abilities, preparedness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People want a vision of a happy ending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;We’re going to put a man on the moon”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
vs.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;em&gt;“We would like a highly competitive and successful space program”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Answer each of these questions with a “before your brand” column and an “after your brand” column:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do they have?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are they feeling?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What’s an average day like?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is their status?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will show you how your customers lives will change and give lots of good
copy for your marketing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talk about the end vision really clearly. And use images of
happy/successful/powerful people enjoying the benefits of your product. Say the
benefits loudly, confidently, clearly, simply, repeatedly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talk about your end-vision for their lives once they’ve benefited from your service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Show the customer a vision of how great their life will be if they do business
with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the end of the story should be a list of resolutions to your
customers problems. How do they feel and how have philosophical/justice
questions been resolved?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stories usually end in one of three ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The hero &lt;strong&gt;gains status&lt;/strong&gt; or power&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offer access - get a free coffee.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offer a premium - skip the line.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create scarcity - write “limited” on it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identity association - wear a Rolex and be associated with what Rolex stands for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The hero &lt;strong&gt;becomes whole&lt;/strong&gt; by being unified with someone&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The hero needed something they couldn’t get themselves, and external provision has saved them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reduced anxiety, or more security.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reduces effort, or more convenience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More time, reaches an aspirational lifestyle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The hero has some internal realisation (coming of age) that gives them
   &lt;strong&gt;confidence to overcome&lt;/strong&gt; their circumstances or  internal shortcomings and become “whole” and wise.
   They can achieve inner peace and know they reached their potential.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inspiration - chariots of fire - you can also run really fast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Acceptance - fashion brands doing positive body image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transcendence - greater purpose and meaning - fair-trade coffee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1 id="people-want-your-brand-to-participate-in-their-transformation"&gt;People want your brand to participate in their transformation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A hero needs someone else to step into their life, tell them they are different
and special and better. That someone is a guide, that’s you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Offering an aspirational identity to our customers adds a lot of value to our
products and services. Realise that your customers want to transform and improve themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;People are looking for a guide&lt;/strong&gt;. Everybody wants to change either into someone
better or someone more self-accepting. You are helping them become wiser,
fitter, more equipped, accepted or peaceful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What does the customer want to become?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what is their aspirational identity?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what kind of person do they want to be?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do they want their friends to talk about them?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a guide is a position of the heart, not just a marketing tactic. Lose
sleep over your customers problems instead of your business. Commit to solving
their internal, external and philosophical problems, and give them a vision to
aspire to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customers needs to be told very clearly how much other customers have changed
and how far journey has taken them. Usually, the hero is deeply flawed right up
until the final climactic scene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not all elements of a story should be used evenly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="implementation"&gt;Implementation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id="websites"&gt;Websites&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Above the fold, use the one-liner. It’s one sentence saying what’s in it for the customer. What
    problem do you solve, what aspirational identity do you offer. It will also
    give customers words they can use to tell others about your business.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Big obvious calls to action, in multiple places. Don’t be timid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customers read in a Z shape.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People don’t read websites, they scan them. Repeat the important things
    so that they are understood by quick readers. Use very few words.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The fewer words you use, the more likely they will be read.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perhaps 10 sentences on the entire landing page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increase the amount of text towards the bottom. The top needs to be short,
    fast, positive and obvious.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a “read more” button to expand longer text, then customers have the
    option if they want.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Place a transitional call to action next to the main call to action. “Download
    a guide” next to “buy now”. Put the transitional &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CTA&lt;/span&gt; in less bright colors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeatedly ask people to buy, twice above the fold and then in subsequent
    sections. If you don’t tell people what to do then they won’t do it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include images of success - people enjoying the benefits - resolved problems,
    aspirations achieved, closed story loops. A sense of health, well-being and satisfaction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The flow of the landing page should follow the StoryBrand framework, albeit
    not exactly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="corporations"&gt;Corporations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not applicable, but if you’re a manager and you give your team a narrative they
can fit themselves into I guess they’re going to have more purpose, confidence
and meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="marketing-roadmap"&gt;Marketing Roadmap&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a one-liner. Say how can you make their lives better in an engaging way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a lead generator and get qualified email addresses. A guide, a free 30
   minute consultation, a voucher, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An automated email campaign - a weekly email, 3 with nurturing advice and
   then 1 with a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CTA&lt;/span&gt;. All automated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collect and tell stories of transformation. Almost all stories are about the
   transformation of the hero. Tell this story and people will understand what
   you are offering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a system that generates referrals. If word of mouth is so powerful,
   incentivize it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;One-liner&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one-liner is a statement. It could be more than 1 sentence, but its supposed
to be super short. It’s the equivalent of a logline for a movie. Keep editing it
until you find a version that works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Memorizie it, put it on your website, and include it in every piece of marketing collateral you create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You could tell this to anybody and they would understand what you do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Helps people realize they need your services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provoke imagination and intrigue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It should include:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A character (“A busy mom”, “A retiree”)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A problem - don’t miss an opportunity to talk about a customers
    challenges. Define the problem as vitally important, it opens a story
    gap and customers will want you to close it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A plan - hint at it. You can’t explain it all in a one-liner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Success - paint an image of life after a custom has bought your services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Example answers to the question “What do you do?”:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;We provide busy moms with a short, meaningful workout they can use to stay
healthy and have renewed energy” vs “I run a gym”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;We help retired couples who want to escape the cold avoid the hassle of a
second mortgage while still enjoying the warm beautiful weather of Florida
during the winter” vs “I got involved in real estate a few years ago and when we
had out second kid we moved to Florida and then….”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Create a lead generator&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A guide to download.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A free webinar or online course.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Software demo or free trials.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free samples.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Live events.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No need to reinvent the wheel, what are others doing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can give away quite a lot of value that is easy to consume in an email or
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; - people will consume it quickly and will probably be happy to pay for a
chance to learn in a more thorough and detailed context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Downloadable guides etc should be about 3 pages in length.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be generous, explain the “why” and give away as much of the “how” as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;An automated email campaign&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if customers don’t click the links in the email, they keep seeing your
brand and they become familiar with it. When they need your services you will be
the go-to brand in their mind. The relationship and association is already built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nurturing emails and Call-To-Action emails - 3:1 - put real value in the
nurturing emails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t be passive in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CTA&lt;/span&gt; emails - you want them to buy, so tell them,
repeatedly, and make it easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Talk about a problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Describe a product you offer that solves the problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Describe what life can look once the customer has bought your product and
   solved their problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Call the customer to an action that leads directly to a sale.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar to a nurturing email, a direct action email also describes a problem and
a solution, but in the direct email the solution is a product you sell and there
is a strong call to action. A lot of the content can be taken from the
StoryBrand script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Collect and tell stories of transformation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A great testimonial gives customers the gift of going second, and lowering the
riskiness of purchasing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good testimonial will:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;showcase the value you create&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the results&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what transformation has occurred?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few things are more important to a good story than a hero that experiences an
external and internal and philosophical transformation. This is because everyone
desires to be transformed in someway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People love businesses that help them transform in some way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questions to get a good testimonial:
1. What was the problem you were having before you discovered our product?
2. What did the frustration feel like as you experienced that problem?
3. What was different about out product?
4. Take us to the moment when you realized our product was actually working to
   solve your problem?
5. Tell us what life looks like now that your problem is solved or being solved?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Create a system that incentivizes referrals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify your existing ideal customers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give them a reason to talk about you - create a video or a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt; that a
   customer can send to their friends to help them introduce your brand and
   explain the value you deliver.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offer a reward - a discount, more access, extra samples, etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.3/latest.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';

    var configscript = document.createElement('script');
    configscript.type = 'text/x-mathjax-config';
    configscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'none' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        availableFonts: ['STIX', 'TeX']," +
        "        preferredFont: 'STIX'," +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";

    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(configscript);
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/><category term="reading"/><category term="marketing"/><category term="communication"/><category term="book"/></entry><entry><title>Notes From An Interview With Geoffrey Hinton</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/notes-from-an-interview-with-geoffrey-hinton.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-02-01T22:17:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-02-01T22:17:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-02-01:/notes-from-an-interview-with-geoffrey-hinton.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read the literature, but don’t read too much&lt;/strong&gt; of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust your intuitions&lt;/strong&gt;, because if you don’t trust them then there’s no point&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="quo"&gt;‘&lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This person is either drunk or stupid&lt;/strong&gt;‘ - feedback on one of his papers that went on to become significant &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For creative researchers; read a bit of the literature and notice something that you think everybody is doing wrong. (I guess &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GH&lt;/span&gt; is contrarian in this sense)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look for a problem that doesn’t feel &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt;. Then figure out how to do it right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people tell you that your (contrarian) approach is just no good, just keep at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either your intuitions are good or they’re not. If they are good then you should follow them and you will eventually be successful. If they are bad then it doesn’t matter what you do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might as well trust your intuitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you try to replicate a published paper you discover all the little tricks needed to make it work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never stop programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you give a student something to do and they are a bad student then they’ll come back and say it didn’t work. They’ll say this because of some little decision they made which they didn’t realise was crucial. But if you give it to a good student, you can give them anything and they will come back and say it works&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read enough so that you start developing intuitions, and then trust your intuitions and go for it! - Don’t be too worried if everybody else says its nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think it’s a really good idea, and others tell you its complete nonsense, then you know you are really onto something!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One example of this is when Ramford and I first came up with variational methods, I sent a mail explaining it to a former student, who showed it to his colleagues. He told me that they said ‘Either this guy is drunk or he is just stupid’. They really really thought is was nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe that is partly because of how i explained it - I explained it in intuitive terms, but when you have what you think is a good idea and other people think it is complete rubbish, that is the sign of a really good idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See if you can find an advisor who has beliefs similar to your own, because if you work on stuff that your adviser feels deeply about, then you’ll get a lot of good advice and time from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read enough so that you can &lt;em&gt;trust your intuitions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/></entry><entry><title>Mental Models I Used To Use</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/mental-models-i-used-to-use.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-20T16:48:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T16:48:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-20:/mental-models-i-used-to-use.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The rules&lt;sup id="sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-1" title="or policies"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and mental models that helped me
succeed in one season or phase of life may not be the best for the next phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a list of a few mental models I remember being concious of in previous
years. Probably I’ve already forgotten some.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Always ask “why…”&lt;/em&gt;. Be obsessive about this. It’s going to make things
    harder for a while before things get easier. You’ll find difficult answers
    that you otherwise wouldn’t. If you’re only concerned with the present then
    its true that ignorance is bliss, but otherwise it’s a liability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;What if…”&lt;/em&gt; is another good question to ask a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adapt&lt;/em&gt; to the situation, don’t make it adapt to you if you have any
    choice. Be kind of like water, going around things and through the gaps.
    Look for the edges and the gaps, the parts that aren’t well known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Let people talk&lt;/em&gt; as much as they want to. Shut up and listen. If they
    mean you harm or don’t respect you then it’ll become more obvious the more
    they keep talking. If they mean you well or they’re saying something
    useful, you will benefit more from letting them talk more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inversion&lt;/em&gt; - it can be hard to know if you should do something, but how
    would you feel if you didn’t do it, or if it didn’t happen?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Regrets are inevitable&lt;/em&gt;, everyone has them. Same as making mistakes. Let
    your regrets be for things that you did do, and not what you didn’t do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are willing to try something, fail at it, and still be glad that you
    tried, then you should almost definitely do it. Commit to it and enjoy the
    experience! Don’t be scared, or at least, be scared &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; optimistic and
    happy&lt;sup id="sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-2-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-2" title="Courage isn’t the absence of fear. It’s being scared and doing     the right thing anyway."&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is beauty and luxury in being in such a bad spot that you are backed
    into a corner with seemingly no way out. Things become black and white,
    instead of shades of gray, and that will make priorities and options much
    clearer. You are likely to work very efficiently and effectively in this
    scenario, and you will learn important things about yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I’m older and I have responsibilities, I can’t ever let things
become so bad that a situation becomes black and white. I have to
navigate a world of grays. If they do become black and white, I’ll
already have a long list of failings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was younger, things were more fragile. My resources were smaller and
things could quickly flip from good to bad. Enjoy the few benefits that a
situation like that gives, because (hopefully) once its gone its gone for good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to solve a problem is to prevent it from occurring in the first
    place. Succeeding at this will bring its own challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take responsibility for things you are not responsible for, kind of. Do it
    deliberately and for your own benefit, but don’t forget that you are only
    pretending that it’s your responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do this, you will force yourself to understand a situation more
deeply and from other peoples perspectives. This will let you learn faster
and help you in future. Keep this at arms length though - it’s make-believe
and you need to be able to switch it on and off. It’s a toy for you to play
with. This seems to be what “extreme responsibility” is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think its important to have mental models that you’re comfortable with,
because it lets you make decisions quickly and consistently. But understand
that &lt;a href="https://fs.blog/2015/11/map-and-territory/"&gt;the map is not the
territory&lt;/a&gt;, and these are just
tools in a toolbox.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-1"&gt;or policies &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-2"&gt;Courage isn’t the absence of fear. It’s being scared and doing
    the right thing anyway. &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-2-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/></entry><entry><title>Why I Want To Write Regularly</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/why-i-want-to-write-regularly.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-18T11:51:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-18T11:51:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-18:/why-i-want-to-write-regularly.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve started writing more frequently. I want to do this because I often have
thoughts which I’d like to explore and develop further but rarely do. Writing
forces me to organise my thoughts and look at how substantial they really are,
or aren’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is truth in the saying that “to know a thing you need to be able to teach
it” &lt;sup id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1" title="Wikipedia article, and some external validation."&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
, and writing well has several similarities to teaching. Can I really copy a
collection of thoughts from my head to yours?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Powerful ideas are resilient and have many consequences. The older I get the more I believe
that ideas matter&lt;sup id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2" title="A complimentary notion is that asking the right question is more important than finding the right answer. I guess asking the right question is always necessary, but finding the right answer is only sometimes sufficient. Sometimes you can get the answer a bit wrong if you asked the right question, and still get enough benefits to avoid the problem."&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. They have so many
subtle consequences. They are the first
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domino_effect"&gt;dominos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t expect writing regularly to become a permanent habit - it doesn’t need
to be. But I do want to focus on it for awhile so that I become significantly
better. It’s a skill that has too many benefits to be ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blogs I remember most are focussed and unapologetic about their priorities.
Most of them have a lot of text and do not focus on design. They make it easy
to read content and don’t spend time or attention on header images or styling. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I redesigned this blog I had default settings that asked me to supply an
image for each post, and for a summary, and a suggested tweet. None of it was
necessary and whilst they all tried to make the blog better they ended up
making it harder to write. These peripheral features added complexity and
distracted from the main thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They’re are still there if I want to use them but they are not set up
to be used by default anymore. They’ve been moved to the background and if I
forget they exist then that’s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt; - it just shows they weren’t as important in
practice as I thought they would be. I was probably just having fun adding new
features and working out how to build them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/You_aren%27t_gonna_need_it"&gt;You Ain’t Gonna Need
It&lt;/a&gt;, mate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1"&gt;Wikipedia
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Learning_by_teaching"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;, and some
&lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20210118112910/https://digest.bps.org.uk/2018/05/04/learning-by-teaching-others-is-extremely-effective-a-new-study-tested-a-key-reason-why/"&gt;external
validation&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2"&gt;A complimentary notion is that asking the right question is more
important than finding the right answer. I guess asking the right question is
always necessary, but finding the right answer is only sometimes &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Necessity_and_sufficiency"&gt;sufficient&lt;/a&gt;.
Sometimes you can get the answer a bit wrong if you asked the right question,
and still get enough benefits to avoid the problem. &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/></entry><entry><title>Using RSS</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/using-rss.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-14T16:52:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-14T16:52:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-14:/using-rss.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Updated: 10 Feb 2021&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found a &lt;a href="https://brandur.org/fragments/rss-abandon"&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; which is
surprisingly similar to my thoughts on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; feeds, but better presented and
thought through. The post mentions the idea that “&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; is about capturing the
long tail of blogs that don’t post frequently”
&lt;sup id="sf-using-rss-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-using-rss-1" title="https://marco.org/2013/03/26/power-of-rss"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This idea crystalised why I was so glad I’d started using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; feeds
again. If readers use &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt;, then authors don’t need to concern themselves with
attention. This removes pressure on the author to post
frequently and lets them focus on quality over quantity. News feeds and ad
supported platforms have fundamentally different mechanics and incentives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; I can let good quality content come to me, on its own schedule. I
don’t need to remember to look for it, and the authors don’t need to remind me
that they exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="google-reader"&gt;Google Reader&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; is a very effective way of having good quality information
come to you. Back in 2008, I used to use Google Reader to subscribe to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt;
feeds. I was an aspiring photographer back then and I remember being subscribed
to around 80 blogs. Each day I’d read articles from whoever had posted
something new, without needing to visit their websites or remember who they are
or that I’d subscribed to their blog. The authors didn’t need to optimize their
output according to an opaque and changing algorithm either - they didn’t need
to optimize article length, tags, post frequency, image inclusion or linked
content. They could write how they wanted to, which I suspect leads to higher
quality content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="social-media"&gt;Social Media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years later Google Reader was closed down, presumably because using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt;
didn’t fit with Googles advertising model. I was unaware of it at the time but
I imagine it sent shockwaves through blogging communities and probably upended
many businesses. I mostly stopped reading blogs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook was growing fast, Instagram felt new and exciting, and content was
moving onto ‘platforms’, or into walled gardens. And as they kept on growing
the average quality of the content decreased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter is like this now I think. There are some real diamonds to be found from
time to time, but there’s a lot of mud too. Mostly its just mud, but the
occasional diamond can have outsized benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; isn’t like this. I choose the contents of my ‘news feed’, and
each article can be much longer than a Tweet, or a caption to a photo, or a
status update. It’s hard to write well and to create an interesting or useful blog
post, and that makes it harder to dilute quality with entertaining
distractions. I have complete control about what content I see, and I can
change it whenever I want. The process is designed around me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="reeder5"&gt;Reeder5&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used &lt;code&gt;netNewsWire&lt;/code&gt; for a few weeks, but it couldn’t sync between my laptop
and phone, so I bought &lt;code&gt;Reeder 5&lt;/code&gt;. It’s got a few unusual design patterns, but
 it works well and has all the features I want. I’ve been unsubscribing from
 email newsletters and subscribing to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; feed instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It keeps my inbox quieter, and it feels good to have a ‘separation of
 concerns’. It makes it easier to read interesting content without being distracted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-using-rss-1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://marco.org/2013/03/26/power-of-rss"&gt;https://marco.org/2013/03/26/power-of-rss&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-using-rss-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/></entry><entry><title>How I learnt to code</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/How-I-learnt-to-code.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-12-01T13:51:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-01T13:51:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-12-01:/How-I-learnt-to-code.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;4 years ago I started learning how to code, and it was difficult! It still is
difficult, but I now have a collection of tools and perspectives that make it
less daunting. Leveling up requires one more abstraction
to wrap my head around, or one more &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; to understand. I can do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I don’t think it needed to be so difficult, so now I’m building &lt;a href="https://codeschoolmeta.com"&gt;Code
School Meta&lt;/a&gt; to make it easier to learn how to code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning to code has been fun, ultimately successful, and life changing (hello
job security!) but at the beginning it was sooo slow, and super tricky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imposter syndrome is real, and I definitely felt it. I hadn’t taken any classes
in computer science, and I felt like I knew almost nothing about anything. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process began with Pandas, a (&lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt;) Python analytics library. Spreadsheets
were slowing me down at work, and I was bored. I found this &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/5JnMutdy6Fw"&gt;great
tutorial&lt;/a&gt; by Brandon Rhodes. From there I found
out about Jupyter Notebooks, and then I found about Github pages and how to
make a blog using &lt;a href="https://blog.getpelican.com/"&gt;pelican&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That led to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; (and also JavaScript, which I tried very hard to avoid
for as long as possible). I felt like a monkey bashing a keyboard as I tried to
make &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; elements do what I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unusally, I think Git was next. Mainly because I found this &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/rys-git-tutorial.html"&gt;amazing
tutorial&lt;/a&gt; to help me learn. It made Git seem &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt;,
and also helped &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; make more sense too. Bonus!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suddenly realized that great learning materials are crucial if I was going to
keep momentum and keep on enjoying the thrill of seeing the computer do
something I hadn’t made it do before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now I’m now working on &lt;a href="https://codeschoolmeta.com"&gt;Code School: Meta&lt;/a&gt;. It’s
an online community to make it easier to teach yourself how to code - less
confusion about how to get started or what to learn next, more encouragement,
and lots of high quality resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’d like to know more, please &lt;a href="https://codeschoolmeta.com"&gt;check it out&lt;/a&gt;
and sign up for updates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/><category term="learning"/><category term="code"/></entry><entry><title>Reading: April 2018</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/reading-april-2018.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2018-06-04T15:52:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-06-04T15:52:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2018-06-04:/reading-april-2018.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A list of interesting things. June&amp;nbsp;2018&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="articles"&gt;Articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fs.blog/mental-models/"&gt;Mental models&lt;/a&gt; A comprehensive list organised around different disciplines. It a long read but probably one of the most easy to apply and tangibly useful articles I’ve read recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/vb.html"&gt;Life is short&lt;/a&gt; - Is life actually short, or would we always want more time, no matter how much we could have?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.eugenewei.com/blog/2018/5/21/invisible-asymptotes"&gt;Invisible asymptotes&lt;/a&gt; - A well written and long look at various facets of business strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://osam.com/Commentary/factors-from-scratch"&gt;Factors from scratch&lt;/a&gt; - Investing: A unified framework to explain how factors work. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://kottke.org/18/06/a-sad-update-about-a-scissors-maker-that-went-viral"&gt;This is tragic&lt;/a&gt; - “…But I do think this highlights the potential disconnects between mental health &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; business, publicity &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; success, and success &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; happiness. The internet can seem so intimate but ultimately it’s a thin view of an individual’s or company’s reality.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://statico.github.io/vim3.html"&gt;Vim&lt;/a&gt; after 15 years&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2018/03/27/a-complete-guide-to-cyprocurrency-regulations-around-the-world.html?__source=sharebar%7Clinkedin&amp;amp;par=sharebar"&gt;Cryptocurrency regulations around the world&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.lrb.co.uk/v40/n13/john-lanchester/after-the-fall"&gt;On the 2008 financial crisis&lt;/a&gt; - “I’m not sure if it’s philosophically possible for an action to be both necessary and a disaster, but that in essence is what the bailouts were.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="podcasts"&gt;Podcasts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/whatbitcoindid"&gt;Jill Carlson&lt;/a&gt; on the “What Bitcoin Did” podcast. “For the first time there is no longer a monopoly on the creation of value or monetary systems, that is really What Bitcoin Did.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/deVoaRTfVqs"&gt;Georges St-Pierre&lt;/a&gt; on the Joe Rogan podcast. A long and candid conversation from one of the world’s best athletes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/KqhRZfKRriU"&gt;Ricardo Spagni&lt;/a&gt; a.k.a Fluffypony on Monero vs Bitcoin, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EOS&lt;/span&gt;, the current bear market, Tari, and ASICs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="resources"&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lots of &lt;a href="https://vincentarelbundock.github.io/Rdatasets/datasets.html"&gt;data sets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/><category term="reading"/><category term="learning"/></entry><entry><title>I’m a chartered accountant</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/chartered.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-10-19T21:56:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-10-19T21:56:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-10-19:/chartered.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve qualified as a chartered accountant and will soon become a member of the Institute of Chartered Accountants in England and&amp;nbsp;Wales&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year I qualified as a chartered accountant. Qualification requires
passing 15 exams and gaining 3150 hours of work experience. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To celebrate passing your exams and verify your success, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ICAEW&lt;/span&gt; print the
names of everyone who passed in an advert in the Financial Times. This happened
for me on the 26 January.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="exam pass list in the financial times" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/exam_pass_list.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/><category term="ICAEW"/><category term="ACA"/><category term="Accounting"/></entry><entry><title>Spare time</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/spare-time.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2016-08-13T21:15:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-08-13T21:15:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2016-08-13:/spare-time.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a list of interests I want to consider pursuing. I wrote it when I began to study for my last set of exams and my mind filled with things I’d rather be doing instead. Some of these interests are just me reacting to having no spare time for a few months, but others are decent goals and projects. Temporarily losing my spare time made me value it more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="free-time" src="/images/spare_time.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote this post so that I could compare what I thought was important when I was busy to when I wasn’t. Writing the list allowed me to move on without forgetting. Here’s a break down of each item:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Run 10k in 50 minutes” - This is easier than I imagined. When I wrote the
     list I could barely run 2k without stopping, but intended to go for a
     weekly run whilst studying. I’ve struggled to stay energetic and healthy
     during previous exam phases, so now I have a rule that I must do some mild
     exercise even if I think I can’t spare the time. I find running really
     lowers my stress levels, and increasing my heart rate and working up a
     sweat lets me sleep better and concentrate for longer. After a few weeks of
     minimal running, I could run 5k easily. If I kept at it, 10k in 50 mins
     would be easy. But point 2…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Be Insanity strong” - As in, do the Insanity workout programme. Again. I thought about it and decided to do P90x instead. Week 1 is going great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Read the bible habitually” - When I was 17 I found out about Jesus and
    became a Christian. In the months and years after that I’d regularly read my
    bible almost every day and pray a lot. I wanted to understand, so I set a
    goal of 5 chapters each day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read through the new testament repeatedly and read most of the old
testament during this time. I knew the scriptures well enough that a lot of
sermons became boring and obvious - I’d already studied the bible passage
being used. During this time I remember being aware that the way I thought
was different to how it would have been otherwise. My perspectives were
long-term and less me focused. I thought about what I was reading instead
of the days’ headlines or social chatter. I remember enjoying the benefits
and thinking that I should keep this habit. The reasons why I think
Christianity is so wonderful are well summarised in &lt;a href="http://messages.destinyedinburgh.com/sermon/the-gospel-we-preach-a-message-for-leaders"&gt;this
sermon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s now 10 years later, and whilst my convictions are strong, my knowledge
of the bible is sadly pretty fuzzy. My thinking is clouded by the
perspectives contained in the media I consume and the conversations I’m
part of. I strongly suspect I would be acting and thinking differently if I
read my bible more, but I don’t know what those differences would be.
Trouble is, it’s often not obvious what the immediate benefits of
reading the bible are, you have to work for it a bit. Praying for help is
effective. The books in the bible were written to last through the ages and
across all cultures, so it’s not surprising that they’re not as easy to
read as something written for an English speaker in a hurry. I should stop
being in a hurry, and stop prioritising only quantifiable goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Think more” - On a similar note to 3, but less supernatural. If I spent
    less time consuming content and a little more looking around me or walking,
    I reckon I’d be more self-aware and make better decisions. This would
    probably lead to a happier, more satisfying life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Pray more” - I don’t know why, but the creator of the universe wants me to
    talk and share my life with him. He cares about me. This makes no sense to
    me, at all. If I was God, I would not go out of my way to consider the views
    and concerns of a very flawed human. But when I pray, my prayers are very
    often answered. I should ask him about this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Amazon seller?” - Amazon have this “Fulfilled by Amazon” service,
     which means you don’t even need to hold the stock you want to sell.
     If I choose the right products, import them cheaply from China and
     reselling  them on Amazon at a profit, I end up quids in for minimal
     effort and manageable risk. Sounds intriguing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Blog about interesting data” - Here I am, blogging. I should stick
    to the main topic and get technical. I was inspired by this
    &lt;a href="http://www.curiousgnu.com/"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Finish Coursera” - The data science specialization is great! It’s in R, and I want to focus on Python, but I’d still like to do it. I need to consider the opportunity cost of the time committed, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Read for fun, history, fiction” - When I started my job, in April 2014, I
    was half way through &lt;a href="https://read.amazon.co.uk/kp/embed?asin=B00796LLLK&amp;amp;asin=B00796LLLK&amp;amp;preview=newtab&amp;amp;linkCode=kpe&amp;amp;ref_=cm_sw_r_kb_dp_GP2Rxb3Q8MYC4"&gt;Savage
    Continent&lt;/a&gt;,
    which is an eye-opening and eye-watering history of Europe in the years
    after World War 2. I see Europe through different eyes because of it.
    However I only got half way though, and since April ‘14 I never felt I had
    the free time or energy to pick it back up. This should change. When I was a
    researcher, and when I was a student, I had so much more opportunity to
    develop my own pursuits. Since entering the corporate world, I find myself
    fighting a war of attrition to exert my personality onto my lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read for fiction… I’m unconvinced. What do you have at the end of
it? What can you do with it? Maybe I’ve just been reading the wrong authors,
but I’m going to leave this for now. Sure, you could gain an appreciation of
a different time or place, but that appreciation comes via the fictional
characters and events, its secondary. What about abstract constructs,
perspectives, morals… things that history books are ill-suited for? Great
fiction would be essential for exploring these. But for now, I’ll prioritise
point 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" class="my-5" frameborder="0" height="550" src="https://read.amazon.co.uk/kp/card?asin=B00796LLLK&amp;amp;asin=B00796LLLK&amp;amp;preview=inline&amp;amp;linkCode=kpe&amp;amp;ref_=cm_sw_r_kb_dp_GP2Rxb3Q8MYC4" style="max-width: 100%; float:middle" width="336"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Do a photography project” - This I would love to do, but probably won’t.
     It would be a luxury, and the opportunity cost would be too great right
     now. I’d like to shoot a series of black and white portraits, and turn them
     into large prints. I think good portrait photography is uniquely impactful
     and moving, choosing B&amp;amp;W removes distractions and leaves a subjects
     humanity more exposed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Have a list of business/product ideas” - There’s no excuse for this
     one, anyone can have several good ideas. It’s turning them into
     reality that takes skill. Need to have the ideas first, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Do a law &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MOOC&lt;/span&gt;” - i.e Study particular areas of law, in my own time
     and at my own pace. I studied a tiny bit of law during the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACA&lt;/span&gt;, and
     realised employment law or contract law could be really useful.
     (Same for the tax system - another surprise). We only had a brief
     introduction though, so if I could find the time I’d like to know more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Do an InfoSec or Network Security &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MOOC&lt;/span&gt;” - Its super interesting,
     but not likely to be a good use of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Learn to fight - Krav Maga / &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MMA&lt;/span&gt;” - Ever since watching The Bourne
     Identity I’ve wanted to learn Krav Maga, and &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/LybrzdG96_8"&gt;Georges
     St-Pierre&lt;/a&gt; made me want to train
     for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MMA&lt;/span&gt;. For now though, I’ll do P90x. I can reconsider in 90 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class="relative" style="padding-top: 56.25%"&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen="" class="absolute inset-0 w-full h-full" frameborder="0" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/u0_8dzaNxhg"&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Get out of London” - My contract ends in April 2017, next summer
     will be a crossroads. I hate the commute, I hate being constantly
     rushed. Living in other cities has been a lot more pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/><category term="Habits"/><category term="Advice"/><category term="Reflection"/></entry></feed>