<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>John Mathews - Non-technical/Learning</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/feeds/non-technical/learning.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://johnmathews.eu/</id><updated>2021-02-01T22:17:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Notes From An Interview With Geoffrey Hinton</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/notes-from-an-interview-with-geoffrey-hinton.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-02-01T22:17:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-02-01T22:17:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-02-01:/notes-from-an-interview-with-geoffrey-hinton.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read the literature, but don’t read too much&lt;/strong&gt; of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust your intuitions&lt;/strong&gt;, because if you don’t trust them then there’s no point&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="quo"&gt;‘&lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This person is either drunk or stupid&lt;/strong&gt;‘ - feedback on one of his papers that went on to become significant &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For creative researchers; read a bit of the literature and notice something that you think everybody is doing wrong. (I guess &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GH&lt;/span&gt; is contrarian in this sense)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look for a problem that doesn’t feel &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt;. Then figure out how to do it right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people tell you that your (contrarian) approach is just no good, just keep at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either your intuitions are good or they’re not. If they are good then you should follow them and you will eventually be successful. If they are bad then it doesn’t matter what you do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might as well trust your intuitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you try to replicate a published paper you discover all the little tricks needed to make it work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never stop programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you give a student something to do and they are a bad student then they’ll come back and say it didn’t work. They’ll say this because of some little decision they made which they didn’t realise was crucial. But if you give it to a good student, you can give them anything and they will come back and say it works&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read enough so that you start developing intuitions, and then trust your intuitions and go for it! - Don’t be too worried if everybody else says its nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think it’s a really good idea, and others tell you its complete nonsense, then you know you are really onto something!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One example of this is when Ramford and I first came up with variational methods, I sent a mail explaining it to a former student, who showed it to his colleagues. He told me that they said ‘Either this guy is drunk or he is just stupid’. They really really thought is was nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe that is partly because of how i explained it - I explained it in intuitive terms, but when you have what you think is a good idea and other people think it is complete rubbish, that is the sign of a really good idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See if you can find an advisor who has beliefs similar to your own, because if you work on stuff that your adviser feels deeply about, then you’ll get a lot of good advice and time from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read enough so that you can &lt;em&gt;trust your intuitions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/></entry><entry><title>Mental Models I Used To Use</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/mental-models-i-used-to-use.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-20T16:48:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T16:48:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-20:/mental-models-i-used-to-use.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The rules&lt;sup id="sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-1" title="or policies"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and mental models that helped me
succeed in one season or phase of life may not be the best for the next phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a list of a few mental models I remember being concious of in previous
years. Probably I’ve already forgotten some.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Always ask “why…”&lt;/em&gt;. Be obsessive about this. It’s going to make things
    harder for a while before things get easier. You’ll find difficult answers
    that you otherwise wouldn’t. If you’re only concerned with the present then
    its true that ignorance is bliss, but otherwise it’s a liability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;What if…”&lt;/em&gt; is another good question to ask a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adapt&lt;/em&gt; to the situation, don’t make it adapt to you if you have any
    choice. Be kind of like water, going around things and through the gaps.
    Look for the edges and the gaps, the parts that aren’t well known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Let people talk&lt;/em&gt; as much as they want to. Shut up and listen. If they
    mean you harm or don’t respect you then it’ll become more obvious the more
    they keep talking. If they mean you well or they’re saying something
    useful, you will benefit more from letting them talk more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inversion&lt;/em&gt; - it can be hard to know if you should do something, but how
    would you feel if you didn’t do it, or if it didn’t happen?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Regrets are inevitable&lt;/em&gt;, everyone has them. Same as making mistakes. Let
    your regrets be for things that you did do, and not what you didn’t do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are willing to try something, fail at it, and still be glad that you
    tried, then you should almost definitely do it. Commit to it and enjoy the
    experience! Don’t be scared, or at least, be scared &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; optimistic and
    happy&lt;sup id="sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-2-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-2" title="Courage isn’t the absence of fear. It’s being scared and doing     the right thing anyway."&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is beauty and luxury in being in such a bad spot that you are backed
    into a corner with seemingly no way out. Things become black and white,
    instead of shades of gray, and that will make priorities and options much
    clearer. You are likely to work very efficiently and effectively in this
    scenario, and you will learn important things about yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I’m older and I have responsibilities, I can’t ever let things
become so bad that a situation becomes black and white. I have to
navigate a world of grays. If they do become black and white, I’ll
already have a long list of failings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was younger, things were more fragile. My resources were smaller and
things could quickly flip from good to bad. Enjoy the few benefits that a
situation like that gives, because (hopefully) once its gone its gone for good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to solve a problem is to prevent it from occurring in the first
    place. Succeeding at this will bring its own challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take responsibility for things you are not responsible for, kind of. Do it
    deliberately and for your own benefit, but don’t forget that you are only
    pretending that it’s your responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do this, you will force yourself to understand a situation more
deeply and from other peoples perspectives. This will let you learn faster
and help you in future. Keep this at arms length though - it’s make-believe
and you need to be able to switch it on and off. It’s a toy for you to play
with. This seems to be what “extreme responsibility” is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think its important to have mental models that you’re comfortable with,
because it lets you make decisions quickly and consistently. But understand
that &lt;a href="https://fs.blog/2015/11/map-and-territory/"&gt;the map is not the
territory&lt;/a&gt;, and these are just
tools in a toolbox.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-1"&gt;or policies &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-2"&gt;Courage isn’t the absence of fear. It’s being scared and doing
    the right thing anyway. &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-mental-models-i-used-to-use-2-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/></entry><entry><title>Why I Want To Write Regularly</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/why-i-want-to-write-regularly.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-18T11:51:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-18T11:51:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-18:/why-i-want-to-write-regularly.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve started writing more frequently. I want to do this because I often have
thoughts which I’d like to explore and develop further but rarely do. Writing
forces me to organise my thoughts and look at how substantial they really are,
or aren’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is truth in the saying that “to know a thing you need to be able to teach
it” &lt;sup id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1" title="Wikipedia article, and some external validation."&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
, and writing well has several similarities to teaching. Can I really copy a
collection of thoughts from my head to yours?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Powerful ideas are resilient and have many consequences. The older I get the more I believe
that ideas matter&lt;sup id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2" title="A complimentary notion is that asking the right question is more important than finding the right answer. I guess asking the right question is always necessary, but finding the right answer is only sometimes sufficient. Sometimes you can get the answer a bit wrong if you asked the right question, and still get enough benefits to avoid the problem."&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. They have so many
subtle consequences. They are the first
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domino_effect"&gt;dominos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t expect writing regularly to become a permanent habit - it doesn’t need
to be. But I do want to focus on it for awhile so that I become significantly
better. It’s a skill that has too many benefits to be ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blogs I remember most are focussed and unapologetic about their priorities.
Most of them have a lot of text and do not focus on design. They make it easy
to read content and don’t spend time or attention on header images or styling. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I redesigned this blog I had default settings that asked me to supply an
image for each post, and for a summary, and a suggested tweet. None of it was
necessary and whilst they all tried to make the blog better they ended up
making it harder to write. These peripheral features added complexity and
distracted from the main thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They’re are still there if I want to use them but they are not set up
to be used by default anymore. They’ve been moved to the background and if I
forget they exist then that’s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt; - it just shows they weren’t as important in
practice as I thought they would be. I was probably just having fun adding new
features and working out how to build them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/You_aren%27t_gonna_need_it"&gt;You Ain’t Gonna Need
It&lt;/a&gt;, mate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1"&gt;Wikipedia
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Learning_by_teaching"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;, and some
&lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20210118112910/https://digest.bps.org.uk/2018/05/04/learning-by-teaching-others-is-extremely-effective-a-new-study-tested-a-key-reason-why/"&gt;external
validation&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2"&gt;A complimentary notion is that asking the right question is more
important than finding the right answer. I guess asking the right question is
always necessary, but finding the right answer is only sometimes &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Necessity_and_sufficiency"&gt;sufficient&lt;/a&gt;.
Sometimes you can get the answer a bit wrong if you asked the right question,
and still get enough benefits to avoid the problem. &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/></entry><entry><title>Using RSS</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/using-rss.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-14T16:52:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-14T16:52:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-14:/using-rss.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Updated: 10 Feb 2021&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found a &lt;a href="https://brandur.org/fragments/rss-abandon"&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; which is
surprisingly similar to my thoughts on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; feeds, but better presented and
thought through. The post mentions the idea that “&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; is about capturing the
long tail of blogs that don’t post frequently”
&lt;sup id="sf-using-rss-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-using-rss-1" title="https://marco.org/2013/03/26/power-of-rss"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This idea crystalised why I was so glad I’d started using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; feeds
again. If readers use &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt;, then authors don’t need to concern themselves with
attention. This removes pressure on the author to post
frequently and lets them focus on quality over quantity. News feeds and ad
supported platforms have fundamentally different mechanics and incentives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; I can let good quality content come to me, on its own schedule. I
don’t need to remember to look for it, and the authors don’t need to remind me
that they exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="google-reader"&gt;Google Reader&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; is a very effective way of having good quality information
come to you. Back in 2008, I used to use Google Reader to subscribe to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt;
feeds. I was an aspiring photographer back then and I remember being subscribed
to around 80 blogs. Each day I’d read articles from whoever had posted
something new, without needing to visit their websites or remember who they are
or that I’d subscribed to their blog. The authors didn’t need to optimize their
output according to an opaque and changing algorithm either - they didn’t need
to optimize article length, tags, post frequency, image inclusion or linked
content. They could write how they wanted to, which I suspect leads to higher
quality content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="social-media"&gt;Social Media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years later Google Reader was closed down, presumably because using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt;
didn’t fit with Googles advertising model. I was unaware of it at the time but
I imagine it sent shockwaves through blogging communities and probably upended
many businesses. I mostly stopped reading blogs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook was growing fast, Instagram felt new and exciting, and content was
moving onto ‘platforms’, or into walled gardens. And as they kept on growing
the average quality of the content decreased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter is like this now I think. There are some real diamonds to be found from
time to time, but there’s a lot of mud too. Mostly its just mud, but the
occasional diamond can have outsized benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; isn’t like this. I choose the contents of my ‘news feed’, and
each article can be much longer than a Tweet, or a caption to a photo, or a
status update. It’s hard to write well and to create an interesting or useful blog
post, and that makes it harder to dilute quality with entertaining
distractions. I have complete control about what content I see, and I can
change it whenever I want. The process is designed around me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="reeder5"&gt;Reeder5&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used &lt;code&gt;netNewsWire&lt;/code&gt; for a few weeks, but it couldn’t sync between my laptop
and phone, so I bought &lt;code&gt;Reeder 5&lt;/code&gt;. It’s got a few unusual design patterns, but
 it works well and has all the features I want. I’ve been unsubscribing from
 email newsletters and subscribing to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; feed instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It keeps my inbox quieter, and it feels good to have a ‘separation of
 concerns’. It makes it easier to read interesting content without being distracted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-using-rss-1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://marco.org/2013/03/26/power-of-rss"&gt;https://marco.org/2013/03/26/power-of-rss&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-using-rss-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/></entry><entry><title>How I learnt to code</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/How-I-learnt-to-code.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-12-01T13:51:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-01T13:51:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-12-01:/How-I-learnt-to-code.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;4 years ago I started learning how to code, and it was difficult! It still is
difficult, but I now have a collection of tools and perspectives that make it
less daunting. Leveling up requires one more abstraction
to wrap my head around, or one more &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; to understand. I can do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I don’t think it needed to be so difficult, so now I’m building &lt;a href="https://codeschoolmeta.com"&gt;Code
School Meta&lt;/a&gt; to make it easier to learn how to code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning to code has been fun, ultimately successful, and life changing (hello
job security!) but at the beginning it was sooo slow, and super tricky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imposter syndrome is real, and I definitely felt it. I hadn’t taken any classes
in computer science, and I felt like I knew almost nothing about anything. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process began with Pandas, a (&lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt;) Python analytics library. Spreadsheets
were slowing me down at work, and I was bored. I found this &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/5JnMutdy6Fw"&gt;great
tutorial&lt;/a&gt; by Brandon Rhodes. From there I found
out about Jupyter Notebooks, and then I found about Github pages and how to
make a blog using &lt;a href="https://blog.getpelican.com/"&gt;pelican&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That led to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; (and also JavaScript, which I tried very hard to avoid
for as long as possible). I felt like a monkey bashing a keyboard as I tried to
make &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; elements do what I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unusally, I think Git was next. Mainly because I found this &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/rys-git-tutorial.html"&gt;amazing
tutorial&lt;/a&gt; to help me learn. It made Git seem &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt;,
and also helped &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; make more sense too. Bonus!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suddenly realized that great learning materials are crucial if I was going to
keep momentum and keep on enjoying the thrill of seeing the computer do
something I hadn’t made it do before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now I’m now working on &lt;a href="https://codeschoolmeta.com"&gt;Code School: Meta&lt;/a&gt;. It’s
an online community to make it easier to teach yourself how to code - less
confusion about how to get started or what to learn next, more encouragement,
and lots of high quality resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’d like to know more, please &lt;a href="https://codeschoolmeta.com"&gt;check it out&lt;/a&gt;
and sign up for updates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/><category term="learning"/><category term="code"/></entry><entry><title>Reading: April 2018</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/reading-april-2018.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2018-06-04T15:52:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-06-04T15:52:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2018-06-04:/reading-april-2018.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A list of interesting things. June&amp;nbsp;2018&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="articles"&gt;Articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fs.blog/mental-models/"&gt;Mental models&lt;/a&gt; A comprehensive list organised around different disciplines. It a long read but probably one of the most easy to apply and tangibly useful articles I’ve read recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/vb.html"&gt;Life is short&lt;/a&gt; - Is life actually short, or would we always want more time, no matter how much we could have?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.eugenewei.com/blog/2018/5/21/invisible-asymptotes"&gt;Invisible asymptotes&lt;/a&gt; - A well written and long look at various facets of business strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://osam.com/Commentary/factors-from-scratch"&gt;Factors from scratch&lt;/a&gt; - Investing: A unified framework to explain how factors work. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://kottke.org/18/06/a-sad-update-about-a-scissors-maker-that-went-viral"&gt;This is tragic&lt;/a&gt; - “…But I do think this highlights the potential disconnects between mental health &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; business, publicity &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; success, and success &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; happiness. The internet can seem so intimate but ultimately it’s a thin view of an individual’s or company’s reality.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://statico.github.io/vim3.html"&gt;Vim&lt;/a&gt; after 15 years&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2018/03/27/a-complete-guide-to-cyprocurrency-regulations-around-the-world.html?__source=sharebar%7Clinkedin&amp;amp;par=sharebar"&gt;Cryptocurrency regulations around the world&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.lrb.co.uk/v40/n13/john-lanchester/after-the-fall"&gt;On the 2008 financial crisis&lt;/a&gt; - “I’m not sure if it’s philosophically possible for an action to be both necessary and a disaster, but that in essence is what the bailouts were.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="podcasts"&gt;Podcasts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/whatbitcoindid"&gt;Jill Carlson&lt;/a&gt; on the “What Bitcoin Did” podcast. “For the first time there is no longer a monopoly on the creation of value or monetary systems, that is really What Bitcoin Did.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/deVoaRTfVqs"&gt;Georges St-Pierre&lt;/a&gt; on the Joe Rogan podcast. A long and candid conversation from one of the world’s best athletes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/KqhRZfKRriU"&gt;Ricardo Spagni&lt;/a&gt; a.k.a Fluffypony on Monero vs Bitcoin, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EOS&lt;/span&gt;, the current bear market, Tari, and ASICs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="resources"&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lots of &lt;a href="https://vincentarelbundock.github.io/Rdatasets/datasets.html"&gt;data sets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/><category term="reading"/><category term="learning"/></entry><entry><title>I’m a chartered accountant</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/chartered.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-10-19T21:56:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-10-19T21:56:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-10-19:/chartered.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve qualified as a chartered accountant and will soon become a member of the Institute of Chartered Accountants in England and&amp;nbsp;Wales&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year I qualified as a chartered accountant. Qualification requires
passing 15 exams and gaining 3150 hours of work experience. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To celebrate passing your exams and verify your success, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ICAEW&lt;/span&gt; print the
names of everyone who passed in an advert in the Financial Times. This happened
for me on the 26 January.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="exam pass list in the financial times" src="https://johnmathews.eu/images/exam_pass_list.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/><category term="ICAEW"/><category term="ACA"/><category term="Accounting"/></entry><entry><title>Spare time</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/spare-time.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2016-08-13T21:15:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-08-13T21:15:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2016-08-13:/spare-time.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a list of interests I want to consider pursuing. I wrote it when I began to study for my last set of exams and my mind filled with things I’d rather be doing instead. Some of these interests are just me reacting to having no spare time for a few months, but others are decent goals and projects. Temporarily losing my spare time made me value it more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="free-time" src="/images/spare_time.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote this post so that I could compare what I thought was important when I was busy to when I wasn’t. Writing the list allowed me to move on without forgetting. Here’s a break down of each item:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Run 10k in 50 minutes” - This is easier than I imagined. When I wrote the
     list I could barely run 2k without stopping, but intended to go for a
     weekly run whilst studying. I’ve struggled to stay energetic and healthy
     during previous exam phases, so now I have a rule that I must do some mild
     exercise even if I think I can’t spare the time. I find running really
     lowers my stress levels, and increasing my heart rate and working up a
     sweat lets me sleep better and concentrate for longer. After a few weeks of
     minimal running, I could run 5k easily. If I kept at it, 10k in 50 mins
     would be easy. But point 2…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Be Insanity strong” - As in, do the Insanity workout programme. Again. I thought about it and decided to do P90x instead. Week 1 is going great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Read the bible habitually” - When I was 17 I found out about Jesus and
    became a Christian. In the months and years after that I’d regularly read my
    bible almost every day and pray a lot. I wanted to understand, so I set a
    goal of 5 chapters each day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read through the new testament repeatedly and read most of the old
testament during this time. I knew the scriptures well enough that a lot of
sermons became boring and obvious - I’d already studied the bible passage
being used. During this time I remember being aware that the way I thought
was different to how it would have been otherwise. My perspectives were
long-term and less me focused. I thought about what I was reading instead
of the days’ headlines or social chatter. I remember enjoying the benefits
and thinking that I should keep this habit. The reasons why I think
Christianity is so wonderful are well summarised in &lt;a href="http://messages.destinyedinburgh.com/sermon/the-gospel-we-preach-a-message-for-leaders"&gt;this
sermon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s now 10 years later, and whilst my convictions are strong, my knowledge
of the bible is sadly pretty fuzzy. My thinking is clouded by the
perspectives contained in the media I consume and the conversations I’m
part of. I strongly suspect I would be acting and thinking differently if I
read my bible more, but I don’t know what those differences would be.
Trouble is, it’s often not obvious what the immediate benefits of
reading the bible are, you have to work for it a bit. Praying for help is
effective. The books in the bible were written to last through the ages and
across all cultures, so it’s not surprising that they’re not as easy to
read as something written for an English speaker in a hurry. I should stop
being in a hurry, and stop prioritising only quantifiable goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Think more” - On a similar note to 3, but less supernatural. If I spent
    less time consuming content and a little more looking around me or walking,
    I reckon I’d be more self-aware and make better decisions. This would
    probably lead to a happier, more satisfying life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Pray more” - I don’t know why, but the creator of the universe wants me to
    talk and share my life with him. He cares about me. This makes no sense to
    me, at all. If I was God, I would not go out of my way to consider the views
    and concerns of a very flawed human. But when I pray, my prayers are very
    often answered. I should ask him about this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Amazon seller?” - Amazon have this “Fulfilled by Amazon” service,
     which means you don’t even need to hold the stock you want to sell.
     If I choose the right products, import them cheaply from China and
     reselling  them on Amazon at a profit, I end up quids in for minimal
     effort and manageable risk. Sounds intriguing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Blog about interesting data” - Here I am, blogging. I should stick
    to the main topic and get technical. I was inspired by this
    &lt;a href="http://www.curiousgnu.com/"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Finish Coursera” - The data science specialization is great! It’s in R, and I want to focus on Python, but I’d still like to do it. I need to consider the opportunity cost of the time committed, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Read for fun, history, fiction” - When I started my job, in April 2014, I
    was half way through &lt;a href="https://read.amazon.co.uk/kp/embed?asin=B00796LLLK&amp;amp;asin=B00796LLLK&amp;amp;preview=newtab&amp;amp;linkCode=kpe&amp;amp;ref_=cm_sw_r_kb_dp_GP2Rxb3Q8MYC4"&gt;Savage
    Continent&lt;/a&gt;,
    which is an eye-opening and eye-watering history of Europe in the years
    after World War 2. I see Europe through different eyes because of it.
    However I only got half way though, and since April ‘14 I never felt I had
    the free time or energy to pick it back up. This should change. When I was a
    researcher, and when I was a student, I had so much more opportunity to
    develop my own pursuits. Since entering the corporate world, I find myself
    fighting a war of attrition to exert my personality onto my lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read for fiction… I’m unconvinced. What do you have at the end of
it? What can you do with it? Maybe I’ve just been reading the wrong authors,
but I’m going to leave this for now. Sure, you could gain an appreciation of
a different time or place, but that appreciation comes via the fictional
characters and events, its secondary. What about abstract constructs,
perspectives, morals… things that history books are ill-suited for? Great
fiction would be essential for exploring these. But for now, I’ll prioritise
point 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" class="my-5" frameborder="0" height="550" src="https://read.amazon.co.uk/kp/card?asin=B00796LLLK&amp;amp;asin=B00796LLLK&amp;amp;preview=inline&amp;amp;linkCode=kpe&amp;amp;ref_=cm_sw_r_kb_dp_GP2Rxb3Q8MYC4" style="max-width: 100%; float:middle" width="336"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Do a photography project” - This I would love to do, but probably won’t.
     It would be a luxury, and the opportunity cost would be too great right
     now. I’d like to shoot a series of black and white portraits, and turn them
     into large prints. I think good portrait photography is uniquely impactful
     and moving, choosing B&amp;amp;W removes distractions and leaves a subjects
     humanity more exposed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Have a list of business/product ideas” - There’s no excuse for this
     one, anyone can have several good ideas. It’s turning them into
     reality that takes skill. Need to have the ideas first, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Do a law &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MOOC&lt;/span&gt;” - i.e Study particular areas of law, in my own time
     and at my own pace. I studied a tiny bit of law during the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACA&lt;/span&gt;, and
     realised employment law or contract law could be really useful.
     (Same for the tax system - another surprise). We only had a brief
     introduction though, so if I could find the time I’d like to know more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Do an InfoSec or Network Security &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MOOC&lt;/span&gt;” - Its super interesting,
     but not likely to be a good use of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Learn to fight - Krav Maga / &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MMA&lt;/span&gt;” - Ever since watching The Bourne
     Identity I’ve wanted to learn Krav Maga, and &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/LybrzdG96_8"&gt;Georges
     St-Pierre&lt;/a&gt; made me want to train
     for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MMA&lt;/span&gt;. For now though, I’ll do P90x. I can reconsider in 90 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class="relative" style="padding-top: 56.25%"&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen="" class="absolute inset-0 w-full h-full" frameborder="0" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/u0_8dzaNxhg"&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Get out of London” - My contract ends in April 2017, next summer
     will be a crossroads. I hate the commute, I hate being constantly
     rushed. Living in other cities has been a lot more pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/><category term="Habits"/><category term="Advice"/><category term="Reflection"/></entry></feed>