<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>JohnMathews.eu - Non-technical/Learning</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/feeds/non-technical/learning.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://johnmathews.eu/</id><updated>2021-01-18T11:51:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Why I Want To Write Regularly</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/why-i-want-to-write-regularly.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-18T11:51:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-18T11:51:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-18:/why-i-want-to-write-regularly.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As you can see, I’ve recently started writing more frequently. I want to do
this because I often have thoughts which I’d like to explore and develop
further, but rarely do. I find writing hard because it forces me to organise my
thoughts and look at how substantial they really are, or aren’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is truth in the saying that “to know a thing you need to be able to teach
it &lt;sup id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1" title="wikipedia article, and some extenal validation"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
“, and writing well has several similarities to teaching. Can I really copy a
collection of thoughts from my head to yours?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember watching Inception and hearing that the most resilient parasite is
an idea. I think that’s mostly true, and the older I get the more I believe
that ideas matter&lt;sup id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2" title="and also, that asking the right question is more important than finding the right answer. I guess asking the right question is always necessary, but finding the right answer is only sometimes sufficient. Sometimes you can get the answer a bit wrong if you asked the right question, and still get enough benefits to avoid the problem."&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. They have so many
subtle consequences. They are the first
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domino_effect"&gt;dominos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t expect writing regularly to become a permanent habit - it doesn’t need
to be. But I do want to focus on it for a while so that I become significantly
better. It’s a skill that has too many benefits to be ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realised that the blogs I remembered most were focussed and unapologetic
about their priorities. Most of them have a lot of text and do not focus on
design. They make it easy to read text, and don’t spend time or attention on
header images or styling. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I redesigned this blog I had default settings that asked me to supply an
image for each post, and for a summary, and a suggested tweet. None of it was
necessary, and whilst they all tried to make the blog better they ended up
making it worse because they added complexity and distracted from the main thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These features are still there if I want to use them, but they are not set up
to be used by default anymore. They’ve been moved to the background, and if I
forget they exist then that is &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt; - it just shows they weren’t as important in
practice as I thought they’d be when I was &lt;a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/yak_shaving"&gt;Yak
Shaving&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/You_aren%27t_gonna_need_it"&gt;You Ain’t Gonna Need
It&lt;/a&gt;, mate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1"&gt;wikipedia
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Learning_by_teaching"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;, and some
&lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20210118112910/https://digest.bps.org.uk/2018/05/04/learning-by-teaching-others-is-extremely-effective-a-new-study-tested-a-key-reason-why/"&gt;extenal
validation&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2"&gt;and also, that asking the right question is more
important than finding the right answer. I guess asking the right question is
always necessary, but finding the right answer is only sometimes &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Necessity_and_sufficiency"&gt;sufficient&lt;/a&gt;.
Sometimes you can get the answer a bit wrong if you asked the right question,
and still get enough benefits to avoid the problem. &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-why-i-want-to-write-regularly-2-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/></entry><entry><title>Using RSS</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/using-rss.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-14T16:52:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-14T16:52:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-14:/using-rss.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;h3 id="updated-10-feb-2021"&gt;Updated: 10 Feb 2021&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found a blog &lt;a href="https://brandur.org/fragments/rss-abandon"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; which is
surprisingly similar to my thoughts on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; feeds, but better presented and
thought through. The post mentions the idea that “&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; is about capturing the
long tail of blogs that don’t post frequently”
&lt;sup id="sf-using-rss-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-using-rss-1" title="https://marco.org/2013/03/26/power-of-rss"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This idea crystalised why I was so glad I’d started using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; feeds
again. If readers use &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt;, then authors don’t need to concern themselves with
attention. This removes pressure on the author to post
frequently and lets them focus on quality over quantity. News feeds and ad
supported platforms have fundamentally different mechanics and incentives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; I can let good quality content come to me, on its own schedule. I
don’t need to remember to look for it, and the authors don’t need to remind me
that they exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="google-reader"&gt;Google Reader&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; is a very effective way of having good quality information
come to you. Back in 2008, I used to use Google Reader to subscribe to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt;
feeds. I was an aspiring photographer back then and I remember being subscribed
to around 80 blogs. Each day I’d read articles from whoever had posted
something new, without needing to visit their websites or remember who they are
or that I’d subscribed to their blog. The authors didn’t need to optimize their
output according to an opaque and changing algorithm either - they didn’t need
to optimize article length, tags, post frequency, image inclusion or linked
content. They could write how they wanted to, which I suspect leads to higher
quality content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="social-media"&gt;Social Media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years later Google Reader was closed down, presumably because using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt;
didn’t fit with Googles advertising model. I was unaware of it at the time but
I imagine it sent shockwaves through blogging communities and probably upended
many businesses. I mostly stopped reading blogs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook was growing fast, Instagram felt new and exciting, and content was
moving onto ‘platforms’, or into walled gardens. And as they kept on growing
the average quality of the content decreased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter is like this now I think. There are some real diamonds to be found from
time to time, but there’s a lot of mud too. Mostly its just mud, but the
occasional diamond can have outsized benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; isn’t like this. I choose the contents of my ‘news feed’, and
each article can be much longer than a Tweet, or a caption to a photo, or a
status update. It’s hard to write well and to create an interesting or useful blog
post, and that makes it harder to dilute quality with entertaining
distractions. I have complete control about what content I see, and I can
change it whenever I want. The process is designed around me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="reeder5"&gt;Reeder5&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used &lt;code&gt;netNewsWire&lt;/code&gt; for a few weeks, but it couldn’t sync between my laptop
and phone, so I bought &lt;code&gt;Reeder 5&lt;/code&gt;. It’s got a few unusual design patterns, but
 it works well and has all the features I want. I’ve been unsubscribing from
 email newsletters and subscribing to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; feed instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It keeps my inbox quieter, and it feels good to have a ‘separation of
 concerns’. It makes it easier to read interesting content without being distracted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-using-rss-1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://marco.org/2013/03/26/power-of-rss"&gt;https://marco.org/2013/03/26/power-of-rss&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-using-rss-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/></entry><entry><title>Product-Led Growth</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/product-led-growth.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-12-08T12:59:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-08T12:59:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-12-08:/product-led-growth.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My notes on &amp;ldquo;Product-Led Growth&amp;rdquo; by Wes&amp;nbsp;Bush&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="part-1-design-your-strategy"&gt;Part 1: Design your strategy&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-1-why-is-product-led-growth-of-rising-importance"&gt;Chapter 1: Why is product-led growth of rising importance?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product-Led Growth is a go-to-market (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt;) strategy that relies on using your product as the main vehicle to acquire, activate and retain customers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product-Led Growth (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLG&lt;/span&gt;) means that every team influences the product:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marketing - how can our products generate a demand fly-wheel?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sales - how can we use the product to qualify our prospects for us?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customer Success - how can we create a product that helps customers become
  successful beyond our dreams?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By having every team focussed on the product, you create a culture that is built around enduring customer value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By leading with the product throughout the org, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PL&lt;/span&gt; companies get&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shorter sales cycles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lower Customer Acquisition Costs (CACs)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;higher Revenue Per Employee (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPE&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; strategy is an action plan that specifies how a company will reach target customers and achieve a competitive advantage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In order to select a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt;, you first need to understand:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;market conditions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;competitive positioning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ideal customer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;product offering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowing these elements will help you choose the correct &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; that will
   acquire, retain and grow you customer base in the most capital-efficient way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sales-led-go-to-market-strategies"&gt;Sales-Led Go-To-Market Strategies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Profit Centers: Sales, Marketing, Customer Success&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cost Centers: Engineering, Product&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advantages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Annual Contract Value (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACV&lt;/span&gt;) can be very high&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enterprise first solutions that are very complex and therefore need a high-touch sales model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the Total Addressable Market (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;TAM&lt;/span&gt;) is very small, because your market is super niche, you can quite easily talk to almost all market participants. (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLG&lt;/span&gt; is built for large TAMs)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s great for new categories of product where education is required, because you need to change how people approach a problem. This takes time and requires education.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is turn requires that you understand your customers pain points, objections, core problems. If you jump to quickly a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLG&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; strategy then you risk a high church rate because you haven’t understood or educated
your customers well enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disadvantages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sales cycles are very long&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Life Time Value (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;LTV&lt;/span&gt;) must be high enough to recoup the investment in
  &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAC&lt;/span&gt;. This often requires charging the customer a premium. This premium
  price isn’t because the product is amazing, or more valuable to the
  customer, but because the customer acquisition model is more expensive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you use a Sales-Led &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt;, you need to watch out for competitors who can
  sell more efficiently, or have a more efficient Customer Acquisition
  Model. They can steal your market share by offering the same product with
  at a lower price.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customer Acquisition methods are super leaky. Most marketing-qualified leads (MQLs) never result in a closed deal, this is partly because:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it encourages markets to gate content in order to hit their &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MQL&lt;/span&gt; goals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it focusses on content consumption as a leading indicator of intent.
  (but reading a white-paper or brochure doesn’t mean I’m going to buy
  the thing).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the entire process rewards creating friction in the buying process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consequently, there is often a disconnect between marketing and sales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="product-led-go-to-market-strategies"&gt;Product-Led Go-To-Market Strategies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Switching from Sales-Led &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; to Product-Led &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; creates a defensive moat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A product led marketing team asks “How can we use the product to qualify our prospects for us?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A product led customer success team asks “How can we create a product that helps customers be successful without our help?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A product-led engineering team asks “How can we create a product with a quick time-to-value?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Growth is much faster, because:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you need fewer resources to scale,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the top of the customer funnel is much wider.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAC&lt;/span&gt; is much lower&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Higher &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPE&lt;/span&gt; (revenue per employee)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User experience is better&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-2-free-freemium-or-demo"&gt;Chapter 2 - Free, Freemium or Demo&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MOAT&lt;/span&gt; framework to pick the right &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; strategy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt;arket Strategy - Dominant? Disruptive? Differentiated?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;O&lt;/strong&gt;cean Conditions - Blue or Red?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;udience - Do you have a top-down or bottom-up marketing strategy?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;ime to Value - How much time do you need for a customer to
  experience the value?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dominant - Do it better than the competition &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; charge a lower price&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is your &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TAM&lt;/span&gt; big enough?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does your product solve a specific job significantly better and at lower cost than anyone else on the market?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can the user realize significant ongoing value quickly with little or no help?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you want to be the undisputed market leader?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Differentiated - Pick and win a fight against an industry giant&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Main line of defense against the giant is specialization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on an underserved niche&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do a specific job better than the competition but charge significantly more&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is not a one-size-fits-all model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free trials and demos work well here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because its specialized, combining freemium with quick time-to-value is difficult&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Main competitive advantage is how you solve your customers problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does your market have underserved customers?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TAM&lt;/span&gt; big enough?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;is the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACV&lt;/span&gt; high enough?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Could prospects experience a Magic Moment during a free trial?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disruptive - Charge less for an inferior product (e.g. Canva, Google docs)&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build a simpler product that solves a specific pain point, and because its simpler, its faster, you can charge less, and its more appropriate to some over-served or priced-out customers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s a scaled-down product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Costs must be low&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product must be easy to use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TAM&lt;/span&gt; large enough?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can on-boarding be completely self-service?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freemium model thrives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-3-red-ocean-or-blue-ocean-markets"&gt;Chapter 3 - Red-Ocean or Blue-Ocean markets?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Red-ocean companies try to outperform their rivals in order to grab a larger share of the existing market. As the market gets crowded, opportunity for profit and growth reduces. Products become commodities. Cut-throat competition turns the waters red.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue-ocean companies access untapped market space and create demand. They have opportunity for highly profitable growth. Competition is irrelevant. Create and capture new demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some markets will be red-ocean, but a particular niche within it will be blue ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue Oceans require educating the customer to create the demand. This is high-touch, and often a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; strategy isn’t going to work. It needs to be sales-led in order to educate the customer enough. But if Time-To-Value (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;TTV&lt;/span&gt;) is short then &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLG&lt;/span&gt; could be great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Red Oceans need big wide funnels in order to compete, and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; strategies work great. They’re defensible, keep costs low and make sales cycles short.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-4-top-down-or-bottom-up-selling-strategy"&gt;Chapter 4 - Top-Down or Bottom-Up selling strategy?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLG&lt;/span&gt; works for bottom-up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High touch sales-led strategies work for Top-Down enterprise sales strategies, where the product is super complex and the sales cyccle is very long.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top-Down (Sales team is the growth engine):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Additional Services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lower customer churn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Poor revenue distribution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Long sales cycles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free Trial sometimes works&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bottom-Up (Product is the growth engine):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wider top-of-funnel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Predictable sales figures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revenue diversity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scalable fast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small contracts only&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;non-paying customers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;expertise shortage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;upfront investment as non-paying customers drain resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freemium&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free-Trial&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-5-time-to-value"&gt;Chapter 5 - Time-to-Value&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much time until you deliver on your promise to prospects?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much time until the product sells itself?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; strategies require fast time-to-value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rank your uses across 2 dimensions and group into 4 quadrants. The dimensions are Ability (low - high) and Motivation (low - high)&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low Motivation - Low Ability = Mission Impossible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High Motivation - Low Ability = Rookie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low Motivation - High Ability = Veteran&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High Motivation - High Ability = Spoiled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Figure out your top two quadrants. Unless all your users are Spoiled, you need to decrease Time-To-Value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How motivated are your users?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is your product easy for your target audience to use?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can users experience the core value (magic moment?) without hand-holding?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id="part-2-build-your-foundation"&gt;Part 2 - Build Your Foundation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-7-build-a-product-led-foundation"&gt;Chapter 7 - Build a product-led foundation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A positive feedback loop:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understand&lt;/strong&gt; your value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Communicate&lt;/strong&gt; it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deliver&lt;/strong&gt; on your promise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-8-understand-your-value"&gt;Chapter 8 - Understand your value&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re selling live-chat software, you’re not really selling live-chat software, you are selling a new and better way to acquire customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are selling the outcome, the result, the why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pain makes us want to change so that we can avoid or prevent the pain altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pain is product agnostic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three reasons why people buy a product:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Functional Outcome - the core task that needs to get done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emotional Outcome - how a customer wants to feel or avoid feeling as a result of the functional outcome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social Outcome - how a customer wants to be perceived by others by using
   your product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In every software, there are usage patterns that point towards to core outcomes that are most important to customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest differences between sales-led and product-led companies is that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SL&lt;/span&gt; companies monitor usage patters to see if users are accomplishing meaningful outcomes. These outcomes are referred to as &lt;strong&gt;value-metrics&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A value-metric is the way you measure value exchange in your product&lt;/strong&gt;. They are the linchpin to successful execution of a product-led &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTM&lt;/span&gt; strategy because you are aligning your revenue model directly with your customer acquisition model. Because your value metrics play a vital role in how you price your product, set up your monitoring, and build your team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Value metrics could be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for Vimeo, number of videos uploaded by the user.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for Slack, number of messages sent by the user&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for PayPal, amount of revenue generated by the user (processed?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;strong&gt;functional&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;outcome based&lt;/strong&gt; value metrics. Functional value metrics are “per user” or “per 100 videos”. Pricing scales around functions of usage. Outcome based value metrics charge based on the outcome, e.g. how many views a video received, or how much money a customer made when using your payment process method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many SaaS companies rely on feature differentiation as a way to justify higher prices, but this produces higher churn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Value metrics outperform feature differentiation with upto 75% less churn…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome based value metrics reduce church by an additional 40%. Apparently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A good value metric is easy for a customer to understand. They need to immediately understand what they’re paying for and where they fit in your packing/pricing structure. If you’re in an established market, it makes senses to look at what the competition charges.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A good value metric is aligned with the value that the customer receives through the product. Consider the low-level components of your high-level outcome. E.g. what low level actions are necessary to get the end result?  Sending lots of messages? Meeting lots of people? Finding lots of things?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A good value metric grows with your customers usage of the valuable outcome. If customers get incredible value from the product, charge them more because the product is worth it. Also, if they aren’t getting much value from the product, charge them less.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t do user based pricing if you want to get lots of users - its a conflict of interests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you’re small, you can try different pricing strategies and iterate to success.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask yourself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do my best customers do?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do my best customers not do?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What features did my best customers try first when they were on-boarding?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the similarities along my best customers that led to success?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For churned customers, what were the main differences between them and the
   best customers? Were they in the ideal audience? Why did they church? What
   did they do or not do that good customers didn’t?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/><category term="marketing"/><category term="startups"/></entry><entry><title>The Mom Test</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/mom-test.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-12-04T16:07:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-04T16:07:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-12-04:/mom-test.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My notes on &amp;ldquo;The Mom Test&amp;rdquo; by Rob&amp;nbsp;Fitzpatrick&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s called the Mom Test because it leads to questions that even your mom couldn’t lie to you about&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="overview"&gt;Overview:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask good questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid bad data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep it casual&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push for commitment and advancement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frame the meeting well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on the right, tight, customer segment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prep well, take good notes, review your notes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-1-opinions-are-worthless-you-want-objective-facts-about-what-happened-in-the-past"&gt;Chapter 1 - Opinions are worthless, you want objective facts about what happened in the past&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find out if people care about your idea by never mentioning it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Forcing yourself not to mention your idea will force you to ask better questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure your questions pass the mom test:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Talk about their lives, not your idea Ask about specifics in the past,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;not hypotheticals Spend most of your time listening, not talking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule of thumb: Anything involving the future is an overly optimistic lie&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-2-avoid-bad-data-compliments-fluff-hypotheticals-ideas"&gt;Chapter 2 - Avoid bad data - Compliments, Fluff, Hypotheticals, Ideas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You aren’t allowed to tell them what their problem is, and they aren’t allowed
to tell you what to build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-3-ask-the-important-questions"&gt;Chapter 3 - Ask the Important Questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should be terrified of at least one of the questions you ask in each conversation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search out the scary questions you’ve been unintentionally avoiding. What’s the worst thing a prospect could say? What’s the scariest question you could ask?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A good way to find scary questions is to imagine that your company has failed and then to ask why.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you get an unexpected answer to one of your questions and it doesn’t have any effect on what you’re going to do, then was it really worth asking it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;General advice for hard things including asking hard questions - imagine you were delegating the task, what would you tel the person to do? That’s you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can ask about money.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Love bad news - if you find out that your idea is fundamentally flawed you’ve just saved a tonne of time and energy and money. Move on. It’s getting you closer to the truth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bad news isn’t the result of an opinion. No one knows if your idea will work, only the market knows. Opinions don’t count.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lukewarm response to your idea can be a great conversation, because you realise that your idea isn’t a great idea. Lukewarm means they don’t care enough to buy the first (worst) version before it’s ready.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look before you zoom. Don’t focus on details too soon, you need to understand the big picture first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have &lt;strong&gt;product risk&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;customer risk&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product risk&lt;/strong&gt; - can I build it and grow it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Customer risk&lt;/strong&gt; - is there a big enough group of people who are going to buy it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pre-plan a list of the 3 most important questions (including a scary one) before every meeting or conversation. Be ready with these. They should change from week to week. As you get good quality answers to existing questions you can bring in new questions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-4-keep-it-casual-structure-problem-solution-sales"&gt;Chapter 4 - Keep it casual, Structure: Problem -&amp;gt; Solution -&amp;gt; Sales&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Normally you would have 3 meetings with a client in order to make a big sale. This lets you do each stage really well without blurring the data:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify your prospect’s problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explain your solution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sell the solution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identifying a problem doesn’t have to be a meeting, keep it casual and you will get more honest feedback much faster. It works better as a chat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It take 5 minutes (max) to identify if a problem exists and is important&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Give as little info as possible about your idea whilst still nudging the conversation along&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-5-the-currencies-of-conversation-time-reputation-money"&gt;Chapter 5 - The currencies of conversation - Time, Reputation, Money&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In early stage sales, the main goal is learning. Money is a side-effect.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If someone is willing to risk reputation, or spend time or money on your idea, then you can believe that they’re interested.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hearing a compliment is still useful - it means they’re trying to get rid of you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If its a bad meeting, push for a commitment of some kind. Ask them to spend time, reputation or money and you’ll see what they really think.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If they aren’t excited (not just interested, but in pain and excited for your solution) then you need to find that out &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ASAP&lt;/span&gt;. It’s still a good meeting if you can discover this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lead isn’t a real lead until you’ve given them a concrete chance to reject you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask learning questions by using the Mom Test, then confirm by selling it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need &lt;strong&gt;crazy customers&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They have a painful and expensive problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They know they have a painful and expensive problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They have the money to pay you to solve it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They already have their own bad solution to this terrible problem, and
  yours is clearly better&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A crazy customer doesn’t say “yeah that’s great, I’m really interested, let me know when its ready”. They say “&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AHHH&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;THIS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;THE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WORST&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PART&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OF&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MY&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LIFE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AND&lt;/span&gt; I &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WILL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PAY&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;YOU&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RIGHT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NOW&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TO&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FIX&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IT&lt;/span&gt;!”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A crazy customer will front you the money when all you have is a prototype made of duct-tape&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A crazy customer is the person reading you blog, searching for workarounds, when you haven’t spent loads of marketing and lead generation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep a crazy customer close - they’ll stick with you when times are tough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-6-finding-good-conversations"&gt;Chapter 6 - Finding good conversations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;eep having conversations until you stop hearing new stuff&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If it’s a topic you both care about, find an excuse. You’ll both enjoy the chat. You don’t need to mention your idea if it breaks the premise.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Warm introductions are the ideal way to start a new conversation. 6 degrees of freedom in the world, so find someone who knows someone who knows someone..&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cold calls - LinkedIn, maybe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Serendipity - be prepared, be bold&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a good excuse - hustle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Landing pages so that googling the problems brings them to you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organise an event - bring the businesses together for an event. You’ll be considered an expert cos you’re facilitating it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Become a subject matter expert&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaking and teaching engagements - you get to have strong opinions, and you’ll be respected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vision -&amp;gt; Framing -&amp;gt; Weakness -&amp;gt; Pedestal -&amp;gt; Ask&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-7-choosing-you-customers"&gt;Chapter 7 - Choosing you customers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Startups don’t starve, they drown. In options, choices, ideas. You get overwhelmed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose a good customer segment, focus on it, and don’t get distracted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the beginning:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google - PhD students&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PayPal - eBay&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evernote - Moms with recipes, etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It will look obvious with hindsight, probably not so obvious before you’ve figured it out though.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you can’t get a consistent answer to a question, maybe you’re speaking to different segments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you aren’t finding &lt;strong&gt;consistent problems and goals&lt;/strong&gt; then you don’t have a specific enough customer segment&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Within the group, which type of person would want it the most?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would everyone within the group want to buy/use it? Or only some?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why does the subset want it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does everyone in the group have the same motivation?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What other motivations are there?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who else (outside the group) have these motivations?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go for &lt;strong&gt;Who-Where&lt;/strong&gt; pairs of segments. “Finance professionals who run marathons”..&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You want customers who are reachable, profitable, and personally rewarding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good segments are usually “who-where” pairs. If you don’t know where to find your customers, keep slicing until you do. Make sure the segment is reachable, profitable, and personally rewarding&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chapter-8-getting-the-most-from-the-conversations-by-prepping-and-reviewing"&gt;Chapter 8 - Getting the most from the conversations by prepping and reviewing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prepare well&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you 3 big questions ready, including the scary ones&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Know who you are speaking to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Know what commitment and next-steps you want to push for&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spend up to an hour &lt;strong&gt;writing down your best guesses about what you think they will say, what they care about and what they want.&lt;/strong&gt; If you have a focussed segment, you’ll only need to do this occasionally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whilst prepping, if you come across a question which can be answered using the internet, use the internet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take good notes&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask if you can record the audio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Record emotions as well as words. Verbatim alone isn’t always accurate 6 months later&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use shorthand for follow up, happy, angry, meh, etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pains and obstacles are a lot more important if someone is embarrassed or angry when they’re talking about them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dig into the big emotions, find out what’s causing them, or why its a big deal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review your notes&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meta - which questions went well or not?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What were the answers to the scary questions?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can you do better next time?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What were the clear signals? What signals did you miss?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/></entry><entry><title>Obviously Awesome</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/obviously-awesome.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-12-03T15:46:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-03T15:46:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-12-03:/obviously-awesome.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My notes on &amp;ldquo;Obviously Awesome&amp;rdquo; by April&amp;nbsp;Dunford&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3 id="intro"&gt;Intro&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In order to do better marketing, understand your value and differentiators better&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand what makes a best-fit customer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positioning is a fundamental input to every business tactic you use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you fail at positioning, you fail at marketing and sales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positioning is “conext setting” for products&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customers need to be able to easily understand&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What your product does&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why it is special&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why it matters to them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your prospects can’t figure out what your product does quickly, they will
   invent a position for you. It might hide your key strengths or misunderstand
   your value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find people to demo your product to, then ask them to describe it back to
   you. Do the same with existing customers. If they’re not saying the same
   thing then you have a positioning problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Products with strong positioning:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find the best kind of customer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the value obvious&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sell quickly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="part-1"&gt;Part 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="positioning-as-context"&gt;Positioning as context&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Without positioning to guide us, we don’t know how to understnad a product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positioning lets us make assumptions about&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who a product is for&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what its main features are&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how much it costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Without it we would be paralyzed by choice, and we wouldnt be able to make
   sense of all the products around us. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The context and purpose of a product from the founders/engineers perspective
   are often different to those of the prospect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Products can be positioned in multiple ways, and often the best positioning
   is not the default positioning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bad positioning makes it harder for prospects to figure out if your product
   is worth thinking about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positioning requires considering:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customers point of view - what problem/pain does it solve&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ways your product is uniquely different&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The characteristics of a potential customer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The best market context to make your value uniquely obvious&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id="five-plus-one-components-of-effective-positioning"&gt;Five (plus one) components of effective positioning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Competitive Alternatives - if you didn’t exist, what would your customers
   use instead?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Its what your prospects would use to do the task if your product didn’t
   exist. It could be excel, or pen and paper. It could be nothing, (in
   which case maybe you product doesn’t solve a real pain point.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You probably know a lot more about your market, and problem, and
   alternative solutions, than your prospects do. (“Doing nothing” could be
   an opportunity, not a red flag.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Its important to understand what customers will compare your product
   with, because this is how they will define “better”. Is it “easier” than
   a pen and paper?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customers might never have purchased a solution like yours before.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unique Attributes - What do you have that alternative do not?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Could be:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivery Model (online vs offline, installed on-site vs not)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Business model (rental vs purchase)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specific expertise (data scientist with financial and back-end web
   dev expertise)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Value (and quantifiable objective proof) - What value do the attributes
   enable for customers?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If unique attributes are your secret sauce, the value is why someone
   might care about your secret sauce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fact based, provable, demonstrable, quantifiable, objective. Third party
   opinions are relevant. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Target market characteristics - Who cares a lot about that value?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on customers who are most likely to purchase quickly, wont ask for
   discounts, will tell their friends about you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should clearly identify who these are and &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identity what sets them apart from other groups of customers. Why are
   they uniquely likely to buy from you when others wouldnt or would take
   longer to consider and make a purchase&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Market Category - What context makes your value obvious to the ideal
   customer?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Declaring that your product exists in a certain market triggers a
   powerful set of assumptions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make these assumptions help you, not hinder you. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When presented with your product, customers will try to use what they
   already know to figure out what your product is all about and why its
   special. You want them to be able to do this really quickly and easily. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make these assumptions work for you, not against you. You won’t have to
   list every feature, because most of them will be assumed by the context
   of the market category. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get it right, and sales efforts (copy) wont be wasted battling those
   assumptions, but can instead build off of them to show secret sauce and
   value more obviously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Bonus) Relevant Trends - what trends make your product relevant right
   now?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Used carefully, trends can show prospoects why they should pay attention
   to your product right now. Increases urgency.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can increase urgency, excitement, coolness, credibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;but the trend must be directly relevant, practically and objectively applicable. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blockchains, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AI&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ML&lt;/span&gt; are trends - they are relevant to multiple markets. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of these components is relevant to the others&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/><category term="marketing"/><category term="positioning"/><category term="startups"/><category term="book"/></entry><entry><title>How I learnt to code</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/How-I-learnt-to-code.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-12-01T13:51:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-01T13:51:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-12-01:/How-I-learnt-to-code.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;4 years ago I started learning how to code, and it was &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; difficult! It’s
still difficult, but I now have a collection of tools and perspectives that
make it less daunting (more on that below). Leveling up requires one more
abstraction to wrap my head around, or one more &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; to understand. I can do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I don’t think it needed to be so difficult, so now I’m building &lt;a href="https://codeschoolmeta.com"&gt;Code
School Meta&lt;/a&gt; to make it easier to learn how to code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning to code has been fun, ultimately successful, and life changing (hello
job security!) but at the beginning it was sooo slow, and super tricky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember feeling like an imposter, and thinking that I was definitely not a
real developer - I hadn’t taken any classes in computer science. I felt like I
knew almost nothing about anything. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process began with Pandas, a (&lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt;) Python analytics library. Spreadsheets
were slowing me down at work, and I was bored. I found this &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/5JnMutdy6Fw"&gt;great
tutorial&lt;/a&gt; by Brandon Rhodes. From there I found
out about Jupyter Notebooks, and then I found about Github pages and how to
make a blog using &lt;a href="https://blog.getpelican.com/"&gt;pelican&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That led to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; (and also JavaScript, which I tried very hard to avoid
for as long as possible). I felt like a monkey bashing a keyboard as I tried to
make &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; elements do what I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Git was next, but I found this &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu/rys-git-tutorial.html"&gt;amazing tutorial&lt;/a&gt;
to help me learn. It made Git seem &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt;, and also helped &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; make more
sense too. Bonus!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suddenly realized that great learning materials are crucial if I was going to
keep momentum and keep on enjoying the thrill of seeing the computer do
something I hadn’t made it do before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now I’m now working on &lt;a href="https://codeschoolmeta.com"&gt;Code School: Meta&lt;/a&gt;. It’s
an online community to make it easier to teach yourself how to code - less
confusion about how to get started or what to learn next, more encouragement,
and lots of high quality resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’d like to know more, please &lt;a href="https://codeschoolmeta.com"&gt;check it out&lt;/a&gt;
and sign up for updates.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/></entry><entry><title>The 1-Page Marketing Plan</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/1-page-marketing-plan.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-11-19T15:50:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-19T15:50:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-11-19:/1-page-marketing-plan.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My notes on &amp;ldquo;The 1-Page Marketing Plan&amp;rdquo; by Allan&amp;nbsp;Dib&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="marketing-has-three-phases"&gt;Marketing has three phases&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Before (prospect) - get people to know you and indicate interest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;During (lead) - get the to like you and buy from you for the first time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After (customer) - get them to trust you, buy from you regularly, and refer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new customers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marketing is &lt;em&gt;strategy&lt;/em&gt;, all the other things are &lt;em&gt;tactics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="jargon-free-definition-of-marketing"&gt;Jargon free definition of marketing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advertising&lt;/strong&gt; - The circus is coming to town, you paint a sign saying “Circus coming to town on Saturday”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Promotion&lt;/strong&gt; - Put the sign on the back of an elephant and walk it into town&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Publicity&lt;/strong&gt; - Walk the elephant through the mayors flower beds and let a newspaper write about it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Public relations&lt;/strong&gt; - Get the mayor to laugh about it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sales&lt;/strong&gt; - the town people go to the circus, you explain how much fun the entertainment is, they buy some tickets, you answer their questions, they spend lots of money on food, games, shows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marketing&lt;/strong&gt; is the plan that made the whole thing happen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/><category term="Marketing"/></entry><entry><title>Learning to market</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/marketing-101.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-11-19T12:40:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-19T12:40:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2020-11-19:/marketing-101.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve learnt many things this year by being a solo technical founder, but so far marketing isn&amp;rsquo;t one of them. I&amp;rsquo;m trying to change&amp;nbsp;that.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Since April I’ve been able to work full time as a solo founder. I’ve challenged
myself to build something useful enough that customers would want to pay for it
and in the process of seeking that goal I’ve become a much better and more
rounded developer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been working solo for about 7 months now, and in that time I’ve begun
using test driven development, I’ve built non-trivial data driven web apps
using Django, and I’ve learnt how to deploy and monitor those apps in
production and make them performant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve made two main apps; &lt;a href="https://moneybar.nl"&gt;moneybar.nl&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://pippip.email"&gt;pippip.email&lt;/a&gt;, and I’ve learnt so much. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m realising though, that I still have much to learn in other spheres. Being a
great developer is deeply meaningful to me. It’s literally a bucket list item
for me and I intend to be writing code as long as I live. But there is no point
creating products if no one knows they exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where marketing and positioning comes in. Right now it feels like I
know nothing about how to get users, or validate an idea, or position a
product. These are all super necessary and super unknown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a more meta level, I’m confronted with the lost benefits of working with
co-founders, or of having friends doing similar things. I want to work faster
and make progress more efficiently. I need to be part of a community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working in isolation does have its advantages, though. I’m self-taught and
self-directed, figuring out the contours of uncharted territory and creating my
own personal map. In my mind, I have a deep and almost personal relationship
with the coding abstractions and tools I’ve learnt to work with. Classes and
functions, strings and floats, literally have (to me) their own textures,
colors and weights when I think or dream about them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It feels like I can pick up these abstractions as if they were physical objects
and turn them around to examine them. Place them next to each other and compare
the differences. Run thought experiements. In my experience, this kind of
relationship and affection simply doesn’t happen when taking a class or
following someone elses schedule. It’s satisying to feel ownership of a skill
like this, and it’s one of the primary reasons I consider coding to be similar
to a craft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having said all that, now that I realise I need to validate my product,
position it, and figure out marketing, I’ve stopped writing code, put down my
tools, and I’m going to learn marketing. I’ve bought some books. Maybe I’ll
post some reviews here later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In no particular order here is what I plan to read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 1-Page marketing plan, by Allan Dib Obviously Awesome, by April Dunford&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lean Analytics, Hooked, How to build habit-forming products, by Nir Eyal The&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mom Test, by Rob Fitzpatrick&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is marketing, by Seth Godin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product-led growth, by Wes Bush&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t know if I’ve covered 90% of the distance required or 50%. It’s
exhausting but I’m here for the journey not the destination.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Learning"/><category term="marketing"/><category term="growth"/></entry></feed>