<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>John Mathews - Non-technical/Social</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/feeds/non-technical/social.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://johnmathews.eu/</id><updated>2021-01-20T14:44:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>What’s So Different About Now</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/whats-so-different-about-now.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-20T14:44:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T14:44:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-20:/whats-so-different-about-now.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I think we are less aware of our ignorance than previous generations. It is
easy to implicitly assume that all useful information is available to us, and
that we are therefore more informed than we really are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is because the internet has made information more accessible
and global air travel have made the world feel smaller.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whilst an individual would hopefully never pretend to know everything, I think
its easy to assume that the right information exists and is being used by the
people to whom it is relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the accessibility of all information has put us in a situation similar to
information scarcity. We still need to actively search for the information we
want, because the information that comes to us easily or for free is not equal
to what we find when we apply effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can easily have so many short pieces of news or information that I am
always slightly overwhelmed. The pace of modern communications encourages me to
never slow down enough to form my own questions or frame my own arguments. I
can always find &lt;em&gt;an&lt;/em&gt; answer to my questions, but when was the last time I checked
that whoever gave it to me wasn’t going to profit from it?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Social"/></entry><entry><title>Predicting the Future using Human Nature and Technology</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/what-happens-next.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-20T14:05:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-20T14:05:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-20:/what-happens-next.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Predicting the future sounds like a tough problem, but we try to do it all the
time without realising it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We predict the future when we think about how risky or scary something is, or
when we think about what’s really going to change because of an announcement or
press release. We try to predict the future when we’re at the supermarket
checkouts and we try to pick the queue that will move the fastest. I always
seem to pick the wrong one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There must be a million ways of trying to predicting the future but all the good
ones are models which reduce complexity and emphasise key considerations. One
of them could be comparing the influence of human nature and technology on the
outcome, and then comparing the event to what’s happened before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human nature doesn’t change, so if something is driven by fear or greed then it
probably doesn’t matter what century it occurs in. Technology &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; change, and
if something is enabled or prevented due to technological progress then the
date is important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is driving the scenario? Is it human nature or technology? Supermarket
checkouts are mostly manual and require a couple of adults to work together, so
human nature has a much bigger role on efficiency than tech. Young men will
stack and pack quickly, old women will be the opposite. What types of shopping
bags they have, or how they pay, or even how many items they’re buying, are
probably not going to lead you to the right decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same probably works for getting through airport security.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Social"/></entry><entry><title>Financial Doom And Gloom</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/financial-doom-and-gloom.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-01-19T14:57:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-19T14:57:00+01:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2021-01-19:/financial-doom-and-gloom.html</id><summary type="html"/><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Financial crises seem to happen fairly regularly so they shouldn’t be
unexpected. But no-one seems particularly concerned about our current financial
system, at the moment our attention is controlled by other threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m concerned that a lot of money has been injected into the money supply but
we haven’t seen any inflation. And I am concerned that the price of stocks
is no longer related to the value created by the company but instead by macro economics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a terrible time to be a value investor. This should be an alarming
statement. Value investing should &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; be a decent way to make money
unless markets are broken. If the price of something doesn’t represent its
value then a correction is inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interest rates are really low at the moment so if you have spare money and you
want to make it work for you then where do you put it? Not into a bank account,
because interest rates are low&lt;sup id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-1-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-1" title="Why are interest rates low? Because confidence in the economy is low, so central bankers have to lower interest rates to make it 1. Cheaper for a business to borrow money to invest in their business and therefore easier for a business investments to be profitable, and 2. So that its more attractive for investors to use their capital to invest in a business  (which grows the economy) relative to depositing spare cash in a bank account (which is safer but a less efficient way to deploy capital). Interest rates affect the relative risk-reward ratios of different investment strategies"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and not into government debt, because
the yield is so low. It has to be stocks if you want the value of your
investments to increase meaningfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But everyone is doing this which drives the price up, and because their price
is increasing they increase even further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that the main reason for concern is super low interest rates and
massive increases in the money supply, but there are a couple of other factors
that are also contributing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easier than ever for retail investors to participate in the stock market,
and this seems like a good idea. Democratization. However if retail investors
have influence to effect prices, and they themselves can be manipulated or
influenced regarding what or when they buy or sell, then that is likely a new
kind of threat to financial stability. We’ve never seen social media combined
with quick, cheap investment services for amateurs before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Index funds are also more popular than ever&lt;sup id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-2-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-2" title="Index Funds Are the New Kings of Wall Street"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; - the efficacy of index investing
relative to traditional funds that use stock pickers is very high over medium
or long time horizons because index funds are much cheaper. But if index
funds become too large then they end up influencing the market in predictable
and rigid ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Index funds cannot choose what they buy or how much they buy - they just track
the index. If a company’s stock crosses certain thresholds, their stock has
to be bought or sold. It seems like its possible to create feedback loops where
funds have to buy more of a rising stock, which increases its scarcity and
price, which then requires index funds to purchase more of the same stock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The amount of euros in existence in 2019 was 90% more than in
2010.&lt;sup id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-3-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-3" title="statista"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
But inflation between 2010 and 2020 is
13%.&lt;sup id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-4-back"&gt;&lt;a class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-4" title="in2013dollars.com"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Why is that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the price of something doesn’t represent its value, then a correction is inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-1"&gt;Why are interest rates low? Because
confidence in the economy is low, so central bankers have to lower interest
rates to make it 1. Cheaper for a business to borrow money to invest in their business and
therefore easier for a business investments to be profitable, and 2. So that
its more attractive for investors to use their capital to invest in a business 
(which grows the economy) relative to depositing spare cash in a bank account (which is safer but a less efficient way to deploy capital). Interest rates affect the relative risk-reward ratios of
different investment strategies &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-2"&gt;&lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20210119144242/https://www.wsj.com/articles/index-funds-are-the-new-kings-of-wall-street-11568799004"&gt;Index Funds Are the New Kings of Wall Street&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-2-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-3"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/254220/value-of-euro-coins-in-circulation-since-2002/"&gt;statista&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-3-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id="sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-4"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.in2013dollars.com/europe/inflation/2010"&gt;in2013dollars.com&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-financial-doom-and-gloom-4-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Social"/></entry><entry><title>Between Clients</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/between-clients.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2019-10-08T16:05:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-10-08T16:05:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2019-10-08:/between-clients.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As a freelance data scientist, I use time between client engagements to up-skill and pursue professional interests that I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t otherwise be able&amp;nbsp;to.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At the end of the summer I had time between engagements to work on some side projects and grapple with some new (to me) libraries and technologies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="during-august-and-september-2019-i"&gt;During August and September 2019, I:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practiced creating websites using the &lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com"&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt; web-framework&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigated and demo’ed &lt;a href="https://pypi.org/project/django-plotly-dash/"&gt;django-plotly-dash&lt;/a&gt; - a library that allows exposing &lt;a href="https://dash.plot.ly"&gt;Plotly Dash&lt;/a&gt; apps to django projects&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Built a personal finance dashboard using &lt;a href="https://dash.plot.ly"&gt;Plotly Dash&lt;/a&gt; and began turning it into a web app using &lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com"&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://pypi.org/project/django-plotly-dash/"&gt;django-plotly-dash&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interviewed for a role at &lt;a href="https://coinmetrics.io"&gt;CoinMetrics.io&lt;/a&gt; and created &lt;a href="https://blog.johnmathews.eu/btc-fork-analysis.html"&gt;this investigation&lt;/a&gt; as a technical exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Created a company “&lt;a href="https://atlasdata.nl"&gt;Atlas Consulting Internatonal&lt;/a&gt;” to facilitate life as a freelance data scientist and consultant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spent a lot of time working at the cafe in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IKEA&lt;/span&gt; because my co-working space wouldn’t let me stay late or work on public holidays&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduced myself to this &lt;a href="http://haarlemoffice.nl"&gt;new coworking space&lt;/a&gt; and suggested we could work together to create the best tech-focussed startup hub and coworking space in the Netherlands. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bought our first car. It required a lot more time and research than I expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Created &lt;a href="http://www.texnidata.com"&gt;Texni Data Consultancy&lt;/a&gt; with Dan Caputo to provide data strategy consultancy services. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Built the website for &lt;a href="http://www.texnidata.com"&gt;Texni Data&lt;/a&gt; using django and deployed it to Heroku with a custom domain name. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deployed a django app to &lt;a href="https://cloud.google.com"&gt;Google Cloud Platform&lt;/a&gt; using &lt;a href="https://cloud.google.com/appengine/"&gt;App Engine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Created a &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu"&gt;business website&lt;/a&gt; to represent my work as a freelance data scientist and made my &lt;a href="https://blog.johnmathews.eu"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; a subdomain of this site. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moved my blog off of github pages and onto &lt;a href="https://firebase.google.com"&gt;firebase&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks Github for several years of simple trouble free hosting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experimented with using storage buckets on Google Cloud Platform to host static sites and serve them over &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSL&lt;/span&gt;. My conclusion is that serving static sites using storage buckets is great - it’s simple, quick and cheap (free). But adding &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSL&lt;/span&gt; proved too difficult. I spent too many hours trying to create a loadbalancer that would work for both the root domain &lt;a href="https://johnmathews.eu"&gt;johnmathews.eu&lt;/a&gt; and also a subdomain &lt;a href="https://blog.johnmathews.eu"&gt;blog.johnmathews.eu&lt;/a&gt;. In the end I found out about firebase. Firebase is also quick and cheap (free) and simple enough to pick-up quickly. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Created a photo book using &lt;a href="https://www.photobox.co.uk"&gt;PhotoBox&lt;/a&gt; that turned out great. It covers the last 3.5 years and is mostly full of snapshots of our kids and selfies with Ritsya.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chose a primary school for my daughter to go to next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Social"/><category term="Freelance"/></entry><entry><title>Coworking in Dublin</title><link href="https://johnmathews.eu/coworking.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2017-09-15T11:55:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-09-15T11:55:00+02:00</updated><author><name>John Mathews</name></author><id>tag:johnmathews.eu,2017-09-15:/coworking.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A review of eight coworking spaces in&amp;nbsp;Dublin&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week I arrived in Dublin and had two days to find a coworking space. I ran around Dublin visiting as many as possible. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m looking to rent a hotdesk, which means I don’t have any storage space at the office and I don’t have a particular desk. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are my impressions of eight businesses offering either hot desks or dedicated desks, ranked in order of preference. It’s subjective. The going rate in Dublin seems to be €200 — €300 per month for a hot desk. Hours range from 9am - 7pm Monday - Friday, to 24/7. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="first-place-dogpatch-labs"&gt;First place: &lt;a href="http://dogpatchlabs.com/"&gt;Dogpatch Labs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dogpatch offer a coworking space and access to a community of tech startups. They run regular networking and mentoring events and occupy 3 floors of a warehouse next to an old dock. The offices have a range of interiors styles. The middle level is fairly standard but pleasant open plan offices, the top floor is a flexible working space with event areas. The lower level is a series of vaults that each contain meeting rooms of various sizes. There’s a lot going on and there’s a good buzz in the air. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The range of interior spaces is a big plus for me and I’m looking forward to being able to switch up my working environment through the day. There’s a couple of kitchen areas, and a table football and table-tennis table on the top level. Access is 6am - midnight, and a hot desk is €200 per month. A dedicated desk is €400. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dogpatch occupy less than a quarter of the warehouse building, the remainder of the space is used as a shopping mall and a museum. In my opinion Dogpatch is by far the best value and if you’re working in tech it’ll probably be your go-to solution. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="second-place-studio9"&gt;Second place: &lt;a href="http://studio9.ie/?page_id=223"&gt;Studio9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These guys are great. The space is a lot smaller that Dogpatch, comprising only ~12 desks. It’s a basement, but don’t let that put you off — its open plan and has large windows at either end. The space is well designed and uses a lot of light colours and textures, including wood on the walls and floors. There are also plenty of pot plants. These combine to give a bright and airy atmosphere that feels very natural and bright.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are alcoves down one side of the main room which serve as meeting rooms, and a garden and basic kitchen at the back. The owners want the space to foster a community, and I expect that this is achieved. There are no dedicated offices and no teams using multiple desks, everyone is an independent worker. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The desks are large, and each has its own little wall to provide some privacy. €200 per month ongoing, or €250 for just one month. They offer a trial day for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="third-place-officesuites"&gt;Third place: &lt;a href="http://www.officesuites.ie/locations/20-harcourt-street/"&gt;OfficeSuites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The building looks well run and appears clean and fresh with adequate resources. The building is an old Georgian tenement with high ceilings, cornicing and lots of natural light. The furnishings and decor lean towards corporate rather than something more interesting, but this works well to add a professional feel to the homely architecture. Access is 24/7. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s only two rooms for hotdesking, and most of the building is given to private offices. There’s a garden with bike storage, meeting rooms and a quiet room for calls. Lockers are extra. They also offer a free day as a trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;€249 p/m for desk access 9am-7pm Monday - Friday&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="fourth-place-element78"&gt;Fourth place: &lt;a href="https://www.element78.co/"&gt;Element78&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friendly and well resourced, but very corporate. The architecture is corporate glass and steel. They’re situated on the ground floor in a posh business district with large financials for neighbours. It’s too corporate for me, but if you wanted an impressive place to meet clients and a nice address, this could be it. There were about 15 hot-desks for rent, plus plenty of dedicated desks. Clients seemed to include mostly young tech companies and tech freelancers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m hoping to find somewhere with more of a community, more inspiring architecture, and more character. I was offered a free day as a trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;€200 for the first month then €350 p/m&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="fifth-place-glandore"&gt;Fifth place: &lt;a href="https://glandore.co/flexible-workspace.aspx#Hot-Desk"&gt;Glandore&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Glandore offer a relatively luxurious package with a corporate feel. They have a few buildings in Dublin and only the flagship has hotdesking space. There’s a super looking restaurant and a large club room to relax in, but these are features that I don’t need, and the rates aren’t competitive if all you need is a desk and somewhere to take calls. It’s set up for teams and for impressing clients, and independent tech workers are probably better off elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;€295 p/m &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sixth-place-regus"&gt;Sixth place: &lt;a href="https://www.regus.ie/office-space/ireland/dublin/dublin-4-ballsbridge"&gt;Regus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regus offer a polished on boarding experience and the friendly staff were quick to respond and generally helpful, but the office space was bland, grey and generic. The rooms I visited didn’t have external windows and it reminded me of the rooms banks often put auditors in. If grey walls and tube lights are your thing then this is for you.  24/7 access, and meeting rooms equipped with A/V.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;€299.70 p/m.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="seventh-place-cocreate"&gt;Seventh place: &lt;a href="http://www.cocreate.ie/"&gt;CoCreate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I visited the southern branch and thought the building was a bit shabby and needed a new layer of paint. I recognised the desks as some of the cheapest available from &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IKEA&lt;/span&gt;. The rooms were small and needed cleaning, and there was weird art on the wall. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thought of paying €200 a month to sit at a small wobbly desk put me off. The place was also almost deserted. Maybe their other branch is better, but this is not for me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;€220 p/m. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="last-place-tcube"&gt;Last place: &lt;a href="http://tcubedublin.com/tcube/index.html"&gt;tCube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last and least, tCube seems to be putting in zero effort. When I visited I saw two rooms that needed painting, disorganised furniture and abandoned bits of computers lying around. The kitchen isn’t high spec and the meeting room isn’t big enough. I was also given a speech about how great the wifi was - a prerequisite that was taken for granted everywhere else. At €300 p/m for a dedicated desk its easy to find better value elsewhere. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Non-technical/Social"/><category term="Freelance"/><category term="Coworking"/><category term="Dublin"/><category term="Element78"/><category term="Regus"/><category term="OfficeSuites"/><category term="CoCreate"/><category term="Studio9"/><category term="Glandore"/><category term="tCube"/></entry></feed>